<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Cold Chain Equipment Inventory (CCEI) System - Service Module</title>
  <section>
    <title>Service Module: Cold Chain Equipment Inventory (CCEI)</title>
    <section>
		<title>Meta Data</title>
		<para>In cold chain Equipment Inventory, the super user has to define the metadata in the application.</para>
		<para>To define model, the super user has to create attributes for model and then add the attributes with its model. The model here for say refrigerator and freezers and the attributes are capacity, dimension etc. The super user can add more models.</para>
		<para>The model indicates the model name, for say Electrolux FG 432. To add a new model, select the model type and then add model.</para>
		<para>Equipment Type Indicates the equipment for say Refrigerator, Cold Box, Cold Room etc. Equipment type has a particular model but equipment have machine specific data with addition to the general data which is common among the models. In order to record the equipment specific data, the super user has to define attributes for the equipment for say Unique ID, Serial No, manufacturer etc. User can add many numbers of attributes for equipment.</para>
		<para>To add a new equipment type for say it is refrigerator and freezers, add it and select model for refrigerator and freezer. It will enable to pull data from selected model and also additional data which are specific to refrigerator and freezer by using equipment attributes.</para>
		<para>In summary metadata defines
		<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data about model attribute</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data about model</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data about equipment type attribute </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data about equipment type</para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
	</section>
  </section>
 </chapter>
	