<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using Event Report</title>
  <section>
    <title>Event Report overview</title>
    <para>The event report app enables analysis of events in two fashions.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Pivot table-style analysis with aggregated values of events</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Lists of events based on queries / filters</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Pivot tables with aggregated values</title>
      <para>By selecting "Aggregated values" from the top-left menu you can use the event reports
        app to create pivot tables with aggregated numbers of events. An event report is always
        based on a program. You can do analysis based on a range of dimensions. Each dimension can
        have a corresponding filter. Dimensions can be selected from the left-side menu and includes
        the following:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data elements</emphasis>: Start by selecting the program and
            program stage for the event report. The data elements associated with the selected
            program will be listed under available items. Each data element acts as a dimension, and
            can be selected by double-clicking on it. After selecting a data element, it will be
            visible under "selected data items". Here you can specify a filter for each data
            element, with operators such as "greater than", "in" or "equal" together with a filter
            value.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Periods</emphasis>: For the period dimension you have three
            options: relative periods, fixed periods and start/end dates. Relative periods can e.g.
            be "last 12 months", and has the advantage that it keeps the data in the report up to
            date as time goes. Fixed periods can e.g. be "January 2014". You can swith to start/end
            dates by selecting from the drop-down menu under the periods tab, which lets you specify
            flexible dates for the time span in the report.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Organisation units</emphasis>: The organisation unit dimension
            lets you select any org unit from the hierarchy. You can use the org unit mode selector
            to select org units explicitly, by org unit hierarchy levels and by org unit
            groups.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/event_report/event_report.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>By clicking <emphasis role="bold">Layout</emphasis> from the top menu you can control
        which dimensions should appear as columns, rows and filters in the pivot table. Note that
        each data element appears as individual dimensions and can each be placed on any of the
        axis.</para>
      <para>Note as data elements of continuous value types (real numbers/decimal numbers) can only
        be used as filters, and will automatically be positioned as filters in the layout dialog.
        The reason for this is that continuous number cannot be grouped into sensible ranges and
        used on columns and rows.</para>
      <para>Event reports can be saved as favorites by clicking on "Favorites" in the top menu.
        Favorites can later be restored by clicking on them in the list of favorites.</para>
      <para>Event reports can be downloaded in various popular formats by clicking on the "Download"
        button on the top menu.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Event queries</title>
      <para>By selecting "Individual cases" fromt the top-left menu you can use the event reports
        app to make searches or queries for events based on a flexible set of criteria. The report
        will be displayed as a table with one row per event. Each dimension can be used as a column
        in the table or as a filter. Each dimension can have a criteria (filter). Data elements of
        type option set allows for "in" criteria, where multiple options can be selected. Numeric
        values can be compared to filter values using greater than, equal or less than
        operators.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Options</title>
      <para>An event report can be customized using a range of options, which can be accessed by
        clicking on "Options" in the top menu. The following options apply to aggregated values-type
        reports only:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Show totals: Show totals at the end of each column and row in the pivot
            table.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Show sub-totals: Show sub-totals for each column and row in the pivot table.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Hide empty rows: Hide empty rows in the pivot table.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Limit: Set a limit on the max number of rows to display in the table, combined with
            a setting for showing top or bottom values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Show hierarchy: Include the names of all parents of each organisation unit in
            labels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>These style-related options apply to both types of reports:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Display density: Control padding around values inside cells.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Font size: Control font size of values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Digit group separator: Control character to use for splitting digit groups.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
