<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>DHIS Mobile</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>DHIS2 provides a range of options to allow data entry from mobile devices, including a dedicated GPRS/3G J2ME client, a SMS based client, and a version of DHIS2 which has been optimized specifically for mobile browsers. Each of these solutions will be described in detail in the following sections.</para>
    <para>Collection of data in the field can be technically challenging and expensive. Mobile phone
      solutions has the potential to significantly reduce the complexity of deploying a distributed
      data collection system. Using a simple Java client installed on a mobile phone or a web browser which works on the mobile phone, field workers
      can report directly to the DHIS2 database through their mobile device.</para>
    <para>While mobile phone solutions have a great potential, it is also an area that can be
      difficult to &quot;get right&quot;. Phones lack processing power and have a small display,
      need to be
      charged and often makes the most sense in areas where mobile network coverage is weak and
      patchy.</para>
    <para>There are currently three main mobile solutions for DHIS2, and we continue to evolve these
      as well as look at other possible solutions:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An mobile browser optimized data entry module</para>
        <para>This module allows for data entry directly with the browser of the mobile device. A wide range of devices and mobile browsers  are supported including: Opera mini 3 &amp; 4 (basic and advanced)
   - Opera mini 4,  Nokia S40 mobiles ,Windows Phone 7, Window Mobile 6
   ,Palm Pre
   ,Blackberry (v5 and v6)
   , Firefox mobile, iOS devices (iPhone)
    and  Android devices. An active GPRS/3G connection is required. This solution is described in <xref linkend="mobile_broswer_based"/></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A dedicated J2ME GPRS/3G client</para>
        <para>This solution  allows  for forms to be updated on the phone and also supports
          community module reporting. An active GPRS/3G connection is required in order to send data to the DHIS2 database, but data can be entered offline and transmitted when a connection is present. This client is intended primarily for low-end devices which support J2ME applications. This solution is described in <xref linkend="mobile_j2me_gprs_client"/></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>SMS based solution</para>
        <para>The SMS based solution is 
          requires a custom built J2MER mobile application
          and installation of a GSM modem and some manual
          configuration on the server side. It would be an appropriate solution where GPRS/3G is not available but GSM coverage is available. Updating of forms to the client is not supported at this point in time. This solution is described in <xref linkend="mobile_sms_based_data_entry"/></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="dhis2_user_man_mobile_web_based.xml" encoding="UTF-8"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="dhis2_mobile_sms_data_entry.xml" encoding="UTF-8"/>
</chapter>
