<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Name-Based Information Tracking Module</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
      <title>Quick Background</title>
      <para>Conventionally, Public Health Systems have been recording and reporting aggregated data of the services provided across various health programmes. Though this is crucial in monitoring &quot;<emphasis role="italic">reach</emphasis>&quot; and &quot;<emphasis role="italic">availability</emphasis>&quot; of public health services, but it lacks tracing the persons being provided these services and quality of these ones. </para>
      <para>For example, the aggregate report will show that 300 pregnant women registered  for ANC and 120 women given IFA tablets or 90 women given TT injection. In an aggregate system, it is not possible to ascertain that if a particular pregnant woman registered for ANC, has also been given IFA and TT, as data only shows aggregate numbers. To understand the quality of services given to each pregnant woman registered for ANC, immunization cycle of each child or treatment of each leprosy person, etc. it is important that treatment information of each person is maintained as an individual case.</para>
      <para>The DHIS name-based information tracking module ( also known as  DHIS Community Module  ) is an integrated module in DHIS2, built to support community health systems and facilitate a smooth integration between the community health data and aggregated data management.</para>
      <para>The module supports management of community health programs, such as child immunization, maternal health and e.g. allows tracking of individuals enrolled in various programs and activity planning for community health workers.</para>
      <para>The following are the major things:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Administrating meta data -  includes person attributes, person attribute groups, identifier types; relationship types, health programs,  program stages corresponding to the program, validations and formulas  for aggregating data value from individual cases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Administrating person registration - registering a new person, setting relationships,  enrolling a person into a program and management of person location</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data entry for inputting individual data for treatment  of each person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reports for individual cases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activity plans.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Linking data between name-based information tracking system   and aggregate management system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages of Name Based Information Tracking:</emphasis></para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate the health service provider  in person&apos;s treatment follow-up by recording all treatment related information in one place and in effective monitoring of different health services and drill down to individual person information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help the person in recording treatment history in one place, which could be used later in case of referral.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate in recording entire treatment information of each person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help strengthen the quality and fidelity of data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The data in primary registers at sub-center level is recorded and maintained by name based individuals or treatment cases, and  sent up-wards as aggregate reports.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Working of Name Based Information Tracking</title>
      <para>The module supports health providers for registering treatment cases and tracks these cases over time through different forms that are filled for the treatment of each person.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Registration a person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Program enrollment</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activity plans</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Treatment cases for a person</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Registration a person</title>
        <para>The process of  creating a new person in the system is through the registration process. The person is first registered in the system (or checked if the person already exists in system). Searching a person can be done through name, identifiers,  location or user-defined person&apos;s attributes (address, phone number, e.g.). If the person already exists in the system, the program enrollment process can continue. If the person is not available,  new registration takes place. </para>
        <para>The system supports for creating identifier type for the registration, such as Passport number, PAN, driving license, health identifier, UID. However, a system unique identifier is created automatically after registration and used to track the person.</para>
        <para>For identification a person, the health worker is first identified through any of the identifiers or name of patient  in the system and the person is identified through identifiers for receiving a health service. After identification, the individual case history can be viewed or a treatment case can be updated for  the new visit that they have received.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Program Enrollment and Activity Plan</title>
        <para>When a person is enrolled into any health programme, the person is  provided various services through the treatment are recorded. Based on the services of the program by the time, the system creates an activity plan for person.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Treatment case</title>
        <para>Each interaction with the person related to the case is considered to be an treatment case and these cases are recorded into the individual case. Individual case is updated with the identification of both the health worker and the person who is receiving the service.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Individual Person user guide</title>
    <section>
      <title>Starting the application</title>
      <para>To use the online NBITS application, in client computer which is connected to Internet, launch web browser ( use of <emphasis role="italic">Mozilla Firefox</emphasis> browser is recommended ).</para>
      <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Firefox-icon.png" align="center"/></para>
      <para>Once you have started NBITS online, the displayed screen will prompt you to enter your registered &quot;<emphasis role="italic">Username</emphasis>&quot; and &quot;<emphasis role="italic">Password</emphasis>&quot;. After entering the required information, click <emphasis role="italic">Login</emphasis> button to log into the application.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure 2.1.1</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.1.1.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>After clicking  the <emphasis role="italic">Login</emphasis> button, you will be directed to the <emphasis role="italic">Welcome</emphasis> screen of the NBITS:</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure 2.1.2</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.1.2.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Modules in NBITS</title>
      <para>The NBITS application is an online application and developed as open source application. The application is platform independent and can be easily linked with other open source application. The application is developed on the similar DHIS framework and it has three basic modules as follows - </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maintenance  module</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Services module</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help module</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>There are some additions in the NBITS in both maintenance and services module. <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> module has one additional sub module for the beneficiary registration and <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> module  has one additional sub-module for name-based data entry and recording.</para>
      <para>The modules provide three main functionalities -</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Processes of case tracking in NBITS.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reports.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Processes of case tracking in NBITS</title>
      <para>The NBITS application is developed with the objective of tracking cases of any disease or condition by using this application. The process of tracking starts with the registration of cases in the application. Application can provide information for only those cases which are available in the database, so the first process is the registration of beneficiary in the NBITS application. Once the beneficiary is registered, she/he can be enrolled in the program for which registered. The application will guide the health provider for the services required by the beneficiary through activity plan and the services received by the beneficiary from time to time can be updated into his/her profile.  The working process of the application can be understood in steps depicted in picture below - </para>
      <para><screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.1</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.1.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>
      <section>
        <title>STEP 1: Beneficiary registration</title>
        <para>The First step in the tracking is the registration of beneficiary/case in the NBITS application. In the registration process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contact and location details &amp; health provider details, are entered in the application. In the registration itself, beneficiary is provided with the unique identification number. This number will be unique and will not match with the identification number of any person in the state jurisdiction. The issue of identification number will be the responsibility of facility where the beneficiary is registered first time.</para>
        <warning>
          <para>Any case irrespective of the program will be registered first and then will be enrolled in any of the program. E.g. every pregnant women and the child need to be registered first as a beneficiary, than the beneficiaries will be enrolled in Mother Care program or Child Health program.</para>
        </warning>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">
              <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">
            <emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="underline"> of Beneficiary registration Process in application</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis> - </para>
        <para>For the registration process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contact and location details, and health provider details, are entered.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To register a beneficiary in the application, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, select option <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis>.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.2</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.2.png" format="CGM-CLEAR"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.3</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.3.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Now click the <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary</emphasis> option to go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Registration</emphasis> window.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.4</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.4.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click  the concerned facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen. Then click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button on the right side.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.5</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.5.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start process of registration by providing name, location details, identification details, contact details and health provider details.  The  click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button (arrow in RED color, fig. 2.3.6,  given at the end of beneficiary registration ) to complete to process of registration.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.6</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.6.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <para>To check the duplicates or to avoid double registration, after providing name and demographic details, click  the <emphasis role="italic">Check duplicate</emphasis> button ( arrow in BLUE color, fig. 2.3.6 ).   Checking process bases on full name, gender and birthday of   the registering beneficiary to look for  the  available beneficiaries  with the similar information  in the database. If    the system finds out the same  beneficiaries ,  the   result list will be displayed. Now user can cancel the registration process and update the existing beneficiary or  continue the process of registration.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>STEP 2 - Beneficiary Enrolment</title>
        <para>After the beneficiary registration, beneficiary needs to be enrolled in any available program  in the application and for which she/he has been registered. To enrol -</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click  the <emphasis role="italic">Manage Program Enrollment </emphasis>icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the beneficiary you would like to modify.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.7</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.7.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a program from the list  ( i.e., Mother Care Program, Child Health Program... )</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.8</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.8.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <warning>
              <para>This task can be executed after register successfully, a  form like Fig. 2.3.8. is  showed up for enrolment.
</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>After the selection of program, you need to provide two dates -</para>
            <para>1) Date of Enrolment: The date of registration of the beneficiary with a facility.</para>
            <para>2) Date of Incidence:  The date when the beneficiary got the disease or he/she has just been committed to an equivalent program for being followed-up.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.9</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.9.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <warning>
              <para>The date of incidence and date of enrollment are very important to generate the activity plan for  each beneficiary. Health provider  needs to ensure  recording and reporting date of incidence with each case.</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click  the <emphasis role="italic">Enroll</emphasis> button to complete the enrollment process.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.10</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.10.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <para>The application will automatically calculate  due-date for each the program stage  and will show same below enrollment. In the health programs, an beneficiary registered and enrolled into the system, needs to be checked from time to time by service providers.
The case update in the  application is designed in the same manner so that services which are received by the beneficiaries can be updated from time to time  when they visit the facility  or  whenever they are visits by the health providers. </para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.11</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.11.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>STEP 3 – Inputting data in treatment stages for each beneficiary</title>
        <para>We have two functionalities which support to  input data in  treatment stages for each beneficiary.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Single data entry.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Multiple data entry.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <section>
          <title>Single data entry</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>From the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> option, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click  it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.12</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.12.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 3.3.14</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.13.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Selection of a beneficiary and individual case</para>
              <para>In order to enter data, you  first have to select the facility for which beneficiaries belong to in order to enter data. Simply clicking  the concerned facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen.</para>
              <para>The next step is searching beneficiaries. Select a program in <emphasis role="italic">program</emphasis> list. The beneficiary list by the selected facility is shown. Each beneficiary in the list is shown with each corresponded stages.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.14</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.14.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Entering data for treatment case</para>
              <para>To open treatment form, click the <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the beneficiary you would like to enter data.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.15`</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.15.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Selection of the Program and Program Stage</para>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">What is program stage ?</emphasis> - This is to handle specific stages of a health program  because of  having multiple encounters for a given health program. E.g. once a pregnant woman enrolls to the &quot;ANC Program&quot;, she will get examination and treatments for the first trimester, the second trimester and/or the third trimester. These encounters in most cases are mandatory, and there will be dropouts in some cases, in which a pregnant woman should go through after she enrolled in the &quot;ANC Program&quot;. So the specific stages of the health program are defined when a health program is created/specified.</para>
              <para>Select the program and the program stage which you want to enter data for the selected beneficiary, then provide the <emphasis role="italic">Report Date</emphasis>  to open   the data entry form.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.16</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.16.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <para>After filling data into the data entry form, click on the <emphasis role="italic">Complete data entry</emphasis> button to complete the  data filling process for this stage.</para>
              <warning>
                <para>During each stage, the section related to that particular stage will be enabled for data entry form, rest of the sections will remain disabled in that particular stage. E.g. if data entry form of ANC registration stage is selected, then only data elements of ANC registration stage  will be enabled and the rest of the data elements of other stages will remain disabled.</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Multiple Data Entry for beneficiaries</title>
          <para>This is an advanced function for data entry. On the same interface on above, many beneficiaries are listed for  entering data by stages. </para>
          <para>To access the multiple beneficiary data entry module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Multiple Data Entry</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.1.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 1 - Show beneficiary list</emphasis>. You will first have to select the facility for which beneficiaries belong to in order to enter data. Simply clicking on the concerned facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen. The next step is listing all beneficiaries by the certain program as follows -</para>
          <para>1) Select a program in <emphasis role="italic">program</emphasis> list. The beneficiary list by the selected facility and program is shown. Each beneficiary in the list is shown with each corresponded stages.</para>
          <para>2)  Select an option from <emphasis role="italic">Sort by</emphasis>  box to sort by beneficiary&apos;s attributes.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 2 - Open treatment form</emphasis>. </para>
          <para>See the below figure illustrates for beneficiary named <emphasis role="italic">Nguyen Van Nam</emphasis>  and the second stage with name  <emphasis role="italic">At 6 weeks after birth</emphasis>.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.3</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.3.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para><screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.2</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.2.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 3 - Enter data</emphasis> ( arrow <emphasis role="italic">labelled 1</emphasis> in Fig. 2.5.3.3  ). After finishing the entering, close the pop-up ( arrow <emphasis role="italic">labelled 2</emphasis> in Fig. 2.5.3.3 )</para>
          <para>The benefits of this advanced function is to optimize the time-transition consuming when entering data for a long list beneficiaries by not switching the main window/interface.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Report Generation</title>
      <para>This module provides two main functions, include NBITS Activity Plan report and NBITS Summary report.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NBITS Activity Plan report - This report is a feedback report to the facilities to help them in planning activities. This is also called as activity plan or visit plan. Basically, view the visit plan to get an overview of outstanding, pending, and completed visits. </para>
          <para>See the illustration for Immunization program for Children under 1yr old.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.17</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.17.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>Each card ( see above Fig. 2.3.17 ) present a coming stage information for a beneficiary of a program.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NBITS Summary report - View the summary report to get an overview of the services provided for a program.</para>
          <para>See an example -</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.18: Each row is a summary of stages of the Immunization program for Children under 1yr old</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.18.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>The color highlight the status of the stages:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>PURPLE: Data entered and uncompleted stages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>RED: Stages open but no data entered while the date estimated for closing/completing is over.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>YELLOW: Coming stages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>GREEN: Compete stages.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder</title>
      <para>This is the core functionality for linking data between name-based information tracking system – NBITS ( beneficiaries, programs, etc ) and aggregate management system ( dataset, report, charts, etc.) by defining the linking/aggregating rules.</para>
      <para>This provides two functions - </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder</emphasis> is a tool for defining formula, expression, rules for aggregation data from name-based to aggregation system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Aggregation</emphasis> to used for generating routine data values from patient-data by month (or other interval if desired) and organization unit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder</title>
        <para>To access <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries Aggregation Query Builder</emphasis> module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.2</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.2.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>After click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button, the following will appear:</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.3</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.3.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 1:</emphasis>
          </emphasis> Provide the basic information for a query: description, aggregation data element from data element group.</para>
        <para>See the example (Fig. 2.5.4.3): description as <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis>,  and the result with be stored with data element as <emphasis role="italic">Number of Children - BCG</emphasis>  in data element group <emphasis role="italic">BCG Program</emphasis>.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">
              <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 2:</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis> </para>
        <para>Select the equivalent data element for the beneficiaries to link to the data element selected above. The information include: program, program stage and data element by the selected program stage.</para>
        <para>Double click on the data element the equivalent code of it will be showed in the condition box (labelled 4). An example of Fig. 2.5.4.3, if double click on the data element named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given date ((default))</emphasis> the code appear as <emphasis role="italic">[DE:8.75.1]</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>To make the condition valid, as default click on button “<emphasis role="italic">!=NULL</emphasis>”. Then there will be the text “<emphasis role="italic">[DE:8.75.1] is not null</emphasis>” in the Condition box.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 3:</emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <para>For adding and advanced condition for the query. So, it is required more knowledge about the health services of the programs specifically.</para>
        <para>All properties and options listed in this area are flexible and depend on the health program. And users can modify them.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">
              <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 4:</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <para>Includes the buttons of operands and a text box showing the conditions for the query.</para>
        <para>After finishing the area above (1, 2, 3 and 4), click on the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Beneficiary Aggregation</title>
        <para>To access <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries Aggregation</emphasis> module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name-Based Data Records</emphasis> option. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Aggregation</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed. Here are the main screen shots:</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.4</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.4.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.5</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.5.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Area in the ORANGE frame: the facility hierarchy tree. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Area in the BLUE frame: for choosing the data set, the start and end date of the aggregated period.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Click on the 
<emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> button to execute aggregate function.
</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.6 - Shows the result from the example</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.6.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>A Sample for Beneficiary Aggregation</title>
        <para>E.g.  Find the number of the children vaccinated BCG by defining a linking rule between the data elements of aggregate dataset named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis>  and the data element of a program stage named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given date</emphasis>.<orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Data Element and Indicators</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Element</emphasis> option to define two new data elements -</para>
              <para><itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Patient</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.2.1</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.2.1.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.2.2 - Define a data element with <emphasis role="italic">Patient</emphasis> option for <emphasis role="italic">Domain Type</emphasis>.</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.2.2.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.2.3 - <emphasis role="italic">Add Data Element </emphasis>form</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.2.3.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Datasets</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Dataset</emphasis> option to create a new dataset named <emphasis role="italic">BCG Report</emphasis> and add <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> data element into the dataset.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Benificaries and Programs</emphasis> option   and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis> option to create a program named <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis> with a stage named <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> and add the <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element into this stage.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Program </emphasis>option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary</emphasis> option to create three benificiaries named <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis> and enrol them into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Create a new Beneficiary Aggregation QueryBuilder named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG Builder </emphasis>to linking between the data elements.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.4</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.4.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Name-Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> option.</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Choose benificiary  <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis> and open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>. Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2011-02-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Choose benificiary  <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis> and open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into Child Health Program. Enter Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2011-02-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Choose benificiary   <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis> and no enter data value for <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage.</para>
                  <warning>
                    <para>Before entering data value for the stage, choose <emphasis role="italic">Report Date</emphasis> as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2011-02-28</emphasis>&quot;</para>
                  </warning>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to Name-Based Data Records option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Case Aggregation</emphasis> option to run<emphasis role="italic"> Number of children - BCG Builder</emphasis> to get data value  and save it into database.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.5</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.5.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.6 - Result after running the query builder</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.6.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Advanced functions</title>
      <para>The content in this part is for the expert users or administrative users who are capable and responsible for development and change</para>
      <section>
        <title>Define a beneficiary attribute</title>
        <section>
          <title>Define a beneficiary attribute</title>
          <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Attribute</emphasis> option to create a new attribute for beneficiaries. </para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.1.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.1.1.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>After, click on <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Attribute Management</emphasis> window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Beneficiary Attribute Management</emphasis> window.<screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.1.2</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.1.2.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot><screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.1.3</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.1.3.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
          <para>Basic information</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of beneficiary attribute.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Description of beneficiary attribute.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Mandatory</emphasis>: Entering value for this attribute is required or not.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Inheritable</emphasis>: </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of characters</emphasis>: Maximum number of characters for value inputed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Value Type</emphasis>: Data type of value inputed.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Define a beneficiary attribute group</title>
          <para>To access the beneficiary attribute group maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Attribute Group</emphasis> option to create a new an attribute group.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.2.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.2.1.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>To create a new attribute group, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Attribute Group</emphasis> window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Beneficiary Attribute Group</emphasis> window , click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill in the <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis> fields and then select attributes that should belong to the group from the left panel. </para>
          <para>Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected items</emphasis> button to add the selected attributes to the attribute group. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected items</emphasis> button to remove attributes from the group that have been selected in the right panel. </para>
          <para>Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes..</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.2.2</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.2.2.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Define a beneficiary identifier type</title>
        <para>To access the beneficiary identifier type maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Identifier Type</emphasis> option to create a new identifier type.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.2a</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.2a.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>To creating a  new identifier type, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Identifier Type Management </emphasis>window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Beneficiary Identifier Type</emphasis> window.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.2b</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.2b.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Basic information -</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of identifier type.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Description of identifier type.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Mandatory</emphasis>: Entering value for the  identifier is required or not.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Related</emphasis>: </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of characters</emphasis>: Maximum number of characters for value inputed. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Type</emphasis>: Data type of value inputted.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Define a relationship type</title>
        <para>Relationship type section provides a mechanism for defining any relationship types and link beneficiaries through these relationship types by creating specific relationships.</para>
        <para>To access the relationship type maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Relationship Type</emphasis> option to create a new relationship type.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.3a</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.3a.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>To define a new relationship type, click  <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Relationship Type Management </emphasis>window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add new Relationship Type</emphasis> window.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig 2.7.3b</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.3b.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Beneficiary Registration</title>
        <para>Beneficiary registration section provides a mechanism for managing facilities which allow to registry new beneficiaries or not.</para>
        <para>To access the beneficiary registration maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Registration</emphasis>  option to select facilities. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.4</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.4.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <warning>
          <para>There are two process for registering facilities. The first one is where the administrator will say which facility can register. The second is when end user logs in and then select a facility, system will display a waring message if the selected facility cannot register beneficiaries; else, the system will display the functions to register beneficiaries.</para>
        </warning>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Define a new program</title>
        <section>
          <title>Define a new program</title>
          <para>Program section provides a mechanism for defining a health program. All name based case entry is organised through the use of programs.

</para>
          <para>To access the program maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>  option to create a new program.</para>
          <para>To create a new program, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and then click the &quot;Add&quot; button.</para>
          <para><screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.1</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.1.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
          <para>Basic information :</para>
          <para><itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: The name of the program</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Descriptions, meanings, explanation, etc. of/about the program</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Date of Enrolment Description</emphasis>: The date in which a beneficiary is registered to the system.
For example: the date in which a beneficiary enrols to the system.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Date of Incidence Description</emphasis>: The date when the beneficiary got the disease or he/she has just been committed to an equivalent program for being followed-up. E.g. In the Immunization program for child under 1yr old, the incident date is the birthday; in the maternal program, the incident date is the date of last menstrual period (LMP).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of max days allowed to input data</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Define stages for a health program</title>
          <para>To define a program stage, click the <emphasis role="italic">Program Stage Management</emphasis>  icon (Fig. 2.5.1.2a) and then <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button  (Fig. 2.5.1.2b). Fill in the <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis> fields and then select the data elements that should belong to the group from the left panel. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected</emphasis> button to add the selected data elements to the right panel. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected</emphasis> button to remove data elements that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2a</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2a.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2b</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2b.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2c</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2c.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>Fig. 2.5.1.2c illustrates for stage named “<emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis>” of  “<emphasis role="italic">Child Health</emphasis>” program.
More explanation for the figure:</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="italic">
                <emphasis role="italic">
                  <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue frame labelled 1:</emphasis>
                </emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis></para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of the stage</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: The description of the stage</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Min no of days to wait from start of Program</emphasis>:  The minimum number of days to wait for starting the program</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>: The name of the program which is already defined before.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">
              <emphasis role="bold">
                <emphasis role="italic">
                  <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue arrow and labelled 2:</emphasis>
                </emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis></para>
          <para>Choose the data elements from the list on the left to the right one. These chosen elements are highlighted with BLUE color.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">
              <emphasis role="bold">
                <emphasis role="italic">
                  <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue arrow and labelled 3:</emphasis>
                </emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis></para>
          <para>Function area with button labeled “<emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis>”, see the arrow labelled 3 and in BLUE to execute the function.</para>
          <para>If successfully, the new stages will showed in the list of stages:</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2d</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2d.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>Your program will then be ready to be used to enroll beneficiaries (which are modified/created under <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance-&gt;Beneficiaries and Programs-&gt;Beneficiaries</emphasis>) and enter data under the data-entry function <emphasis role="italic">Services-&gt;Name Based Data Records-&gt;Data Entry</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">Multiple Data. Entry</emphasis> for the facilities that you have assigned.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Other functionalities</title>
          <para>You can assign the facilities to a program in the Program Management ( in which a list of available programs are shown) by clicking on the blue folder icon, which is the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the program you would like to modify.

</para>
          <para>The function <emphasis role="italic">Define Program Validation</emphasis> is designed for defining validations of a program in which you would like to modify after entering patient data values for program stages.

For instance, Parity, Previous live birth male, Previous live birth female, Previous still birth are patient data elements. They belong to many stages. And if data value of Parity is 0, then ( Previous live birth female + Previous still birth ) = 0. Besides, if a patient data element exists into many program stages, the system will check whether the values of the patient data element are in all program stages of the program or not.

For instance, TT1 is a patient data element. It exists into program stages as follows Checkup 1, Checkup 2, Checkup 3. If the data value of this data element into Checkup 1 is null, the data values into Checkup 2, Checkup 3 should be null.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Define validation criteria</title>
        <para>Validation criteria section provide a mechanism for defining criteria for beneficiaries when enrolling a program.

</para>
        <para>To access the validation criteria maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Validation Criteria</emphasis>  option to create a new program</para>
        <para>To create a new validation criterion, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and click <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button.

</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.6.6.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>You can assign facilities to a validation criterion in the <emphasis role="italic">Validation Criteria Management </emphasis>(list of available validation criteria are shown) by clicking the blue folder icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the validation criterion you would like to assign. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected</emphasis> button to add the selected programs to the validation criterion. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected</emphasis> button to remove programs from the group that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Save</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
