<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using Event Capture</title>
  <section>    
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The event capture app allows users to register events that occurred at a particular time
      and place. An event can happen at any given point in time. This stands in contrast to routine
      data, which can be captured for predefined, regular intervals. Events in DHIS 2 are linked to
      program. Hence, the event capture app lets you select the organisation unit, program and point
      in time when an event (also known as case or record) happened, before entering information for
      that event.</para>
    </section>
  <section>
    <title>Capturing events</title>
    <para>To capture an event, the first step is to select an organisation unit from the left-side
      organisation unit tree. After selecting an org unit, the list of programs will display the
      programs which have been associated with the selected organisation unit and which have been
      given access to the current user through user roles. Events are displayed in a tabular fashion
      as shown in the figure below. As seen in the screenshot, each row corresponds to an event. The
      columns display information about the events, more specifically they display data for data
      elements which are part of the program.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example event list</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/event_capture/event_list.png" format="JPG"
            width="70%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>All event related operations are accessible from the screen shown above. The operations
      currently available are: <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Capturing data: this available by clicking the "Register New Event" button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Showing/hiding colums: this is to allow users decide which columns to show/hide in
            the table of events. This feature is especially important when we have a long list of
            data elements assigned to a program stage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Editing - the rows in the table are clickable. Clicking them shows three menus -
              <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Edit in grid</emphasis>
            and <emphasis role="bold">Remove.</emphasis> The edit function takes you to a new page
            where information for the selected event can be updated. The edit in grid function
            allows you to edit the selected event within the table but only those columns (data
            elements) visible in the grid. If more columns are required it is possible to add using
            the "Show/Hide columns" button to speficy which columns should be displayed in the
            list.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sorting: this can be done by clicking the text of each column header.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Filtering: this is done by clicking the small search icon shown to the right of each
            column header. Clicking them provides an input field to type a filtering criteria. The
            system starts applying the filter the moment a user starts to type. During filtering it
            is possible to define start and end dates for date type data elements and lower and
            upper limits for number types.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Paging: The list of events can be paged by using the paging section at the bootom of
            the list. Paging allows you to quickly move between pages of events and to change the
            page size, i.e. the number of events per page.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
    <para>The event capture module works offline, in the sense that if Internet connectivity drops
      during your working session, you can continue to capture events which will be stored locally
      in your web browser (client). When connectivity has returned the system will ask you to upload
      your locally stored data, which sends the data to the Web server where it is stored. Note that
      if you close your Web browser while being disconnected from the Internet, you cannot return to
      your working session; however your data will still be saved locally and can be uploaded to the
      Web server the next time your are online and log into the system.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
