<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>User management</title>
  <para>DHIS2 allows for multiple users to access the system simultaneously, each with a defined set of permissions. These permissions can be finely tuned so that certain users can only enter data, while others may generate reports. Multiple user roles can be created, each with their own set of permissions, and then assigned to users which grant them certain privileges within the system. This chapter describes how to manage users and user roles.</para>
  <section id="creating_new_users">
    <title>Creating new users and roles</title>
    <para>This section will describe how to add new users and manage existing users to the DHIS2 application. You can create as many user names as you need. Each user can be assigned certain privileges, and can be assigned to certain organisation units for which they will be enabled to enter data on behalf of. To access the user module, choose <emphasis role="italic">Users</emphasis> from the Apps menu and then click &quot;User&quot; from the menu items on the left-hand pane.</para>
    <section id="user_maintenance">
      <title>User maintenance</title>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Select Users menu item</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/select_user_menu.png" format="PNG" align="center" width="80%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>User acconts already registered will appear as a list as seen below.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Search by user name</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/search_user_by_name.png" format="PNG" align="center" width="80%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>You can search for specific user names in the user list by entering the name in the
          <emphasis role="italic">Filter by name</emphasis> field as shown above. Some non-standard
        functions are available by clicking on each user in the list:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Replicate: This will create an exact copy of the user. You will be asked to enter
              a new username and password for the replicated account.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Disable: This will disable the user, meaning that the account is not deleted, but
              the user will not be able to log in or use it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section id="user_user_roles">
      <title>User role management</title>
      <para>As part of creating a user name you are required to define the user
      role. Do so by clicking on <emphasis role="italic">User Role</emphasis> on the left side of
      the displayed screen. This will lead you to the User role management page where you can
      click on <guibutton>Add new</guibutton> to create a new role.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Add new user role</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/add_user_role.png" format="PNG" width="80%" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>The following screen will open and here in the first text box you
      need to give a <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> of the Role such as Super User,      Admin User, etc. The
      second text box called <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis> gives more information about the
      type of User Role that is being created for e.g. State Admin User,
      District Data Entry.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Role maintenance page</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/role_maintenance_page.png" format="PNG" wordsize="" width="80%" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Next you will specify the particular data set(s) that are to be
      made available to the particular role. You will also need to specify the
      type of <emphasis role="italic">Authority</emphasis> to be given to the particular user. For each of the
      three options namely Datasets, Reports and Authorities user can select
      multiple options from the scroll down menu provided against each field.
      A user can choose multiple options either by moving them
      one-by-one.</para>
      <para>In order for particular users to be able to enter data, you must
      add them to both a dataset as well as an organisational unit level. You
      can also select multiple datasets individually by pressing the Ctrl key
      on the keyboard and clicking on individual datasets.</para>
      <para>Finally when you have entered the required fields click on
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> which is located on the lower part of the
      displayed screen. The desired user role and related authorisation will
      be saved to the database, and can then be assigned to a particular
      user.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="user_management">
      <title>User management</title>
      <para>Under particular user role there can be more than one user. To manage
      users, click on <emphasis role="italic">User</emphasis> on the left side of the screen.
      This will lead you to the <emphasis role="italic">User management</emphasis> page.</para>
      <para>To add a new user, follow these steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Add New</guibutton> button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose whether you want to fill in all the personal user information now, or invite the user by email to complete the
          rest of the user information:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Create account with user details</emphasis> - Choose this if you would like to enter all the details of the new user
              such as name, password, etc.</para>
              <para>If you choose this action, then enter the following information: username, password, surname, first name, E-mail,
              OpenID account (if any) and mobile phone number (if any).</para>
              <para>After you finish adding the user, the account will be ready for them to use with the username and password
              that you supply.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Select Users menu item</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/user_management_details.png" format="PNG" align="center" width="80%"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Email invitation to create account</emphasis> - Choose this if you would like to send by email an invitation for
              the user to return to the system and finish setting up their user account. The user will then return to the
              system and fill in most of their personal information. The account that the user finishes setting up will be limited according to how you configure it below.</para>
              <para>Note that you may not select this option to create an account with &quot;critical&quot; system authorities such as All, Scheduling Administration, Perform maintenance tasks, Merge organisation units, Eliminate duplicate data elements, Sql View Management, Change system settings, and List, Add or Delete user roles.</para>
              <para>If you choose this action, then enter the email address to which the invitation should be sent.
              If you want to, you may also enter the user name that the account will have. If you leave the username
              empty, then the user may choose their own username when they respond to the invitation (as long as it
              is not taken already for another user.)</para>
              <para>After you finish adding the new user, two emails will be sent to the address you provided. One contains
              a unique web link by which the user can return to the system and activate their account by entering the rest of their
              user information. The other email contains a unique code that they must enter into the system in order to
              complete the registration, after following the link in the first email. The user must finish setting up the account within three months, or the invitation
              becomes invalid.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Select Users menu item</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/user_management_invite.png" format="PNG" width="80%" align="center"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the <emphasis role="italic">Interface language</emphasis> for the user. You may choose a language into which fixed elements of the
          DHIS2 user interface have been translated.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the <emphasis role="italic">Database language</emphasis> for the user. You may choose a language into which implementation-supplied
          items have been translated in the database, for example data element names, organisation unit level names, etc.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Users must be assigned to at least one data capture and maintenance organisation unit. Users will
            have access to all children of the organisation units which have been assigned to
            them. For instance, if a user has been assigned to a district which has several
            facilities contained in the district, the user would have access to the district&apos;s data,
            as well as all of the facilities contained within the district. The data approval organisation
            units control for which organisation units the user can do data entry.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Users can be assigned to any number of data view organisation units. This controls
            which organisation units the user can view aggregated data for in analysis modules.
            Giving access to an organisation unit implicitly gives access to all organisation unit
            below it in the organisation unit hierarchy. Note that data view organisation units are
            optional. If you do not specify any, the user will have access to the full organisation
            unit hierarchy for viewing aggregated data.</para>
          <para>In several places in the analysis modules one can select &quot;user organisation unit&quot;
            for the organisation unit dimension. This mechanism will first attempt to use the data
            view organisation units linked to the current user. If not found, it will use the data
            capture organisation units.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>User management screen</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/user_management_fewer_options.png" format="PNG" align="center" width="80%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>(Click on <emphasis role="italic">Show more options</emphasis>.) You may optionally assign users to user groups on this page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>(Click on <emphasis role="italic">Show more options</emphasis>.) You may optionally restrict the values this user sees in data analytics
          by selecting dimensions that will restrict the users view. For example, let&apos;s say you have defined <emphasis role="italic">Implementing Partner</emphasis>
          as a category option group set, and you have shared with this user only one or more specific implementing partners
          (category option groups.) If you want to insure that the user does not see totals in analytics that include values
          from other groups, assign <emphasis role="italic">Implementing Partner</emphasis> to this user. This insures that any data visible to the user
          through DHIS2 analytics will be filtered to select only the Implementing Partner category option group(s) which
          are visible to the user.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>User management screen</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/user_management_more_options.png" format="PNG" align="center" width="80%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Click on the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to complete adding the new user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The recently created new user can be seen in main <emphasis role="italic">User management</emphasis> screen</para>
      <para>You can edit (like password, surname, etc.) and delete the
      details of new/old users by selecting corresponding User’s
      <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>
      menu options.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="user_by_org_unit">
      <title>User by organisation unit</title>
      <para>The <emphasis role="italic">User by organisation unit</emphasis> function allows you see which users have been assigned to a particular organisation unit. Simply select the organisation unit from the tree on the left, and a list of users which have been assigned to this particular organisation unit will be displayed</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>OpenID Support</title>
      <para>DHIS 2 supports the OpenID standard, which allows third party login using a OpenID
        provider, please see <ulink url="http://openid.net">http://openid.net</ulink> for more
        information. To create a custom OpenID URL for a username you can visit this URL and log in
        with your OpenID provider: <ulink url="http://openid-provider.appspot.com">http://openid-provider.appspot.com</ulink>.</para>
      <para>To enable support for this in DHIS 2, two steps must be done:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Set your OpenID provider</emphasis>: This can be done inside
              system settings, under &quot;Access&quot;. Here you can set both the OpenID provider, and also
              the label to display on the login page to login with this provider (defaults to Login
              with OpenID).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Set the OpenID identifier on the user</emphasis>: For every
              user that should be able to login with his openid identifier, you will need to set
              this on the user itself. This can be done in user management, under the email field,
              there is noe a field called <emphasis role="italic">OpenID</emphasis> which can be
              used to fill in the OpenID identifier. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
