<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Setting up GIS</title>
  <section>
    <title>Context</title>
    <para>Setting up the GIS simply means storing coordinates for the organisation units you want to show on the map in the database. Coordinates are  often distributed in  proprietary formats and will need to be converted to a format which DHIS2 understands. ESRI shapefiles are the most common geospatial vector data format for desktop applications. You might find shapefiles for your country <ulink url="http://www.diva-gis.org/gdata">here</ulink> or in many other geospatial data repositories on the web. Some amount of work needs to be done in order to use these coordinates in DHIS 2 GIS, namely transforming the data into a suitable format and ensuring the name which are contained in the geospatial data match exactly with the names of the organization units which they should be matched to. </para>
    <para>If you go to the organisation unit module and edit one of the units, you can see a text field called Coordinates. Here you may fill in its coordinates directly (geojson format) which is useful if you just want to update a couple of units.</para>
    <para>An example point/facility coordinate:</para>
    <para><programlisting><userinput>[29.341,-11.154]</userinput></programlisting></para>
    <para>An example polygon/area coordinates string:</para>
    <para><programlisting><userinput>[[[[29.343,-11.154],[28.329,-11.342],[28.481,-10.239],[29.833,-10.412]]]]</userinput></programlisting></para>
    <para>However, if you are going to e.g. add coordinates for all units at a certain level you don&apos;t want to do that manually. This is where the automatic GML import comes into play and the following section explains the preferred way of using it.<important>
        <para>The only co-ordinate reference system supported by DHIS2 is EPSG:4326, also known as
          geographic longitude/latitude. Coordinates must be stored with the longitude (east/west
          position) proceeding the latitude (north/south position). If your vector data is in a
          different CRS than EPSG 4326, you will need to re-project the data first before importing
          into DHIS2. </para>
      </important></para>
  </section>
  <section id="gisSetup">
    <title>Importing coordinates</title>
    <para>Step 1 - Simplify/generalize your geographical data</para>
    <para>The boundaries in geographical data files are usually very accurate, too much so for the
      needs of a web-based GIS. This usually does not affect the performance when using GIS files on
      a local system, but it is usually necessary to optimize the geographical data for the
      web-based GIS system of DHIS2. All geographical data needs to be downloaded from the server
      and rendered in a browser, so if the data is overly complex, the performance of the DHIS2 GIS
      will be negatively impacted. This optimization process can be described as follows:</para>
    <para><simplelist>
        <member>Coordinates: The number of significant decimal digits (e.g. 23.02937874993774) should be shortened to fewer digits (e.g. 23.03). Although this will result in some inaccuracies on the map, given the usual scale at which maps in DHIS2 are produced (&gt; 1:50,000), the loss of precision should not be noticeable. Normally, no more than four significant digits after the decimal point should be necessary.</member>
        <member>Polygons: In addition to shortening the number of significant digits, the actual number of points should also be reduced to an optimal level. Finding this optimal level may take a bit of experimentation. Decreasing the precision of the points as well as the number of points through generalization, will lead to degradation of the polygon. However, after a bit of experimentation, an optimal level of generalization can be found, where the accuracy of the polygon is visually acceptable, and the performance of the GIS is optimal. </member>
      </simplelist></para>
    <para>For polygons, we need to make the boundary lines less detailed by removing some of the line points. Make a backup of your shapefiles before you start. One possible method is the use of <ulink url="http://mapshaper.com/test/MapShaper.swf">MapShaper</ulink>   which is an online tool which can be used to generalize geographical data. To use MapShaper, simply upload your shapefile to the site. Then, at the center bottom you see a slider that starts at 0%. It is usually acceptable to drag it up to about 80%. In the left menu you can check &quot;show original lines&quot; to compare the result and you may want to give a different simplification method a try. When you are happy with the result, click &quot;export&quot; in the top right corner. Then check the first of the four options called &quot;Shapefile - polygons&quot;, click &quot;create&quot; and wait for the download buttons to appear. Now, download the two files to your local computer and overwrite the existing ones. Move on to the next step with your new simplified shapefile.
    </para>
    <para>Step 2 - Convert the shapefile to GML</para>
    <para>
      The recommended tool for geographical format conversions is called &quot;ogr2ogr&quot;. This should be available for most Linux distributions <command>sudo apt-get install gdal-bin</command>. For Windows, go to <ulink url="http://fwtools.maptools.org/">http://fwtools.maptools.org/ </ulink>and download &quot;FWTools&quot;, install it and open up the FWTools command shell. During the format conversion we also want to ensure that the output has the correct coordinate projection (called EPSG:4326 with geographic longitude and latitude). For a more detailed reference of geographic coordinates, please refer to this <ulink url="http://www.epsg-registry.org/">site</ulink>.  If you have already reprojected the geographic data to the geographic latitude/longitude (EPSG:4326) system, there is no need to explicitly define the output coordinate system, assuming that <command>ogr2ogr</command> can determine the input spatial reference system. Note that most shapefiles are using the EPSG:4326 system. You can determine the spatial reference system by executing the following command.</para>
    <para><programlisting><userinput>ogrinfo -al -so filename.shp</userinput></programlisting></para>
    <para>Assuming that the projection is reported to be EPSG:27700 by <command>ogrinfo</command>, we can transform it to EPSG:4326 by executing the following command.<programlisting><userinput>ogr2ogr -s_srs EPSG:27700 -t_srs EPSG:4326 -f GML filename.gml filename.shp </userinput></programlisting></para>
    <para>If the geographic data is already in EPSG:4326, you can simply transform the shapefile to GML by executing the following command. </para>
    <para><programlisting><userinput>ogr2ogr -f GML filename.gml filename.shp</userinput></programlisting></para>
    <para> You will find the created GML file in the same folder as the shapefile.
    </para>
    <para>Step 3 - Prepare the GML file</para>
    <para>Unfortunately, the GML file is not ready for importation yet. Open it in a robust text
      editor like Geany (Linux) or Notepad++ (Windows). GML is an XML based format which means that
      you will recognize the regular XML tag hierarchy. In the GML file an organisation unit is
      represented as a &lt;gml:featureMember&gt;. Inside the feature members we usually find a lot
      of attributes, but we are just going to import their coordinates.</para>
    <para>In order to import geospatial data from the feature members of the GML input, DHIS 2 must
      match each of them with an organisation unit in its database. The feature member element must,
      in other words, contain a reference to its corresponding organisation unit. The reference
      itself must be one of three possible DHIS 2 identifiers: <emphasis role="bold">uid</emphasis>,
        <emphasis role="bold">code</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis>. The
      identifier of choice must be provided as a property for each feature member element. The
      importer will look for a property with the local name of either <emphasis role="italic"
        >Uid</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Code</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"
        >Name</emphasis>, e.g. &quot;ogr:Name&quot; or &quot;anyPrefix:Code&quot;.</para>
    <para>If your feature members already contain a property of the identifier you wish to use (such
      as the name of an area) you can use search and replace in a text editor to rename these
      elements to a name DHIS 2 will recognize (see the below table). This is typically a workflow
      which is applicable when using the name as the identifier (the source shapefile or even GML
      will usually contain the name for each area it defines).</para>
    <para><table frame="all">
      <title>Organisation unit identifiers supported for GML import</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="newCol1"/>
          <colspec colname="c1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2"/>
          <colspec colname="c4"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Matching priority</entry>
              <entry>Identifier</entry>
              <entry>Valid spellings</entry>
              <entry>Guaranteed unique</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1</entry>
              <entry>Uid</entry>
              <entry>uid, Uid, UID</entry>
              <entry>Yes</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2</entry>
              <entry>Code</entry>
              <entry>code, Code, CODE</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3</entry>
              <entry>Name</entry>
              <entry>name, Name, NAME</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table></para>
    <para>In the case of renaming properties one would usually find a tag named something like
      &quot;ogr:DISTRICT_NAME&quot;, &quot;ogr:NAME_1&quot; and rename it to &quot;ogr:Name&quot;.
      If using the <emphasis role="italic">code</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">uid</emphasis>
      identifiers on the other hand, looking up the correct values in the DHIS 2 database and going
      through the GML file, adding the properties for each corresponding feature member might be
      necessary. In any of the cases it is important to realize that the identifier used must
        <emphasis role="bold">uniquely</emphasis> identify an organisation unit (e.g. if there are
      two organisation units in the database of the same name or code, these cannot be matched
      properly on either). As <emphasis role="italic">uid</emphasis> is the only
      guaranteed-to-be-unque identifier it is the most robust choice. However, as matching on name
      is usually easier (given that the name is already part of your data), a viable approach to
      solving uniqueness conflicts can be to match any non-uniquely named organisation units on a
      different identifier (uid, preferrably) and the rest on their names.</para>
    <para>As can be seen in the above table there is a matching priority, meaning is any two or more
      identifiers are provided for the same feature member, matching will be performed on the
      highest priority identifier. Note also the valid properties which can be used in you GML. The
      namespace prefix is not important as only the local name is used.</para>
    <para>A common pitfall of performing preparation of the GML files is syntax- or element naming
      errors. Therefore please make sure that all properties of the GML file are started and
      terminated with correctly corresponding tags. Also make sure the properties follow either of
      the given valid spellings of the property name. The identifying properties are supposed to
      look like e.g. &lt;ogr:Name&gt;Moyamba District&lt;/ogr:Name&gt;,
      &lt;somePrefix:uid&gt;x7uuia898nJ&lt;/somePrefix:uid&gt; or &lt;CODE&gt;OU_12345&lt;/CODE&gt;.
      Another common error is not making sure the identifier matches exactly, especially when using
      the <emphasis role="italic">name</emphasis> property. All matches are performed on exact
      values, meaning that &quot;Moyamba&quot; in a source GML file would not be matched against
      &quot;Moyamba District&quot; in the database.</para>
    <para>Have a brief look at the identifiers and compare them to the corresponding values in the
      database. If they seem to match fairly good, it is about time to do a preview in the
      import-export module. </para>
    <para>
      Go to Services -&gt; Import-Export, select &quot;Preview&quot;, select the GML file and click &quot;Import&quot;. Look for new/updated organisation units. Our intention is to add coordinates to already existing organisation units in the database, so we want as many updates as possible and 0 new. Those listed as new will be created as root units and mess up the organisation unit trees in DHIS 2. If any listed as new, click the number and the organisation units in question will appear in the list below. If there are any slight misspellings compared to the organisation unit names in the database - fix them and do the preview again. Otherwise, click the &quot;discard all&quot; button below the list and then the &quot;Import all&quot; button above the list.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the import process completes successfully, you should now be able to utilize the geographical data in the DHIS2 GIS. If not, check the log for hints and look for common errors such as:    
    </para>
    <para>- Name duplicates in the GML file. The name column in the database is unique and does not accept two organisation units with the same name.</para>
    <para>- The &quot;shortname&quot; column in the organisationunit table in your database has a too
      small varchar definition. Increase it to 100.</para>
    <para>- Special name characters in the GML file. Be sure to convert these to appropriate XML
      equivalents or escape sequences.</para>
    <para>- Wrongly formatted input GML, non-matching tags</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
