<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using GIS</title>
  <section>
    <title>Using the GIS module</title>
    <para>You can access the GIS module from the Services -&gt; GIS link in the top menu. The picture below shows the various panels you can use to interact with the map.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Main GIS screen</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_main.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <section id="gisThematicMap">
      <title>Thematic mapping</title>
      <para>The two thematic layer panels let you use your data for thematic mapping. All you need to do is selecting your desired indicator/dataelement-period-map combination. Then click either boundary or level to open the organisation unit selection window. Here you are supposed to select the parent organisation unit and the level of its children. If your database has coordinates for these organisation units they will appear on the map.</para>
      <para>You may choose between legend types: <guimenuitem>automatic</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>predefined</guimenuitem>. Automatic means that the application will create a legend set for you based on your what method, number of classes, low color and high color you select. Method alludes to the size of the legend classes. Set to <guimenuitem>Equal intervals</guimenuitem> they will be “highest map value – lowest map value / number of classes”. Set to <guimenuitem>Equal group count</guimenuitem> the legend creator will try to distribute the organisation units evenly. Choose <guimenuitem>Fixed bounds </guimenuitem>and you may define your own class break values, type e.g. “20,40,60” using a comma to separate each of them. The legend will appear as an even gradation from the start color to the end color. Predefined legend sets are described in section 1.4.</para>
      <para>Low radius and high radius only have effect on points (facilities) and decides the the circle radius for points with the lowest and highest value.</para>
      <para>The map view combo box lists all map views (favorites) saved by the user. The settings that are stored in the map view is automatically applied to the thematic map panel.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Thematic mapping</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_thematic_mapping.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section id="gisSymbolicMap">
      <title>Symbolic mapping</title>
      <para>This layer displays icons that represent facilities based on the facility type. Currently, <guimenuitem>type</guimenuitem> is the only supported group set. Polygons will not show up on the map, so make sure to select a facility level. Click an icon on the map to open the information window.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Symbolic mapping</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_symbolic_mapping.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section id="gisFavoriteMapView">
      <title>Register favorite map views</title>
      <para>This window will save the current thematic map view in order to
    restore it whenever you want via the <guimenuitem>map view</guimenuitem> combo box in the <guimenu>thematic map</guimenu> panel. By
    adding your views to DHIS 2 Dashboard you may access them there by
    inserting <guimenuitem>map views</guimenuitem> into one of the link
    areas. Please see the referred window in section 1.1.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisLegendSet">
      <title>Register legend sets</title>
      <para>A legend set may be connected to many indicators, but an indicator
    may only have one legend set. Thus, you may select many indicators when
    you create a legend set. When an indicator that has a legend set is
    selected in the <guimenu>thematic map</guimenu> panel, the number of
    classes, low color and high color is automatically set.</para>
      <para>Example usage (vaccination coverage): Firstly, create the legends that are going to constitute the legend set. The first one could be &quot;Low bad&quot; (display name), 0 (start value), 30 (end value), red (color). Then create &quot;Medium&quot; / 30 / 70 / yellow and finally &quot;High good&quot; / 70 / 100 / green. Now, open the &quot;legend set&quot; panel, type e.g. &quot;High is good&quot; as display name and select the desired legends below. Multi-select your three legends by pressing and holding the Ctrl/Shift button when selecting. Then click the register button to store the legend set. Assign indicators/data elements to your legend set in one of the two last panels. Select the legend set in the combo box and multi-select items in the list below. Click the assign button to update the legend set. Please see the referred window in section 1.1.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisImageExport">
      <title>Exporting/saving map images</title>
      <para>Click the image icon on the map toolbar and the  print window will open. Title: Image title, will appear as a headline in the image. Layers: Choose whether polygons, points or both will be printed. Width/Height: The pixel resolution of the image. Choose among the predefined &quot;small&quot; (800x600), &quot;medium&quot; (1190x880), &quot;large&quot; (1920x1200) or type the exact number of pixels yourself (type the number only, avoid text like &quot;px&quot;). If you want to exclude the legend from the image, untick the legend checkbox. Finally click the export button to print the image  (PNG). Please see the referred window in section 1.1.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisMeasureDistance">
      <title>Measure distance</title>
      <para>Click the two-way arrow icon on the map toolbar to enter measuring mode. Now, click your desired start location on the map and a dotted line will follow the cursor towards your destination. Single click to create a line point, double click to finish the line. To exit measuring mode, click the toolbar icon again or close the window.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisLayerOptions">
      <title>Layer options</title>
      <para>Right-click or left-click any layer in the layer tree in the upper right corner to open the layer options context menu. There are currently three layer options available for vector layers: &quot;Locate feature&quot;, &quot;Labels&quot; and &quot;Opacity&quot;. See picture below.
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Layer options</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="50%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_layer_options.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          Locate feature (organisation unit): Click one of the units in the list and its color in the map will change to the color you have specified in the &quot;Highlight color&quot; combo box. If the list of organisation units is long you can easily create a text filter in the textfield below. See picture below.
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Locate organisation unit</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_locate_feature.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          Labels: Select size, style and color of the text and hit "Toggle" to show/hide the labels, which shows the organisation unit name and its value (based on the current indicator/period selection). See picture below.
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Organisation unit labels</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_labels.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          Opacity: Adjust the opacity/transparency of the layer in the map.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisViewHistory">
      <title>View history</title>
      <para>The 10 latest views shown in the map are available by clicking the watch icon on the map toolbar. If you e.g. are drilling down the levels and want to go one level back, select row number two in the list.
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>View history</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="50%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_view_history.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisAdministratorSettings">
      <title>Administrator settings</title>
      <para>Administrator settings are available only to users with admin rights. Date: Choose between fixed periods and start/end dates. Fixed periods refers to the periods created by the DHIS 2. Start/end dates means that you can define the period yourself by selecting the exact start date and end date of the period. Google Maps: In order to have Google Maps as background you need to fill in an Google Maps API key created for the domain the applcation is running on. The default key works for localhost. If you want to set up GIS on an external server you have to create and fill in the key for this domain, more info here http://code.google.com/apis/maps/signup.html. You will be provided with a link such as: http://maps.google.com/maps?file=api&amp;v=2&amp;sensor=false&amp;key=ABQIAAAAut6AhySExnYIXm5s2OFIkxRKNzJ-_9njnryRTbvC6CtrS4sRvRREWnxwlZUa630pLuPf3nD9i4fq9w. Note that you are supposed to fill in the key only, i.e. the encrypted string that follows after "key=", not the entire link.
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>View history</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="50%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_google_key.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
      </para>
    </section>  </section>
</chapter>
