<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using MyDatamart</title>

  <section id="Application">
    <title>The Mydatamart application</title>
    <para>The purpose of the Mydatamart application is to manage a local datamart store which is
            populated by downloading small chunks of data from the central DHIS2 web application. It
            also manages the details of ODBC connection parameters required to link Excel workbooks
            to your data.</para>
    <para>The simplest way to start mydatamart.exe is to double-click on the icon on your
            desktop. The application should open and show a window like <xref linkend="first"/>
            below:</para>
    <figure id="first">
      <title>Mydatamart on first open</title>
      <graphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/first.png" width="3in" align="center"/>
    </figure>
    <para>All of the functionality of mydatamart is available through the menu items in the
            upper menu bar. Some of the more commonly used functions are also available through the
            image button bar immediately below the menu. If you hover your mouse slowly over these
            buttons a tooltip window should show the functions of each.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Maintaining the local datamart</title>
      <para/>
      <section>
        <title>Creating a new datamart</title>
        <para>Now the main purpose of mydatamart is to manage your personal datamart files
                    so the first thing you will need to do is to create a new datamart. You can
                    create a new datamart either through the File-&gt;New menu option or by pressing
                    the button with the blue cross. When you create this new datamart you will be
                    prompted for a file name. The extension .dmart will be appended automatically to
                    the name. Give some thought to how and where you are going to store this file as
                    it will soon be full of valuable data so you really do need to look after it.
                    You can create a backup at any time by simply making a copy of this file, eg.
                    onto a USB memory stick.</para>
        <note>
          <para>The .dmart file is actually an sqlite3 database file which you can also
                        open and view or edit with any sqlite3 capable tool, such as
                        sqlitestudio.</para>
        </note>
        <para>When you create the new datamart, the application will present a dialog like
                        <xref linkend="new"/>.</para>
        <figure id="new">
          <title>Creating a new datamart</title>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/new.png" width="3in" align="center"/>
        </figure>
        <para>The first thing you must do is to establish a connection with your dhis
                    server. To do this enter the full url (including http://) of the dhis server
                    into the box labelled <emphasis>URL</emphasis>. Then enter your online dhis user
                    name and password. Your password will not be saved anywhere on your machine. To
                    login press the button labelled <emphasis>Login</emphasis>. If the login was
                    successful you will be rewarded with a green tick icon next to the login
                    button.</para>
        <figure id="loggedin">
          <title>Logging in to dhis2 server</title>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/loggedin.png" width="3in" align="center"/>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Populating the datamart with metadata</title>
        <para>The local datamart is designed to store aggregated data values from
                    dataelements and indicators in the online DHIS2 application. But before you can
                    do this, you must first populate the local datamart with
                        <emphasis>metadata</emphasis> from the remote dhis2.</para>
        <para>Metadata refers to the parts of the database which give the data values
                    meaning. This includes: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Organisation units and hierarchy;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Dataelement and Indicator names;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Datavalue disaggregations (categories and categoryoptions);</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Various groups and groupsets.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist> This information is required to work with pivot tables and to
                    select important parameters relating to your organisation unit. </para>
        <para>Fortunately populating with metadata is a straightforward, if time consuming,
                    operation. The easiest way to load metadata from DHIS2 is to press the toolbar
                    button with the <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/hierarchy.png" width="0.5cm"/> image.
                    It can also be done via the &quot;Datamart-&gt;Load metadata from dhis&quot; menu
                    option.</para>
        <para>The Mydatamart application will then contact the remote DHIS2 server and
                    download, transform and save the metadata into the local database.</para>
        <note>
          <para>Currently the transform part of the operation is quite slow. Expect it to
                        take as long as ten minutes. During this time you cannot work with the
                        application so you have to be patient. The reason for the long time is that
                        it must process all of the orgunits in the dhis hierarchy, which for many
                        countries can be quite large. In future editions of Mydatamart we will
                        improve on this by cutting down the number of orgunits to be
                        processed.</para>
        </note>
        <para>Once the metadata download is complete the user will be returned to the
                    Settings interface where she can proceed to enter information about her
                    organisation unit and the level of analysis to be used. This configuration is
                    covered in the following section.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Choosing Organisation unit and analysis level</title>
        <para>The benefit of using mydatamart is that you only need to download the data
                    from the dhis2 server which you need in your routine analysis. By selecting the
                    appropriate orgunit and level of analysis you ensure that your regular data
                    updates will be small and manageable even when bandwidth is limited.</para>
        <para>The two concepts to be aware of are your <emphasis>root orgunit</emphasis> and
                    your <emphasis>analysis level</emphasis>. To illustrate this using an example
                    from Kenya, let us assume you are based in the district office of Nyeri North in
                    Nyeri County. You have either been given pivot tables or you will make them to
                    analyze your data down to facility level. So you require data for all the
                    facilities within Nyeri North and you also require to see data for your peers
                    ie. the other districts within Nyeri County.</para>
        <para>Once you have created a new datamart and have downloaded metadata as described
                    in the previous section, you should be able to set these two parameters in the
                    settings dialog as illustrated below. If the dialog is not visible you can
                    access it by pressing the <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/configuration.png" width="0.5cm"/>
                    button.</para>
        <figure id="analysis_level">
          <title>Setting analysis parameters</title>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/analysis_level.png" width="3in" align="center"/>
        </figure>
        <para>Once you have set these once they will be saved with your datamart file.
                    Though they can be changed at any time or you might have different datamart
                    files with different settings. In most cases you will likely be maintaining a
                    single datamart file which you will have set up like the case of Nyeri North
                    above.</para>
        <note>
          <para>You will have noticed from <xref linkend="analysis_level"/> that the
                        analysis level is converted to a number. So for example, in Kenya, the
                        facility is at level 5, the district is level 4 etc. These correspond to
                        orgunit hierarchy levels within dhis2. These numbers will vary from one
                        country implementation to another. For the most part you do not need to be
                        concerned with the number of the level, except when you come to selecting
                        views for analysis. Here you will see that the level number is used as part
                        of the naming convention for views.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Downloading data</title>
        <para>Now that you have your local datamart set up you are ready to start populating
                    it with data from your online dhis2 server. Whereas you will probably only
                    adjust the settings when creating a new datamart, you will be doing regular
                    synching of your local datamart with the online server. If data is being
                    downloaded once a month, then the incremental size of each download will be
                    small. You can get to the data download screen either by pressing the
                        <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/data_mart_export.png" width="0.5cm"/> button or by navigating to the &quot;Datamart-&gt;Update Aggregate
                    Data&quot; menu item.</para>
        <para><xref linkend="download"/>, shows the datamart update screen. You can set the
                    detailed options for your download here. There is not much to be done as the
                    defaults should match your typical operations.</para>
        <figure id="download">
          <title>Downloading data</title>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/mydatamart/download.png" width="3in" align="center"/>
        </figure>
        <para>On the left hand side there are check boxes which you should set to indicate
                    whether you need data weekly, monthly, quarterly or yearly (you can select more
                    than one). These are independently set for aggregated datavaues as well as
                    aggregated indicator values, though in most cases you will require the same
                    periodicity of databvalue and indicator value.</para>
        <para>On the right hand side you have the option to set the time period you are
                    downloading. The application will attempt to select a reasonable period for you.
                    Other than the very first time you download data, the default should be to
                    download the previous month&apos;s data.</para>
        <para>Below the period selection section are the two buttons which actually initiate
                    the download. The first button is used to download data for orgunits below the
                    root orgunit at the level which was specified previously. So in the example, it
                    will download aggregated data at the facility level (level 5) for facilities in
                    Nyere North.</para>
        <para>The second button is used to download aggregate data of our peers. In this
                    case it would ensure that we had data for all the districts in Nyere County.
                    This will allow the Nyere North user to analyze the data for all facilities in
                    Nyere North as well as to compare the performance of Nyere North district with
                    Nyere South district.</para>
      </section>

    </section>
      
    </section>
</chapter>
