<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[]>
<chapter>
  <title>Using Tracker Capture</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Tracker capture is an advanced version of the event capture app. While the event capture
      deals with single event without registration, tracker capture deals with multiple events
      (including single event) with registration. The implication of this is that, any event
      capturing has to be for a registered tracked entity. This makes registration/searching of a
      tracked entity a key component of tracker capture. </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Registering/searching tracked entity</title>
    <para>To proceed with the tracker capture one needs to have a tracked entity. As shown in the
      screenshot below, the first page of the app provides two features for this - searching an
      existing one or registering a new one.</para>
    <para/>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example searching/registration</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/tracker_capture/search_register.png" format="JPG"
            width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>All searching and registration operations are accessible from the screen shown above.<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Searching: there are two modes of searching - simple and advanced. The simple one
            works when by typing a free text on the provided area. The advanced one works when
            various search criteria are provided in the drop down window. Both search modes return
            matching list of tracked entity displayed in a table. Clicking on any row takes to the
            selected tracked entity dashboard.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Registration: this is accessible through the "Register" button. The label for this
            button changes according to a program selected in the first drop down select box. Since
            "TB program" is selected and this program is assigned a tracked entity of type "Person",
            the label has changed to "Register Person". During registration, it is possible to stay
            on the same page and keep doing more registration or go straight to the dashboard of the
            registered entity. Selecting a program and doing registration also performs enrollment
            at the background. If a tracked entity is registered without a program, then enrollment
            is possible from the tracked entity's dashboard.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
    <para/>
    <para>Both search and registration are dictated by a selected program. It is program attributes
      which are being used as search criteria, registration attributes and also as columns names for
      tracked entity list. If no program is selected, the system picks default attributes. If no
      search criteria is assigned for an attribute, then the attribute has no effect on searching.
      However to control the appearance or not of an attribute as a column list, one has to go
      through a menu available under the small gear icon. </para>
    <para>Once a tracked entity is obtained - either through searching or registration - the app
      presents the selected tracked entity's dashboard.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Tracked entity dashboard</title>
    <para>All operations on a tracked entity are available from this dashboard. Anticipating
      multiple usecases or operations on registered tracked entity, we have structured the dashboard
      as a collection of widgets - more widgets can be added. This helps to scale and handle
      complexity while staying simple and clean. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example tracked entity dashboard</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/tracker_capture/tei_dashboard.png" format="JPG"
            width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>As shown in the figure above, the dashboard starts with three menus at the top: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>back button - this helps to go back to the search and registration page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>program selection menu - this is to dictate what kind of data to record and track
            for the selected entity. This also affects the contents of the widgets.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a small gear icon at the right corner - currently this helps to control which
            widgets to display. From the figure above, there are six widgets on display. The widgets
            are collapsible, responsive and draggable - this helps to acquire optimal view area as
            per user needs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para> The widgets:- <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Enrollment widget</emphasis> - this helps to enroll the
            tracked entity for the selected program. If an active enrollment already exists, the
            widget automatically displays it with some details about it. The widget also helps to do
            some operations on active enrollment - for example terminate/complete.</para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Dataentry widget</emphasis> - this is for doing data entry
            using either default or custom forms (the small black icon helps for switching).
            Depending on program definition, in particular program stages, events will be displayed
            in a timely fashion. Clicking on any of them displays the corresponding data entry. It
            is also possible to create new events. To proceed with data entry, it is mandatory to
            have event date. Once an event date is specified it is not possible to change due date.
            The assumption is that by specifying event date, the event has already taken place. If
            the event hasn't yet occurred, it is possible to change due date - this is effectively
            doing nothing but rescheduling. The buttons at the bottom help to change the status of a
            selected event. Another key feature from this widget is addition of multiple notes for
            an event. Normally data recording is through datalements, however there are cases where
            it is necessary to record additional information or comments. This is where the notes
            section comes handy. However, a interesting feature here is - it is not possible to
            delete a note. The idea is notes are more like log books. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Profile widget</emphasis> - this is to edit tracked entity's
            profile.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Relationship widget</emphasis> - this helps to relate the
            selected tracked entity (the one whose dashboard is shown) to another tracked entity.
            Adding a relative is possible by either searching from existing or registering a new
            one.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Notes widget</emphasis> - this is the same as event notes. The
            difference between the two is that, here notes are attached not to events but to
            enrollments. This helps to record some notes based on enrollment - for example why is an
            enrollment terminated or what is the overall observation of the tracked entity
            throughout the enrollment.</para>
        </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Report widget</emphasis> - this is to provide a "journal" of the
            tracked entity per program. A report row is provided for each program the tracked entity
            is/was associated.</para>
      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
