<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using GIS</title>
  <section>
    <title>Using the GIS module</title>
    <para>You can access the GIS module from the Services-&gt;GIS link in the top menu. The picture below shows the various panels you can use to interact with the maps.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Main GIS screen</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_main.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <section id="gisThematicMap">
      <title>Thematic mapping</title>
      <para>This panel lets you use your registered maps for thematic mapping. All you need to do is selecting your desired indicator/dataelement-period-map combination in the left side menu. Then click either boundary or level to open the organisation unit selection window. Here you may select both the parent organisation unit and the level of its children. If your database has coordinates for these organisation units they will appear on the map.</para>
      <para>Calculation method
    alludes to the  size  of the legend classes. Set to <guimenuitem>Equal intervals</guimenuitem> they will be “highest map value – lowest map value
    / number of classes”. Set to <guimenuitem>Equal group count</guimenuitem> the legend creator will try to distribute the organisation units evenly. Choose <guimenuitem>Fixed bounds </guimenuitem>and
    you may define your own class break values, type e.g. “20,40,60” using a comma to
    separate each of them.</para>
      <para>The map view combo box lists all map views (favorites) saved by the user. The settings that are stored in the map view will be automatically applied to the thematic map panel.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Main data entry screen</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_thematic_mapping.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section id="gisFavoriteMapView">
      <title>Register favorite map views</title>
      <para>This window will save the current thematic map view in order to
    restore it whenever you want via the <guimenuitem>map view</guimenuitem> combo box in the <guimenu>thematic map</guimenu> panel. By
    adding your views to DHIS 2 Dashboard you may access them there by
    inserting <guimenuitem>map views</guimenuitem> into one of the link
    areas.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisLegendSet">
      <title>Register legend sets</title>
      <para>A legend set may be connected to many indicators, but an indicator
    may only have one legend set. Thus, you may select many indicators when
    you create a legend set. When an indicator that has a legend set is
    selected in the <guimenu>thematic map</guimenu> panel, the number of
    classes, low color and high color is automatically set.</para>
      <para>Example usage (vaccination coverage): Firstly, create the legends that are going to constitute the legend set. The first one could be &quot;Low bad&quot; (display name), 0 (start value), 30 (end value), red (color). Then create &quot;Medium&quot; / 30 / 70 / yellow and finally &quot;High good&quot; / 70 / 100 / green. Now, open the &quot;legend set&quot; panel, type e.g. &quot;High is good&quot; as display name and select the desired legends below. Multi-select your three legends by pressing and holding the Ctrl/Shift button when selecting. Then click the register button to store the legend set. Assign indicators/data elements to your legend set in one of the two last panels. Select the legend set in the combo box and multi-select items in the list below. Click the assign button to update the legend set.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisImageExport">
      <title>Exporting/saving map images</title>
      <para>Click the image icon on the map toolbar and the  print window will open. Title: Image title, will appear as a headline in the image. Layers: Choose whether polygons, points or both will be printed. Width/Height: The pixel resolution of the image. Choose among the predefined &quot;small&quot; (800x600), &quot;medium&quot; (1190x880), &quot;large&quot; (1920x1200) or type the exact number of pixels yourself (type the number only, avoid text like &quot;px&quot;). If you want to exclude the legend from the image, untick the legend checkbox. Finally click the export button to print the image  (PNG).</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisLayerOptions">
      <title>Layer options</title>
      <para>Right-click any layer in the layer tree in the upper right corner to open the layer options context menu. There are currently three layer options available for vector layers: &quot;Locate feature&quot;, &quot;Show/hide labels&quot; and &quot;Opacity&quot;. Locate feature (organisation unit): Click one of the units in the list and its color in the map will change to the color you have specified in the &quot;Highlight color&quot; combo box. If the list of organisation units is long you can easily create a text filter in the textfield below. Show/hide labels: By clicking this option, a label with the organisation unit name and its value (based on the current indicator/period selection) appears on the map. Opacity: Adjust the opacity/transparency of the layer in the map.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
