<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Import and export</title>
  <highlights>
    <para><emphasis>Learning objectives:</emphasis></para>
    <para>
After reading this module you will be able to understand:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Why do we need functions of export and import data.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How to export data from DHIS2</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
How to import data into DHIS2</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </highlights>
  <section>
    <title>What is import and export?</title>
    <para>In a primary health system, the HMIS typically involves a distributed application, where the same application is running in different geographical locations (PHCs,CHCs, hospitals, districts, and state). Most of these physical locations do not have Internet connectivity, and hence they work offline. At some point (normally at the district level), the data needs to be synchronised in order to have a consolidated database for the a particular geographical region. For this, it is important to be able to export data from one location (which is working offline, say at the health facility  level) to another one say at the district level where the data would need to be imported. This feature of exporting and importing is thus a crucial function of a HMIS. This feature also helps us overcome the dependency on Internet to some degree, as data updates can be transferred via USB key where there is no connectivity, or through email where there is limited Internet connectivity. DHIS 2 provides robust export-import functionality to fulfil these needs.
</para>
  </section>
  <section id="export">
    <title>Exporting data</title>
    <para>In the case on on-line data entry, all data is saved into one database only. In an offline deployment, each deployment will have a separate database in their local system. So the data will be stored in their local database. In an offline deployment, after the data entry is finished, it will need to be manually sent to the next level of where the application is running. In an on-line application, however, that is not required, as all data is stored at a central location using the Internet.
</para>
    <section>
      <title>Exporting from DHIS 2</title>
      <para>The export option can be made use of by selecting it as follows. 
The import or export is available only when the selected organisation (source/destination) has defined datasets. This is because datasets help to define which data is to be or is being exported. Further, which specific data elements get exported is determined by the composition of the dataset being exported.
If there are no datasets defined for an organisation unit, it indicates that no data values are registered for this level of organisation or lower.
To access the main Import-Export module, choose <guimenu>Services-&gt;Import-Export</guimenu></para>
      <para>The exported data values are stored in an ‘xml file’. The file name is defined by the name of the source organisation unit and the period to allow the receiving organisation unit to identify the source and the period of the export file. The XML is placed in your home directory (On Windows this is normally <filename>C:\Documents and Settings\</filename> under the sub-directories <filename>/dhis / import-export</filename>.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Exporting data to other DHIS 2 systems</title>
      <para>Once the data export screen is displayed, select the Organisation unit, period and dataset for which data export should be selected.Finally click on the export option that will be available on the lower left side of displayed screen.
If there are no datasets defined for an organisation unit, it indicates that no data values are registered for this level of organisation or lower.
</para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/import_export/export_to_dhis2.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>A pop-up save option will appear on the displayed screen (see picture below) prompting the saving of the exported data. You may save the export folder on your desktop or any other folder by selecting the ‘Save to Disk’ option from the pop-up prompt.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Exporting metadata to other DHIS 2 systems</title>
      <para/>
      <section>
        <title>Metadata export</title>
        <para>Metadata is &quot;data about data&quot;. In the context of DHIS 2, metadata consists
          of definitions of data elements, indicators, the structure and names contained in the
          organizational hierarchy, and other options. Click on the &quot;Metadata export&quot; link
          from the main &quot;Data export&quot; screen in order to access this. Just select the
          features, format, and the compression that you want and click &quot;Export&quot;. This
          metadata file can then be transmitted just like a data file, except it will contain
          information on the definitions of the various features, as opposed to the values of the
          data themselves. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/import_export/metadata_export.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>DHIS 1.4 Metadata export</title>
      <para>The DHIS 1.4 Metadata export functionality provides the same functionality as the standard DHIS 2 metadata export, except that the resulting file can be used to transmit metadata information to DHIS 1.4 systems. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>DHIS 1.4 Detailed Metadata Export</title>
      <para>The DHIS 1.4 Metadata export functionality provides the same functionality as the detailed DHIS 2 metadata export, except that the resulting file can be used to transmit metadata information to DHIS 1.4 systems. Simply select the data elements and indicators that you want and click &quot;Export&quot; to begin the export process.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>PDF Metadata Export</title>
      <para>Auctor natoque ve vulputate quam. Quam duis posuere risus felis mus class tempor eu sociosqu. Risus duis penatibus turpis, tristique dictum enim est. Quisque mi pulvinar ultrices, fusce diam porttitor mi hendrerit viverra, augue leo vestibulum rutrum. Ridiculus dictumst luctus. Eros.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="import">
    <title>Importing data</title>
    <para>The import option allows different instance of DHIS 2 to receive standardised set of data in the absence of a networked system. Typically, a data set is exported from one DHIS instance (e.g. a district level system) to another system (e.g. a provincial level system).  DHIS 2 is capable of importing data from other systems that either support the DXF of IXF formats. DHIS 2 is capable of importing data directly from a DHIS 1.4 Access database. Each of these options will be discussed in the following sections. </para>
    <section id="import_another_instance">
      <title>Importing data from another DHIS 2 instance</title>
      <para>Data can be imported into different instances of DHIS 2 through the use of the DXF data exchange format. There are two screens that are used to import data, with default and advanced options. </para>
      <para>The default data import menu can be accessed by clicking the <guimenuitem>&quot;Import&quot;</guimenuitem> from the main <guimenuitem>Import-Export</guimenuitem> screen. </para>
      <para>By clicking the <guibutton>&quot;Browse&quot;</guibutton> button, you can select a file from you local file system. This file may have been received by email, copied from another users system, or received on a CD for example. Simply select the file that you wish to import. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Default import screen</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/import_export/import_default.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para/>
      <para>There are three separate options for importing data. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Dry run: This is similar to the old preview option, this will do a dry run import,
            and give you information about any errors.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Strategy: There are three options here, "New and Updates", "New only", and "Update
            only". New and updates tells the importer to expect both new metadata, and updates to
            existing ones. New only will only accept fresh metadata, usually you would use this on a
            empty database. Updates only will only allow the metadata to match metadata that is
            already there (same identifiers, new name etc).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE: We highly recommend always using the Dry run
              option</emphasis> when importing data to make sure you keep control over any changes
            to your metdata and databases being out of synch on data elements or orgunit
            names.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Dry run before importing</title>
        <para>Before doing the import into your database it is highly recommended to dry run the
          data to make sure no changes to the metadata (data element, organisation units, etc
          identifiers) have taken place at the source DHIS 2 installation. Set dry run to true in
          the Import window. In the dry run window it is<emphasis role="bold"/><emphasis role="bold"
              ><emphasis role="bold">IMPORTANT</emphasis> to look for New and Updates in
            metadata.</emphasis> DO NOT just click the Import all button without carefully reviewing
          the information in the preview window. Importing new data elements or orgunits without
          checking properly whether they are really new or just old names can cause a corrupted
          database with duplicate or incomplete data, so be careful! </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Importing data from DHIS 1.4</title>
      <para>There are two ways to import data from a DHIS 1.4 database; 1) through the 1.4 XML-based export files, or 2) directly from the DHIS 1.4 data file (.mdb). Both are accessible from the DHIS 1.4 Import menu under Import in the Import-Export module.</para>
      <para>It is critical that all data integrity violations which are present in the DHIS 1.4 database be fully resolved before attemtping an import into DHIS 2. You can check the data integrity of DHIS 1.4 through the CORE Module-&gt;Advanced-&gt;Data integrity checks. A report will be generated of all data integrity violations which should be resolved prior to importing into DHIS 2.</para>
      <section>
        <title>DHIS 1.4 File (database) Import</title>
        <para>This method is recommend when doing large imports from 1.4, and especially when importing into a new  DHIS 2 database.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DHIS 1.4 File Configuration</emphasis> </para>
        <para>Before you can start the 1.4 file import you need to provide a  few details about the 1.4 database:</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Datafile(#):</emphasis> Here you put the full path to the DHIS 1.4 data file you want to import from, e.g. C:\DHIS14\DHIS_#LR_LIBERIA.mdb. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Username:</emphasis>  Leave blank (unless you have set up extra security measures on the file)</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Password:</emphasis> Leave blank (unless you have set up extra security measures on the file)</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Levels:</emphasis> Provide the number of levels in the orgunit hierarchy in your 1.4 database, e.g. 5.</para>
        <para>Click &quot;Save&quot; and you will return to the DHIS 1.4 File Import window. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Import Type:</emphasis></para>
        <para>As with other imports you have the options to Import (directly), Preview, or Analyse the import. We recommend using the Analyse option first to check that the 1.4 database is OK and ready to be imported. </para>
        <para>When importing a large database into a new blank DHIS 2 database we recommend using the Import option to save time. </para>
        <para>For smaller incremental imports the Preview is OK.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Last Updated:</emphasis> </para>
        <para>If you want the full import, all the data in the 1.4 database you leave this field blank.</para>
        <para>If you only want to do an incremental import into an already existing DHIS 2 database you can use this field to filter which data values to import. Only values added or edited after the date you specify will be imported. This filter makes use of the LastUpdated column in the RoutineData table in the DHIS 1.4 data file.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Import process:</emphasis></para>
        <para>When you are done selceting Method, and LastUpdated you can begin the import by clicking on the Import button. This process might take a long time, depending on how many data values you are importing. On a reasonable spec. computer the import takes about 2 million records per 30 minutes.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>DHIS 1.4 XML Import</title>
        <para>Import thof XML data from DHIS 1.4 is also possible using the standard DHIS 1.4 export format. Just be sure that the DHIS 1.4 export format has been set to &quot;DHIS 2.0&quot; as illustrated in the screen shot below.  After the data has been exported by DHIS 1.4, you can import the data by choosing &quot;Services-&gt;Import-Export-&gt;DHIS 1.4 Import-&gt;DHIS 1.4 XML Import&quot; and proceeding via the procedure outline in the <link linkend="import_another_instance">previous section</link>.  </para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/import_export/dhis14_export.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Limitations to DHIS 1.4 imports</title>
        <para>Although it is possible to import and export data between instances of   DHIS 1.4 and DHIS 2, there are significant limiations. Currently, the import of some metadata is not supported from DHIS 1.4 to DHIS 2. This includes:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Validation rules</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Organisational unit alternate names</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Compulsory data element pairings</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Custom data entry forms</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Dataset data entry levels</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>It is also important that the aggregation operator defined in DHIS 1.4 be set to the correct value. Some data, such as population, should have their aggregation operator set to &quot;Average&quot; in DHIS 2, as this controls how the aggregation of data is handled over time (but not within the organisational unit hierarchy). </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Importing CSV data</title>
    <para>DHIS 2 supports import of data in the CSV format. This can be used to import exchange file produced by DHIS 2 itself. It also comes in handy when you want to import data from a third-party system as CSV is widely supported in applications and is easy to produce manually.</para>
    <para>To import a CSV data exchange file navigate to the <emphasis role="italic">CSV Data Import </emphasis>item in the left-side menu. Upload the exchange file and click <emphasis role="italic">Import</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>The following section describes the CSV format used in DHIS 2. The first row is assumed to be a header row and will be ignored during import.</para>
    <para><table>
        <title>CSV format of DHIS 2</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Column</entry>
              <entry>Required</entry>
              <entry>Notes</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Data element</entry>
              <entry>Yes</entry>
              <entry>Refers to uid by default, can also be name and code based on selected id scheme</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Period</entry>
              <entry>Yes</entry>
              <entry>In ISO format</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Org unit</entry>
              <entry>Yes</entry>
              <entry>Refers to uid by default, can also be name and code based on selected id scheme</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Category option combo</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
              <entry>Refers to uid</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Value</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
              <entry>Data value</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Stored by</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
              <entry>Refers to username of user who entered the value</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Timestamp</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
              <entry>Date in ISO format</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Comment</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
              <entry>Free text comment</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Follow up</entry>
              <entry>No</entry>
              <entry>true or false</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>
    <para>The following is an example CSV file which can be imported into DHIS 2. It  can be imported both as plain text file or as compressed ZIP file archive.</para>
    <screen>&quot;dataelelement&quot;,&quot;period&quot;,&quot;orgunit&quot;,&quot;categoryoptioncombo&quot;,&quot;value&quot;,&quot;storedby&quot;,&quot;timestamp&quot;,&quot;comment&quot;,&quot;followup&quot;
&quot;DUSpd8Jq3M7&quot;,&quot;201202&quot;,&quot;gP6hn503KUX&quot;,&quot;Prlt0C1RF0s&quot;,&quot;7&quot;,&quot;bombali&quot;,&quot;2010-04-17&quot;,,&quot;false&quot;
&quot;DUSpd8Jq3M7&quot;,&quot;201202&quot;,&quot;gP6hn503KUX&quot;,&quot;V6L425pT3A0&quot;,&quot;10&quot;,&quot;bombali&quot;,&quot;2010-04-17&quot;,,&quot;false&quot;
&quot;DUSpd8Jq3M7&quot;,&quot;201202&quot;,&quot;OjTS752GbZE&quot;,&quot;V6L425pT3A0&quot;,&quot;9&quot;,&quot;bombali&quot;,&quot;2010-04-06&quot;,,&quot;false&quot;</screen>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Importing XML data</title>
    <para>DHIS 2 supports import of data in XMl format. The format is called DXF (DHIS Exchange Format). To import an XML file navigate to the XML Data Import item in the left side menu. Upload the exchange file and click <emphasis role="italic">Import</emphasis>. After the import process is finished you can follow the link to the import summary, which will inform you about the outcome of the import process in terms of number of records  imported, updated and ignored and potential conflicts.</para>
    <para>If you need to manually produce such XML files please refer to the Web API chapter where you can find detailed documentation of the DXF format.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
