<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>DHIS Tracker Module</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
      <title>Quick Background</title>
      <para>Conventionally, Public Health Systems have been recording and reporting aggregated data of the services provided across various health programmes. Though this is crucial in monitoring &quot;<emphasis role="italic">reach</emphasis>&quot; and &quot;<emphasis role="italic">availability</emphasis>&quot; of public health services, but it lacks tracing the persons being provided these services and quality of these ones. </para>
      <para>For example, the aggregate report will show that 300 pregnant women registered  for ANC and 120 women given IFA tablets or 90 women given TT injection. In an aggregate system, it is not possible to ascertain that if a particular pregnant woman registered for ANC, has also been given IFA and TT, as data only shows aggregate numbers. To understand the quality of services given to each pregnant woman registered for ANC, immunization cycle of each child or treatment of each leprosy person, etc. it is important that treatment information of each person is maintained as an individual case.</para>
      <para>The DHIS tracker module ( also known as  DHIS Community Module  ) is an integrated module in DHIS2, built to support community health systems and facilitate a smooth integration between the community health data and aggregated data management.</para>
      <para>The module supports management of community health programs, such as child immunization, maternal health and e.g. allows tracking of individuals enrolled in various programs and activity planning for community health workers.</para>
      <para>The following are the major things:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Administrating meta data -  includes person attributes, person attribute groups, identifier types; relationship types, health programs,  program stages corresponding to the program, validations and formulas  for aggregating data value from individual cases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Administrating person registration - registering a new person, setting relationships,  enrolling a person into a program and management of person location</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data entry for inputting individual data for treatment  of each person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reports for individual cases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Linking data between tracker system and aggregate management system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages of tracker module -</emphasis></para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate the health service provider  in person&apos;s treatment follow-up by recording all treatment related information in one place and in effective monitoring of different health services and drill down to individual person information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help the person in recording treatment history in one place, which could be used later in case of referral.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate in recording entire treatment information of each person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help strengthen the quality and fidelity of data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The data in primary registers at sub-center level is recorded and maintained by individual data or treatment cases, and sent up-wards as aggregate reports.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Processes in the system</title>
      <para>The module supports health providers for registering treatment cases and tracks these cases over time through different forms that are filled for the treatment of each person.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person registration</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Program enrollment</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Treatment case</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reports</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Information tracking process</title>
        <para>The process  starts with the person registration. Then she/he can be enrolled in the program for which registered. The application will guide the health provider  the services required for her/him through activity plan and the services  from time to time can be updated into his/her profile.  The working process is described in steps depicted in picture below - </para>
        <para><screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Name based information tracking process.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot></para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Person registration</title>
        <para>The process of  creating a new person in the system is through the registration process. The person is first registered in the system (or checked if the person already exists in system). Searching a person can be done through name, identifiers,  location or user-defined person&apos;s attributes (address, phone number, e.g.). If the person already exists in the system, the program enrollment process can continue. If the person is not available,  new registration takes place. </para>
        <para>The system supports for creating identifier type for the registration, such as Passport number, PAN, driving license, health identifier, UID. However, a system unique identifier is created automatically after registration and used to track the person.</para>
        <para>For identification a person, the health worker is first identified through any of the identifiers or name of patient  in the system and the person is identified through identifiers for receiving a health service. After identification, the individual case history can be viewed or a treatment case can be updated for  the new visit that they have received.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Program enrollment</title>
        <para>When a person is enrolled into any health programme, the person is  provided various services through the treatment are recorded. Based on the services of the program by the time, the system creates an activity plan for person.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Treatment case</title>
        <para>Each interaction with the person related to the case is considered to be an treatment case and these cases are recorded into the individual case. Individual case is updated with the identification of both the health worker and the person who is receiving the service.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Reports</title>
        <para>The module provides two functions for viewing the  reports to get an overview of the services provided for a program or a program stage.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>User guide</title>
    <para>There are two additions in the module in both maintenance and services module - </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs maintenance module </emphasis>- Definition  meta data, include person attributes, person attribute groups, identifier types, relationships, program and program-stages, validation for program and formula to generate aggregate data value.</para>
        <para>When the ‘<emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis>’ options is chosen from the main <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, the following screen appears -</para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/persons_and_programs_main_page.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Individual records module</emphasis> - Support main functions for person registration, tracking information and individual reports.</para>
        <para>When the ‘<emphasis role="italic">Individual Records</emphasis>’ options is chosen from the main <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, the following screen appears -</para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/individual_records_main_page.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Persons and Programs maintenance</title>
      <para>The content in this part is for the expert users or administrative users who are capable and responsible for development and change.</para>
      <para>Each of the options for the maintenance will be described in the following sectionThe options for the maintenance will be described in the following section - </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Attribute</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view Person attributes. An attribute can be used to register extra information for a Person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Attribute Group</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view Person attribute groups. Groups makes it more convenient to add attributes to a Person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Identifier Type</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view Person identifier types. Any type and multiple identifiers can be registered.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Relationship Type</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view relationship types. A relationship is typically wife and husband or mother and child.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Program</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view programs. A program has program stages and defines which actions should be taken at each stage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Aggregation Query Builder</para>
          <para>Define formulas, expressions, rules for aggregation data from tracker to aggregation module</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Validation Criteria</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view validation criteria. A criteria is used for validation of Person data. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section id="patient_attribute">
        <title>Person attribute</title>
        <para>Create, modify and view person attributes. An attribute can be used to register extra information for a person.</para>
        <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person Attribute</emphasis> option to create a new attribute for persons. </para>
        <para>After, click on <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Person Attribute Management</emphasis> window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Person Attribute Management</emphasis> window.</para>
        <para>Basic information</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of person attribute.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Description of person attribute.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Mandatory</emphasis>: Entering value for this attribute is required or not.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Inheritable</emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Value Type</emphasis>: Data type of value inputed.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>: Specify a program which this attribute belongs to.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="patient_attribute_group">
        <title>Person attribute group</title>
        <para>To access the person attribute group maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person Attribute Group</emphasis> option to create a new an attribute group.</para>
        <para>To create a new attribute group, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Person Attribute Group</emphasis> window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Person Attribute Group</emphasis> window , click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill in the <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis> fields and then select attributes that should belong to the group from the left panel. </para>
        <para>Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected items</emphasis> button to add the selected attributes to the attribute group. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected items</emphasis> button to remove attributes from the group that have been selected in the right panel. </para>
        <para>Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes..</para>
      </section>
      <section id="patient_identifier_type">
        <title>Person identifier type</title>
        <para>To access the person identifier type maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person Identifier Type</emphasis> option to create a new identifier type.</para>
        <para>To creating a new identifier type, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Person Identifier Type Management </emphasis>window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Person Identifier Type</emphasis> window.</para>
        <para>Basic information -</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of identifier type.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Description of identifier type.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Mandatory</emphasis>: Entering value for the identifier is required or not.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Related</emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of characters</emphasis>: Maximum number of characters for value inputed. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Type</emphasis>: Data type of value inputted.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>: specify a program which the identyfier type belongs to.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="relationship_type">
        <title>Relationship type</title>
        <para>Relationship type section provides a mechanism for defining any relationship types and link persons through these relationship types by creating specific relationships.</para>
        <para>To access the relationship type maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Relationship Type</emphasis> option to create a new relationship type.</para>
        <para>To define a new relationship type, click <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Relationship Type Management </emphasis>window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add new Relationship Type</emphasis> window.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="program">
        <title>Program and Program stage</title>
        <section>
          <title>Program</title>
          <para>Program section provides a mechanism for defining a health programme.</para>
          <para>To access the program maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis> option.</para>
          <para>To define a new program, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button on the main page. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and then click the &quot;Add&quot; button.</para>
          <para>Basic information -</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: The name of the program</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Descriptions, meanings, explanation, etc. of/about the program.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Type</emphasis>: There are three type of program: multi events with registration, single event with registration and single event without registration.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Show provided elsewhere</emphasis>: Set show/hide status of provided elsewhere column in data entry form.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description of enrollment date</emphasis>: The date in which a person is registered to the system.
For example: the date in which a person enrolls to the system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description of incident date</emphasis>: The date when the person got the disease or he/she has just been committed to an equivalent program for being followed-up. E.g. In the Immunization program for child under 1yr old, the incident date is the birthday; in the maternal program, the incident date is the date of last menstrual period (LMP).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Duration in days</emphasis>: System gets the days to calculate the activity plan of each person in mobile project ( refer mobile chapter ).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Program stage</title>
          <para>To define a program stage, click the <emphasis role="italic">Program Stage Management</emphasis> icon  and then <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill in the Name and Description fields and then select the data elements that should belong to the group from the left panel. Click the Move selected button to add the selected data elements to the right panel. Click the Remove selected button to remove data elements that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the Add button to save changes, or the Cancel button to discard any changes.</para>
          <para>Basic information -</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of the program stage</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: The description of the program stage</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Scheduled days from start</emphasis>: The minimum number of days to wait for starting the program stage.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Repeatable</emphasis>: specify the program stage as repeatable or not.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Standard interval days</emphasis>: specify the number of days to repeat the repeatable program stage.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="patient_aggregation_query_builder">
        <title>Person aggregation query builder management</title>
        <para>This is the core functionality for linking data between tracker module and aggregate management module by defining the linking/aggregating rules.</para>
        <para>This provides two functions - </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Person aggregation query builder management</emphasis> is a tool for defining formulas, expressions, rules for aggregation data from tracker to aggregation module.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Person aggregation</emphasis> is used for generating routine data values from individual data by period and organization unit. Please refer the Service module to see this part.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
          <title>Person Aggregation Query Builder</title>
          <para>To access <emphasis role="italic">Aggregation Query Builder</emphasis> module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option. Select <emphasis role="italic">Aggregation Query Builder</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
          <para>After click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button, the following will appear:</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.3</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/create_new_person_aggregate_query_builder.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>Basic information -</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Provide name of query,  this name is usually same with the name of aggregate data element. For example Number of mothers got VAT, Number of children got BCG vaccine,...</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Dataset</emphasis>: Select dataset contains data elements which will be used to link with individual data.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Data element</emphasis>: Select aggregate data element which will be used to link with individual data.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Operator</emphasis>: Select <emphasis role="italic">Number of persons</emphasis> if aggregate based on persons, or <emphasis role="italic">Number of visits</emphasis> if aggregate data based on  times that persons received services.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>: Select program   needed for aggregation.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Program Stage</emphasis>: Select program stage from the selected program above.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Next section included 3 tabs: <emphasis role="italic">Data elements</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Person attributes</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>. Depend on the requirement of data aggregation, data element, person attributes, and number of programs are selected. </para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="italic">Data elements tab</emphasis>:</emphasis>
            </emphasis> List all available data elements  from selected program stage. To create a formula related to each data element, double click on the   data element. The formula of the data element is filled on the condition field,  like [DE:1.2.3], in with: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>1 - id of  the selected program.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>2 - id of the selected program stage.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>3 - id of the selected data element.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <note>
            <para>The formula can be create without any program stage, like [DE:1.*.3]</para>
          </note>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="italic">Person attribute tab</emphasis>: </emphasis>
            </emphasis>List all available fixed attributes, such as gender, DOB type, Age(days), .. and user-defined attributes. Besides, provide a formula for calculating number of persons who registered in system. However, if a program without registration is selected,  person attributes aren&apos;t shown.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="italic">Program tab</emphasis>:</emphasis>
            </emphasis> Provide formulas for calculating data value related to the selected program and program stage - </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The number of persons who enrolled the selected program.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The number of persons / times that ( Date of enrollment - Date of incident ) is greater then a certain number.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The number of persons who visited the selected program stage OR the number of visits what are registered in the system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The number of persons  by age at the report-time.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="underline">Condition: </emphasis>
            </emphasis>This section contains comparing operations (&lt;, &lt;=, &gt;, &gt;=, =, != ), calculation operation (+), priority operation ( ( ) ), boolean values (Yes, No), status operations (=NULL, != NULL), relation operations (AND, OR). These operations are used for supporting in setting condition for query. </para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="underline">Description :</emphasis>
            </emphasis> Show description for the condition above. </para>
          <para>E.g To get number of <emphasis role="italic">girls</emphasis> who got <emphasis role="italic">Vitamin A dose 6</emphasis> enrolled <emphasis role="italic">Child Health program</emphasis> on <emphasis role="italic">January 2012</emphasis>. Then query is created as in the figure below. Note that January 2012 is period parameter which user will select when generate report. It is not set in the query.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Fig. example_query</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example_query.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Sample of person aggregation</title>
          <para>E.g.  Find the number of the children vaccinated BCG by defining a linking rule between the data elements of aggregate dataset named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis>  and the data element of a program stage named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given</emphasis>.</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Data Element and Indicators</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Element</emphasis> option to define two new data elements -</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Datasets</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Dataset</emphasis> option to create a new dataset named <emphasis role="italic">BCG Report</emphasis> and add <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> data element into the dataset.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option   and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis> option to create a program named <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis> with a stage named <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> and add the <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given</emphasis> data element into this stage.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Create a new person aggregation query builder named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG Builder </emphasis>to linking between the data elements.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example agg query builder.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Individual Records </emphasis>option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person</emphasis> option below <emphasis role="italic">Registration</emphasis> header in the left menu to register three persons named <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis> in <emphasis role="italic">Ngelehun CHC</emphasis> and enroll them into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>.</para>
              <para>1) For  <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis>, open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>. Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2012-01-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
              <para>2) For  <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis>, open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into Child Health Program. Enter Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2012-01-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
              <para>3) For    <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis>,  no enter any data value for <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage.</para>
              <warning>
                <para>Before entering data value for the stage, choose <emphasis role="italic">Report Date</emphasis> as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2012-01-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Individual Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person aggregation</emphasis> option to run<emphasis role="italic"> Number of children - BCG Builder</emphasis> to get data value  and save it into database.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example person aggregation.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>- Result after running the query builder</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example_person_aggregation_result.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <para>1) Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
              <para>2) Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Patient</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="validation_criteria">
        <title>Validation criteria</title>
        <para>Validation criteria section provides a mechanism for defining criteria for persons when enrolling a program.</para>
        <para>To access the validation criteria maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Validation Criteria</emphasis> option to create a new program</para>
        <para>To create a new validation criterion, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and click <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button.</para>
        <para>You can assign facilities to a validation criterion in the <emphasis role="italic">Validation Criteria Management </emphasis>(list of available validation criteria are shown) by clicking the blue folder icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the validation criterion you would like to assign. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected</emphasis> button to add the selected programs to the validation criterion. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected</emphasis> button to remove programs from the group that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Save</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Individual records module</title>
      <para>Each of the options for the services will be described in the following section -</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person</para>
          <para>Create, modify and search for persons. Any type of data can be registered for a person by including attributes.
    </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Multiple Individual records</para>
          <para>Enter data for multiple program stages and persons for a program. The entry screen gives an overview of the stage status.
    </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Single event with registration </para>
          <para>The data to register is defined by a single event with registration program.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Single event without registration</para>
          <para>Register Single events without registration. The data to register is defined by a single event without registration program.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Program summary</para>
          <para>View the summary report to get an overview of the services provided for a program.
    </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Tabular report</para>
          <para>Use an interactive reporting tool for tracker-data using tabular presentation with dynamic filters for each person attribute/data element.
    </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person aggregation</para>
          <para>Generate routine data values from patient data by month (or other intervals if desired) and organisation unit.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section id="patient">
        <title>Person registration</title>
        <para>The first step in the tracking is the registration of person/case in the application. In the registration process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contract and location details &amp; health provider details, are entered in the application. In the registration itself, person is provided with the unique identification number. This number will be unique and will not match with the identification number of any person in the state jurisdiction. The issue of identification number will be the responsibility of facility where person is registered first time.</para>
        <warning>
          <para>No matter what program persons need  to enroll, they must register into the system first. Then health providers will enroll the persons into relevant  programs. E.g. every pregnant women and the child need to be registered first as a person, then they will be enrolled in Mother Care program or Child Health program.</para>
        </warning>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">
            <emphasis role="italic">
              <emphasis role="bold">Person registration process</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <para>For the registration process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contact and location details, and health provider details, are entered.</para>
        <orderedlist inheritnum="inherit" continuation="restarts" arch="">
          <listitem>
            <para>To register a person, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, select option <emphasis role="italic">Individual Records</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click the <emphasis>Person</emphasis> option below <emphasis role="italic">Registration</emphasis> header to go to <emphasis>Person Registration</emphasis> window.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select  a  facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the screen. Then click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button on the right side.</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Add new Person.PNG" align="center"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start process of registration by providing name, location details, identification details, contact details and other details like <emphasis role="italic">child contact name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">child contact type</emphasis>.  The  click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button  to complete to process of registration or click the <emphasis>Back to registration</emphasis>  to navigate to previous page.</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Person Management Page.PNG" align="center"/></para>
            <para>To check the duplicates or to avoid double registration, after providing name and demographic details, click the <emphasis role="italic">Check duplicate</emphasis> button. Checking process bases on full name, gender and birthday of the registering person to look for the available persons with the similar information in the database. The result list will be displayed if the system finds out the same persons. Now health providers can cancel the registration process and update the existing person or continue the process of registration.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <section>
          <title>Person enrollment</title>
          <para>After the  registration, the person needs to be enrolled in any available program. To enroll:</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click  the <emphasis role="italic">Program management </emphasis>icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the person you would like to enroll.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Select a program from the list  ( i.e., Death,  Child Health Program... )</para>
              <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Select Program for person.PNG" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <warning>
                <para>This task can be executed after registration successfully, a  form like the form above is  showed up for enrollment.
</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>After the selection of program, you need to provide two dates:</para>
              <para>1) <emphasis role="italic">Date of enrollment:</emphasis> The date when person enrolls into the selected program.</para>
              <para>2) <emphasis role="italic">Date of incident</emphasis>: The date when the person got the disease or he/she has just been committed to an equivalent program for being followed-up.</para>
              <warning>
                <para>The date of incident are very important to generate the activity plan for  each person. Health provider  needs to ensure  recording and reporting date of incidence with each case of multi events with registration. However,  the date is ignored with single event programs.</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click  the <emphasis role="italic">Enroll</emphasis> button to complete the enrollment process.</para>
              <para>The system will automatically calculate  due-date for each the program stage  and will show same the below enrollment. In  health programme, a person  registered and enrolled, needs to be checked from time to time by health providers.
The case update  is designed in the same manner so that services which are received by the persons can be updated from time to time  when they visit the facility  or  whenever the health providers need to <emphasis role="italic">track</emphasis>.</para>
              <para>The system will automatically calculate  due-date for each the program stage  and will show same the below enrollment. In  health program, a person  registered and enrolled, needs to be checked from time to time by health providers.
The case update  is designed in the same manner so that services which are received by the persons can be updated from time to time  when they visit the facility  or  whenever the health providers need to track.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Complete.PNG" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Editing person profile</title>
          <para>After enrolling a person to any program, you can edit profile for that person.</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click the <emphasis>Edit profile</emphasis> icon, the second icon under <emphasis>Operations</emphasis>, corresponding to the person you would like to edit.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>When you click on <emphasis>Edit profile</emphasis> icon, a dialog box may appear to require you verify the date of birth if it is not verified. You just simply click <emphasis>OK</emphasis> to go to the edit page.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Adding relationship</title>
          <para>Now you can add relationship for person. To do that, you have to click on the <emphasis>Relationship management</emphasis> icon under <emphasis>Operations</emphasis>. Then, the management page appears...</para>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/management page.PNG" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>To add relationship for a person, you have to click on <emphasis>Search available person</emphasis> button to navigate to <emphasis>adding relationship page.</emphasis></para>
          <para>To register a new person and create relationship with the selected person, click <emphasis role="italic">Register new person</emphasis> button.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Change person location and View person details and history</title>
          <para>You can change person location by clicking the <emphasis>Change person location</emphasis> icon under <emphasis>Operations</emphasis>. In addition, you can view all person details and history by click on <emphasis>Person details and history</emphasis>  icon under <emphasis>Operations</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>Furthermore, you can download all person details and history in the format of <emphasis role="italic"> XLS</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">PDF</emphasis> by clicking <emphasis>Download as Excel</emphasis> or <emphasis>Download as PDF </emphasis> button.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Change person location and view details.PNG" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Data entry</title>
        <section id="multiple_individual_records">
          <title>Multiple individual records</title>
          <para>The multiple individual records function is where individual data is manually registered in the DHIS database. A list events for each person who enrolled into the selected program after clicking a multi events with registration.</para>
          <para>To access the multiple individual records function, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Individual Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Multiple individual records</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
          <para>To start enter data, the first step is to open a list events of person who enrolled a certain program by clicking a program in the list on the main page. Follow these steps:</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Locate the organisation unit you want to register data for in the tree menu to the left. Expand and close branches by clicking on the +/- symbols. A quick way to find an organisation unit is to use the search box just above the tree (the green symbol), but you need to write in the full name to get a match.</para>
              <para>The system loads multi events with registration which belong to the selected organisation unit.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Select a program in the list. A list events of persons who enrolled into the selected program is shown.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click an event to open data entry form.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section id="single_event_with_registration">
          <title>Single event with registration</title>
          <para>The data to register is defined by a single event with registration program. The functionality supports health providers to register person information and input data values for a program into one form.</para>
          <para>In order to register an event, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> option, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Single event with registration</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
          <para>In order to list all persons in the selected facility, click <emphasis role="italic">List All Persons</emphasis> button.</para>
          <para>In order to add new event, select a program in the combo box. And then click <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button.</para>
          <para>To update event of a registered person:</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click <emphasis role="italic">Advanced search</emphasis> button. Then enter criterion for searching available persons. The seach result is displayed below.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click on the first icon to update value for the event.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section id="single_event_without_registration">
          <title>Single event without registration</title>
          <para>The data to register is defined by a single event without registration program.</para>
          <para>To register an event, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> option, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Single event without registration</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
          <para>To list all events in the selected facility, click <emphasis role="italic">List All Events</emphasis> button.</para>
          <para>To remove empty events of the selected program, click <emphasis role="italic">Remove empty events</emphasis> button.</para>
          <para>To add new event, click <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button.</para>
          <para>To update an event:</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click <emphasis role="italic">Advanced search</emphasis> button. Then enter criterion for searching events. The list events are displayed below.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Click on the first icon to update value for the event.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Reports</title>
        <para>The sub module provides two functions for individual reports -<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Program summary - view the summary report to get an overview of the services provided for a program.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Tabular report  - an interactive reporting tool for tracker-data using tabular presentation with dynamic filters for each person attribute and data element. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
        <section id="program_summary_report">
          <title>Program summary</title>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Program summary</emphasis> provides a tool for   generating summary list of individual information with  color shown on program stages to identify status of receiving services in each stage.</para>
          <para>To access the program summary report, choose  <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> -&gt; <emphasis role="italic">Name-based Data Records</emphasis> &gt;  <emphasis role="italic">Program summary</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>Select a <emphasis role="italic">organisation unit</emphasis>  which provides services on the left menu. Then on the main page, select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Start date</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">End date </emphasis>to get period. Finally, click <emphasis role="italic">Generate</emphasis> button. </para>
          <para>The result is get based on the date of enrollment of each person who registered the selected organisation unit and enrolled in the selected program in the interval from start-date and end-date what health provider entered.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/program_summary_report.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>The color highlight the status of the stages -</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>PURPLE: Data entered and uncompleted stages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>RED: Stages open but no data entered while the date estimated for closing/completing is over.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>YELLOW: Coming stages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>GREEN: Compete stages.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Tabular report</title>
          <para>This is  an interactive reporting tool for tracker-data using tabular presentation with dynamic filters for each person attribute/data element.</para>
          <para>To access the tabular report function, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Individual Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Tabular report</emphasis> option below Reports header on left menu to proceed. </para>
          <para>To start, the first step is to select a program in the list. Follow these steps:</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="run_case_aggregation">
        <title>Person aggregation</title>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Person Aggregation</emphasis> module is used for aggregating individual data and import into aggregated data element. To open <emphasis>Person Aggregation</emphasis> module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Individual Records</emphasis> option. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person Aggregation</emphasis> option on left menu.  <emphasis>Person Aggregation form</emphasis> is opened as below -</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.4</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/person_aggregation_form.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>In the <emphasis>Person aggregation form</emphasis> above</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select <emphasis role="italic">dataset</emphasis> from Dataset List to get aggregate values. Note that only datasets which were assigned to at least one organisation unit will be shown in this list.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Depend on frequency of the selected dataset, select <emphasis role="italic">period</emphasis> to get aggregate data. For example, if frequency of dataset is quarterly, then select begin quarter and end quarter. To select a particular quarter, then begin quarter and end quarter is the same particular quarter name.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select <emphasis role="italic">organisation unit level</emphasis> where person data will be select to aggregate. There are 3 options - </para>
            <para>- <emphasis role="italic">Children only</emphasis>: Individual data from the children of  the selected organisation unit will be aggregated.</para>
            <para>- <emphasis role="italic"> Selected</emphasis>: Individual  data from the selected organisation unit will be aggregated. </para>
            <para>- <emphasis role="italic">All</emphasis>: Individual data from both selected organisation unit and its children will be aggregated.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the 
<emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> button to execute aggregate function. The <emphasis>Person aggregation result</emphasis>page is opened as below figure -</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure - Person aggregation result</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/person_aggregation_result.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>In <emphasis>Person aggregation result</emphasis> page -</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="italic">Save all values</emphasis> button to save all aggregated data values .</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic"><emphasis role="italic">Click</emphasis> Orange arrow</emphasis> next to period name for showing list of aggregated data values at this period. Select only necessary data values and click <emphasis role="italic">Save</emphasis> selected values to save them</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis><emphasis role="italic">Click </emphasis>Show details</emphasis> icon  to view detail  information which aggregated.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
