<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Settings</title>
  <para>The settings module provides a set of application configuration options. There are two main
    groups of settings: the <emphasis role="italic">system settings</emphasis> apply to the whole
    system and all its users while the <emphasis role="italic">user settings</emphasis> apply to the
    environment of the currently logged in user. The system settings can be accessed from the
    maintenance menu, settings module. The user settings can be accessed under the profile menu,
    settings page.</para>
  <section>
    <title>User settings</title>
    <para>The user settings section provides general configuration options and options specifically for email.</para>
    <section id="userGeneralSettings">
      <title>User general settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface language: Sets the locale / language of the user interface, such as labels, menus and headers. You can currently select between 18 languages.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Database language: Sets the locale / language of the database contents in the
            system, such as the list of data elements and reports.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Style: Sets the style / look-and-feel of the system. You can choose among four
            different styles while the <emphasis role="italic">light blue</emphasis> style is the
            default and recommended style. The user setting overrides the corresponding style system
            setting.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable message email notifications: Decides whether you want to receive email
            notifications. Currently the system offers email notifications of messages received in
            the dashboard. This requires that you have entered your email address in your personal
            account details - you can access it in the "User account" page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable message SMS notifications: Decides whether you want to receive SMS
            notifications. Requires that a SMS provider has been configured for your
            deployment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>System settings</title>
    <para>The system settings section provides general configuration options and options specifically for appearance and email.</para>
    <section id="systemGeneralSettings">
      <title>General settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Cache strategy: Decides for how long reports and responses related to analysis
            should be cached. If you are using the scheduled, nightly data mart tasks it makes sense
            to put this on "Cache until 6 AM tomorrow". This is because we know that data in reports
            change at that time, and you can safely cache data up to the moment when the data mart
            is updated. If you are loading data continously into the datamart you should set it to
            "No cache". If you load data very infrequently into data mart you should consider
            setting it to "Cache for twol weeks".</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Infrastructural data elements: This setting defines a data element group where the member data elements should describe data about the infrastructure of  organisation units. Examples of such infrastructural data elements could be population, doctors, beds, internet connectivity and climate. This infrastructural data can currently be viewed in the GIS module in the facility information sheet.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Infrastructural period type: Sets the frequency for which the data elements in the infrastructural data elements group are captured. This will typically be yearly. When viewing the infrastructual data you will be able to select the time period of the data source.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Feedback recipients: This setting defines a user group where the members will
            recieve all messages being sent through the function for writing feedback in the
            dashboard module. This will typically be members of the super user team who are ablet to
            support and answer questions coming from end-users.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maximum offline organisation unit levels: This setting defines how many levels in
            the organisation unit hierarchy will be available offline in the organisation unit tree
            widget. Under normal circumstances you can leaves this on the lowest level, which is
            default behavior. Setting it to a higher level might be useful in order to reduce
            initial load time in cases where you have extremely many organisation units, typically
            more than 30 000.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data analysis std dev factor: Sets the number of standard deviations for use in the outlier analysis performed on the captured data in the data entry module. The default value is 2; a high value will catch less outlier values than a low value.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Days after period end to qualify for timely data submission: Sets the number of days after the end of a period in which a data entry form must be marked as complete in order to be considered timely. This affects the &quot;reporting rate&quot; tool in the reporting module which lists forms marked as complete as well as marked as complete in time. The default value is 15.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Phone number area code: The area code for the area in which your deployment is
            located. Used for sending and receiving SMS.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Omit indicator values with zero numerator value in data mart: Defines whether
            aggregated indicator values with zero as the numerator value should be written to the
            indicator data mart table. Having such values written is required for instance when
            connecting Excel pivot tables to the data mart as Excel will need the numerator data to
            correctly aggregate up in the organisation unit hierarchy. If third-party tools like
            Excel are not used with the application this will reduce the total number of values
            written to the data mart (which again will improve performance) and could safely be set
            to omit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="systemAppearanceSettings">
      <title>Appearance settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application title: Sets the application title on the top menu.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application introduction: Sets an introduction of the system. Will be visible on the
            login page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application notification: Sets a notification which should be displayed to users.
            Will be visible on the front page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Style: Sets the style / look-and-feel of the system. The corresponding user style setting overrides this.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Flag: Sets the flag which is displayed in the left menu of the dashboard module.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start page: Sets page / module which the user will be redirected to after logging in. The dashboard module is the recommended start module.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="systemEmailSettings">
      <title>Email settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Host name: Refers to the host name of the SMTP server. For instance when using Google SMTP services this should be smtp.gmail.com.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>User name: The user name of the user account with the SMTP server. For instance mail@dhis2.org.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Password: The password of the user account with the SMTP server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Access settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Self registration account user role: Defines which user role shoul be given to
            self-registered user accounts. To enable self-registration of users, select any user
            role from the list. To disable it, select "Do not allow self registration". When
            enabled, a link to the self-registration form will be displayed on the login
            page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Self registration account organisation unit: Defines which organisation unit should
            be associated with self-registered users. Any organisation unit must be selected in
            order to enable self registration.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable user account recovery: Defines whether users are allowed to restore the
            password of their account if they forgotten it. When enabled, a link to the account
            recovery form will be displayed on the front page. User account recovery requries that
            you have configured email settings (SMTP).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
