<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using Event Capture</title>
  <section>    
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The event capture module allows users to register events that occurred at a particular
      time and place. In DHIS2,time and place correspond, respectively, to period and organisation
      units. However, since events are treated as random occurrences there is no such thing as
      period for them, rather a date the event has occurred.
    </para>
    </section>
  <section>
    <title>Program definition</title>    
    <para>In order to capture events, it is mandatory for users to first define the nature of the
      event using the Program/Attribute module. Below is a guiding step for this:<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Go to Programs/Attributes module</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select Program</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click Add new and fill in the necessary details. Under <emphasis role="bold">Program
              details</emphasis> make sure <emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis> is <emphasis
              role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">"Single event without
              registration"</emphasis></emphasis>. Below is a snapshot to depict this.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Example single event program creation</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/event_capture/create_program.png" format="JPG"
              width="70%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>Once a single event program is created, the system automatically creates a single
      program stage. The stage can be accessed from the context menu of the program created.
      Clicking <emphasis role="bold">"Edit"</emphasis> from the context menu of the program stage
      takes to the detail view of the program stage, similar to the one shown below. 
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Example single event program stage creation</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/event_capture/edit_program_stage.png" format="JPG"
              width="70%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>As can be seen from the program stage screen shot above, users have the chance to
      define what to collect during event capture. This is possible by selecting a list of data
      elements from <emphasis role="bold">"Available data elements" </emphasis>to <emphasis
        role="bold">"Selected data elements"</emphasis>. Under selected data elements, please pay
      attention for the following check boxes:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Compulsory: </emphasis>whether it is mandatory or not to
            collect the element during event capture</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Allow provided elsewhere: </emphasis>this is to define if
            the data element can be collected by the selected organisation unit while it has
            occurred elsewhere. For example, from the figure, it is possible for "mnch Blood
            pressure" to be measured in another facility but reported in the selected facility where
            these is no blood pressure measuring device.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Display in reports:</emphasis> this decides if the data
            element can appear in reports or not. If there are many data elements to be collected
            during event capture, it makes more sense to prioritize which ones to show in report by
            default.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Date in future: </emphasis>this is only for those date type
            data elements and to decide if it is possible to allow collect future dates or
            not.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para>In addition to defining program and program stage, another important step to complete
      before event capturing is associating programs with organization units. This can be done
      through <emphasis role="bold">"Assign program to organisation units"</emphasis> button from
      the context menu of the selected program.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Operations</title>
    <para>Event capturing is possible by selecting an organisation unit and a program. The moment a
      program is selected the system displays existing events. Events are displayed in a tabular
      fashion as shown in the figure below. From the figure, each row corresponds to an event and
      the columns are event details (data elements).</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example event list</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/event_capture/event_list.png" format="JPG"
            width="70%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>All event related operations are accessible from the screen shown above. The operations
      currently available are: <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Capturing - this available by clicking the "Register New Event" button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Column show/hide - this is to allow users decide which columns to show/hide. This
            feature is especially important when we have a long list of data elements assigned to a
            program stage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Editing - the rows in the table are clickable. Clicking them shows three menus -
              <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Edit in grid</emphasis>
            and <emphasis role="bold">Remove.</emphasis> The difference between edit and edit in
            grid is that, Edit takes to a new page with an opportunity to edit all the data elements
            of the selected event. However, edit in grid allows to edit the selected event within
            the table but only those columns (data elements) visible in the grid. If more columns
            are required, it is possible to add using the "Show/Hide columns" button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sorting - this is possible by clicking the text of each column header.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Filtering - this is possible by clicking the small search icon shown to the right of
            each column header. Clicking them provides an input field to type a filtering criteria.
            The moment a user types a filter, the system starts applying. During filtering it is
            possible to define start and end dates for date type data elements and lower and upper
            limits for number types. For the rest, it is just a text.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Paging - using the links at the bottom of the table, it is possible to have some
            paging interactions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
