<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Apps</title>
  <para>A packaged app is an <ulink
      url="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Open_Web_apps_and_Web_standards">Open Web
      App</ulink> that has all of its resources (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, app manifest, and so on)
    contained in a zip file and can be uploaded to a DHIS 2 installation at runtime. A packaged app
    is a zip file with an <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/2008/webapps/manifest/">app manifest</ulink>
    in its root directory. The manifest must be named manifest.webapp. Since DHIS 2.12, an
    implementer can install packaged apps in DHIS 2 and extend the web interface of DHIS2.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Purpose of Packaged Apps</title>
    <para>The purpose of packaged apps is to extend the web interface of DHIS 2. A system deployment
      will often have custom and unique requirements. The apps provide a convenient extension point
      to the user interface. Through apps, you can complement and customize the DHIS 2 core
      functionality with custom solutions in a loosely coupled and clean manner.</para>
    <para>Apps do not have permissions to interact directly with DHIS 2 Java API. Instead, apps are
      expected to use functionality and interact with the DHIS 2 services and data by utilizing the
      DHIS 2 Web API.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Creating Apps</title>
    <para>Creating apps is simple: You can create HTML, JavaScript and CSS files similar to any
      other web application. Then one needs to create a file called <emphasis role="italic"
        >manifest.webapp</emphasis> which describes the contents of the app. This file should be in
      the format specified by the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/2008/webapps/manifest/">W3C Manifest
        for Web Applications</ulink>. A basic example of the <emphasis role="italic"
        >manifest.webapp</emphasis> is shown below:</para>
    <para>
      <screen>{
    "version": "0.1",
    "name": "My App",
    "description": "My App is a Packaged App",
    "launch_path": "/index.html",
    "icons": {
        "16": "/img/icons/mortar-16.png",
        "48": "/img/icons/mortar-48.png",
        "128": "/img/icons/mortar-128.png"
    },
    "developer": {
        "name": "Me",
        "url": "http://me.com"
    },
    "default_locale": "en",
    "activities": {
        "dhis": {
            "href": "*"
        }
    }
}</screen>
    </para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">manifest.webapp</emphasis> file must be located at the root of
      the project. Among the properties, the <emphasis role="italic">activities</emphasis> property
      is an extension meant to differentiate between a standard Open Web App and an App that can be
      installed in DHIS 2. The <emphasis role="italic">*</emphasis> value for <emphasis
        role="italic">href</emphasis> is converted to the appropriate URL when the App is uploaded
      and installed in DHIS 2. This value can then be used by the application's JavaScript and HTML
      files to make calls to the DHIS 2 Web API  and identify the correct location of DHIS 2 server
      on which the App has been installed. The <emphasis role="italic">icons&#x2192;48</emphasis>
      property is used for the icon that is displayed on the list of apps that are installed on a
      DHIS 2 instance.</para>
    <para>The App can contain HTML, Javascript, CSS and image files. The file structure looks like
      this:</para>
    <screen>/                   #html files
/manifest.webapp    #manifest file
/css/               #css stylesheets
/img/               #images
/js/                #javascripts</screen>
    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/apps/appList.png"/></para>
    <para>All the files in the project should then be compressed into a standard zip package. This
      zip package can then be installed into DHIS 2 as you will see in the next section.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Configuring DHIS 2 for Apps Installation</title>
    <para>The App manager is found under Services &#x2192; Apps. If your logged in user has
      permissions to view and edit settings you will see the Settings link in the left menu.</para>
    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/apps/appSettings.png"/></para>
    <para>The following settings can be configured:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>App Installation Folder: The folder on the file system where apps are unpacked. By
          default this is under the expanded DHIS folder suffixed by /apps. If you like to install
          your apps in another location, say www folder of Apache 2, you can specify the absolute
          path to that directory on the server, making your apps to be unpacked at that
          location.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>App Base URL: The URL through which the apps can be found on the Web. By default this
          is the same as your DHIS 2 URL suffixed by /apps. If you are installing apps through a
          different web server you need to provide the full URL for that web server.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>App store URL: The app repository through which new apps can be downloaded and
          installed. Each deployment can host their own, approved set of apps that can be installed
          in DHIS 2. We plan to host the global DHIS 2 App store at <ulink
            url="https://appstore.dhis2.org">https://appstore.dhis2.org</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Installing Apps into DHIS 2</title>
    <para>Apps can be installed by uploading zip file into the App manager. In, Services &#x2192;
      Apps, click on the <emphasis role="italic">App Store</emphasis> menu item.</para>
    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/apps/appStore.png"/></para>
    <para>The app can be uploaded by pressing the Browse button and after selecting the zip package,
      the file is uploaded automatically and installed in DHIS 2. You can also browse through apps
      in the app store and download apps from there. The app store allows for app searching,
      reviewing, commenting, requesting features, rating on the apps by the community.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Launching Apps</title>
    <para>After installation your apps can be accessed from the home page of the apps module. Click
      on an app in the list in order to launch it.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
