<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Name-Based Information Tracking Module</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
      <title>Quick Background</title>
      <para>Conventionally, Public Health Systems have been recording and reporting aggregated data of the services provided across various health programmes. Though this is crucial in monitoring &quot;<emphasis role="italic">reach</emphasis>&quot; and &quot;<emphasis role="italic">availability</emphasis>&quot; of public health services, but it lacks tracing the persons being provided these services and quality of these ones. </para>
      <para>For example, the aggregate report will show that 300 pregnant women registered  for ANC and 120 women given IFA tablets or 90 women given TT injection. In an aggregate system, it is not possible to ascertain that if a particular pregnant woman registered for ANC, has also been given IFA and TT, as data only shows aggregate numbers. To understand the quality of services given to each pregnant woman registered for ANC, immunization cycle of each child or treatment of each leprosy person, etc. it is important that treatment information of each person is maintained as an individual case.</para>
      <para>The DHIS name-based information tracking module ( also known as  DHIS Community Module  ) is an integrated module in DHIS2, built to support community health systems and facilitate a smooth integration between the community health data and aggregated data management.</para>
      <para>The module supports management of community health programs, such as child immunization, maternal health and e.g. allows tracking of individuals enrolled in various programs and activity planning for community health workers.</para>
      <para>The following are the major things:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Administrating meta data -  includes person attributes, person attribute groups, identifier types; relationship types, health programs,  program stages corresponding to the program, validations and formulas  for aggregating data value from individual cases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Administrating person registration - registering a new person, setting relationships,  enrolling a person into a program and management of person location</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data entry for inputting individual data for treatment  of each person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reports for individual cases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activity plans.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Linking data between name-based information tracking system   and aggregate management system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages of Name Based Information Tracking:</emphasis></para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate the health service provider  in person&apos;s treatment follow-up by recording all treatment related information in one place and in effective monitoring of different health services and drill down to individual person information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help the person in recording treatment history in one place, which could be used later in case of referral.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate in recording entire treatment information of each person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help strengthen the quality and fidelity of data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The data in primary registers at sub-center level is recorded and maintained by name based individuals or treatment cases, and  sent up-wards as aggregate reports.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Processes in the system</title>
      <para>The module supports health providers for registering treatment cases and tracks these cases over time through different forms that are filled for the treatment of each person.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person registration.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Program enrollment</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activity plans</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Treatment cases for a person</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Name based information tracking process</title>
        <para>The process  starts with the person registration. Then she/he can be enrolled in the program for which registered. The application will guide the health provider  the services required for her/him through activity plan and the services  from time to time can be updated into his/her profile.  The working process is described in steps depicted in picture below - </para>
        <para><screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Name based information tracking process.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot></para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Person registration</title>
        <para>The process of  creating a new person in the system is through the registration process. The person is first registered in the system (or checked if the person already exists in system). Searching a person can be done through name, identifiers,  location or user-defined person&apos;s attributes (address, phone number, e.g.). If the person already exists in the system, the program enrollment process can continue. If the person is not available,  new registration takes place. </para>
        <para>The system supports for creating identifier type for the registration, such as Passport number, PAN, driving license, health identifier, UID. However, a system unique identifier is created automatically after registration and used to track the person.</para>
        <para>For identification a person, the health worker is first identified through any of the identifiers or name of patient  in the system and the person is identified through identifiers for receiving a health service. After identification, the individual case history can be viewed or a treatment case can be updated for  the new visit that they have received.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Program Enrollment and Activity Plan</title>
        <para>When a person is enrolled into any health programme, the person is  provided various services through the treatment are recorded. Based on the services of the program by the time, the system creates an activity plan for person.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Treatment case</title>
        <para>Each interaction with the person related to the case is considered to be an treatment case and these cases are recorded into the individual case. Individual case is updated with the identification of both the health worker and the person who is receiving the service.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>User guide</title>
    <para>The module has two basic modules as follows - </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Maintenance  module</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Services module</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Functionalities</title>
      <para>There are two additions in the module in both maintenance and services module. <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> module has one additional sub module for defining meta data and  <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> module  has one additional sub-module for name-based data entry and reports.</para>
      <para>The modules provide three main functionalities -</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Definition  meta data, include person attributes, person attribute groups, identifier types, relationships, program and program-stages, validation for program and formula to generate aggregate data value.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person registration  and Tracking information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Individual reports</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Person registration</title>
      <para>The first step in the tracking is the registration of person/case in the application. In the registration process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contract and location details &amp; health provider details, are entered in the application. In the registration itself, person is provided with the unique identification number. This number will be unique and will not match with the identification number of any person in the state jurisdiction. The issue of identification number will be the responsibility of facility where person is registered first time.</para>
      <warning>
        <para>No matter what program persons need  to enroll, they must register into the system first. Then health providers will enroll the persons into relevant  programs. E.g. every pregnant women and the child need to be registered first as a person, then they will be enrolled in Mother Care program or Child Health program.</para>
      </warning>
      <para><emphasis role="underline">
          <emphasis role="italic">
            <emphasis role="bold">Person registration process</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
        </emphasis></para>
      <para>For the registration process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contact and location details, and health provider details, are entered.</para>
      <orderedlist inheritnum="inherit" continuation="restarts" arch="">
        <listitem>
          <para>To register a person, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, select option <emphasis role="italic">Name-Based Data Records</emphasis>.</para>
          <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/goto name-based data records.PNG" width="100%" contentwidth="65%" align="center"/></para>
          <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/name-based main page.PNG" contentwidth="70%" align="center"/></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Now click the <emphasis>Person</emphasis> option to go to <emphasis>Person Registration</emphasis> window.</para>
          <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Person Registration Window.PNG" align="center"/></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select  a  facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the screen. Then click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button on the right side.</para>
          <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Add new Person.PNG" align="center"/></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start process of registration by providing name, location details, identification details, contact details and other details like <emphasis role="italic">child contact name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">child contact type</emphasis>.  The  click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button  to complete to process of registration or click the <emphasis>Back to registration</emphasis>  to navigate to previous page.</para>
          <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Person Management Page.PNG" align="center"/></para>
          <para>To check the duplicates or to avoid double registration, after providing name and demographic details, click the <emphasis role="italic">Check duplicate</emphasis> button. Checking process bases on full name, gender and birthday of the registering person to look for the available persons with the similar information in the database. The result list will be displayed if the system finds out the same persons. Now health providers can cancel the registration process and update the existing person or continue the process of registration.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Person Enrollment</title>
        <para>After the  registration, the person needs to be enrolled in any available program. To enroll:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click  the <emphasis role="italic">Program management </emphasis>icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the person you would like to enroll.</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Click to modify.PNG" contentwidth="70%" align="center"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a program from the list  ( i.e., Death,  Child Health Program... )</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Select Program for person.PNG" align="center"/><warning>
                <para>This task can be executed after registration successfully, a  form like the form above is  showed up for enrollment.
</para>
              </warning></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>After the selection of program, you need to provide two dates:</para>
            <para>1) Date of enrollment : The date when person enrolls into the selected program.</para>
            <para>2) Date of incident: The date when the person got the disease or he/she has just been committed to an equivalent program for being followed-up.</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Provide two days.PNG" align="center"/></para>
            <warning>
              <para>The date of incident are very important to generate the activity plan for  each person. Health provider  needs to ensure  recording and reporting date of incidence with each case of multi events with registration. However,  the date is ignored with single event programs.</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click  the <emphasis role="italic">Enroll</emphasis> button to complete the enrollment process.</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Enroll to complete.PNG" align="center"/></para>
            <para>The system will automatically calculate  due-date for each the program stage  and will show same the below enrollment. In  health programme, a person  registered and enrolled, needs to be checked from time to time by health providers.
The case update  is designed in the same manner so that services which are received by the persons can be updated from time to time  when they visit the facility  or  whenever the health providers need to track.</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Complete.PNG" contentwidth="70%" align="center"/></para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title> Inputting data in treatment stages for each beneficiary</title>
        <para>We have two functionalities which support to  input data in  treatment stages for each beneficiary.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Single data entry.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Multiple data entry.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <section>
          <title>Single data entry</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>From the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> option, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click  it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.12</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.12.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 3.3.14</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.13.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Selection of a beneficiary and individual case</para>
              <para>In order to enter data, you  first have to select the facility for which beneficiaries belong to in order to enter data. Simply clicking  the concerned facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen.</para>
              <para>The next step is searching beneficiaries. Select a program in <emphasis role="italic">program</emphasis> list. The beneficiary list by the selected facility is shown. Each beneficiary in the list is shown with each corresponded stages.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.14</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.14.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Entering data for treatment case</para>
              <para>To open treatment form, click the <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the beneficiary you would like to enter data.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.15`</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.15.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Selection of the Program and Program Stage</para>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">What is program stage ?</emphasis> - This is to handle specific stages of a health program  because of  having multiple encounters for a given health program. E.g. once a pregnant woman enrolls to the &quot;ANC Program&quot;, she will get examination and treatments for the first trimester, the second trimester and/or the third trimester. These encounters in most cases are mandatory, and there will be dropouts in some cases, in which a pregnant woman should go through after she enrolled in the &quot;ANC Program&quot;. So the specific stages of the health program are defined when a health program is created/specified.</para>
              <para>Select the program and the program stage which you want to enter data for the selected beneficiary, then provide the <emphasis role="italic">Report Date</emphasis>  to open   the data entry form.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.16</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.16.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <para>After filling data into the data entry form, click on the <emphasis role="italic">Complete data entry</emphasis> button to complete the  data filling process for this stage.</para>
              <warning>
                <para>During each stage, the section related to that particular stage will be enabled for data entry form, rest of the sections will remain disabled in that particular stage. E.g. if data entry form of ANC registration stage is selected, then only data elements of ANC registration stage  will be enabled and the rest of the data elements of other stages will remain disabled.</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Multiple Data Entry for beneficiaries</title>
          <para>This is an advanced function for data entry. On the same interface on above, many beneficiaries are listed for  entering data by stages. </para>
          <para>To access the multiple beneficiary data entry module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Multiple Data Entry</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.1.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 1 - Show beneficiary list</emphasis>. You will first have to select the facility for which beneficiaries belong to in order to enter data. Simply clicking on the concerned facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen. The next step is listing all beneficiaries by the certain program as follows -</para>
          <para>1) Select a program in <emphasis role="italic">program</emphasis> list. The beneficiary list by the selected facility and program is shown. Each beneficiary in the list is shown with each corresponded stages.</para>
          <para>2)  Select an option from <emphasis role="italic">Sort by</emphasis>  box to sort by beneficiary&apos;s attributes.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 2 - Open treatment form</emphasis>. </para>
          <para>See the below figure illustrates for beneficiary named <emphasis role="italic">Nguyen Van Nam</emphasis>  and the second stage with name  <emphasis role="italic">At 6 weeks after birth</emphasis>.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.3</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.3.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para><screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.2</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.2.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 3 - Enter data</emphasis> ( arrow <emphasis role="italic">labelled 1</emphasis> in Fig. 2.5.3.3  ). After finishing the entering, close the pop-up ( arrow <emphasis role="italic">labelled 2</emphasis> in Fig. 2.5.3.3 )</para>
          <para>The benefits of this advanced function is to optimize the time-transition consuming when entering data for a long list beneficiaries by not switching the main window/interface.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Reports</title>
      <para>The sub module provides two functions for individual reports -<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Program summary - view the summary report to get an overview of the services provided for a program.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Tabular report  - an interactive reporting tool for tracker-data using tabular presentation with dynamic filters for each person attribute and data element. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
      <section>
        <title>Program summary</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Program summary</emphasis> provides a tool for   generating summary list of individual information with  color shown on program stages to identify status of receiving services in each stage.</para>
        <para>To access the program summary report, choose  <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> -&gt; <emphasis role="italic">Name-based Data Records</emphasis> &gt;  <emphasis role="italic">Program summary</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>Select a <emphasis role="italic">organisation unit</emphasis>  which provides services on the left menu. Then on the main page, select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Start date</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">End date </emphasis>to get period. Finally, click <emphasis role="italic">Generate</emphasis> button. </para>
        <para>The result is get based on the date of enrollment of each person who registered the selected organisation unit and enrolled in the selected program in the interval from start-date and end-date what health provider entered.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/program_summary_report.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>The color highlight the status of the stages -</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>PURPLE: Data entered and uncompleted stages.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>RED: Stages open but no data entered while the date estimated for closing/completing is over.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>YELLOW: Coming stages.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>GREEN: Compete stages.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
   </section>
  <section>
    <title>Person Aggregation Query Builder</title>
    <para>This is the core functionality for linking data between name-based information tracking system  and aggregate management system  by defining the linking/aggregating rules.</para>
    <para>This provides two functions - </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Person aggregation query builder management</emphasis> is a tool for defining formulas, expressions, rules for aggregation data from name-based to aggregation system.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Person aggregation</emphasis> is  used for generating routine data values from name-based-data by period and organization unit.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Person aggregation query builder management</title>
      <para>To access <emphasis role="italic">Aggregation Query Builder</emphasis> module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option. Select <emphasis role="italic">Aggregation Query Builder</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.2</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.2.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>After click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button, the following will appear:</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.3</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/create_new_person_aggregate_query_builder.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">Name:</emphasis>
        </emphasis> Provide name of query,  this name is usually same with the name of aggregate data element. For example Number of mothers got VAT, Number of children got BCG vaccine,...</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">
            <emphasis role="underline">Dataset:</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
        </emphasis> Select dataset contains data elements which will be used to link with individual data.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">Data element: </emphasis>
        </emphasis>Select aggregate data element which will be used to link with individual data.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Operator</emphasis>:</emphasis> Select Number of persons if aggregate based on persons, or Number of visits if aggregate data based on  times that persons received services.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Program</emphasis>: </emphasis>Select program   needed for aggregation.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Program Stage</emphasis>: </emphasis>Select program stage from the selected program above.</para>
      <para>Next section included 3 tabs: <emphasis role="italic">Data elements</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Person attributes</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>. Depend on the requirement of data aggregation, data element, person attributes, and number of programs are selected. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">Data elements tab:</emphasis>
        </emphasis> List all available data elements  from selected program stage. To create a formula related to each data element, double click on the   data element. The formula of the data element is filled on the condition field,  like [DE:1.2.3], in with: </para>
      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>1 - id of  the selected program.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>2 - id of the selected program stage.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>3 - id of the selected data element.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
      <note>
        <para>The formula can be create without any program stage, like [DE:1.*.3]</para>
      </note>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">Person attribute tab: </emphasis>
        </emphasis>List all available fixed attributes, such as gender, DOB type, Age(days), .. and user-defined attributes. Besides, provide a formula for calculating number of persons who registered in system. However, if a program without registration is selected,  person attributes aren&apos;t shown.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">Program tab:</emphasis>
        </emphasis> Provide formulas for calculating data value related to the selected program and program stage - </para>
      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The number of persons who enrolled the selected program.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The number of persons / times that ( Date of enrollment - Date of incident ) is greater then a certain number.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The number of persons who visited the selected program stage OR the number of visits what are registered in the system.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The number of persons  by age at the report-time.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">Condition: </emphasis>
        </emphasis>This section contains comparing operations (&lt;, &lt;=, &gt;, &gt;=, =, != ), calculation operation (+), priority operation ( ( ) ), boolean values (Yes, No), status operations (=NULL, != NULL), relation operations (AND, OR). These operations are used for supporting in setting condition for query. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">
          <emphasis role="underline">Description :</emphasis>
        </emphasis> Show description for the condition above. </para>
      <para>E.g To get number of <emphasis role="italic">girls</emphasis> who got <emphasis role="italic">Vitamin A dose 6</emphasis> enrolled <emphasis role="italic">Child Health program</emphasis> on <emphasis role="italic">January 2012</emphasis>. Then query is created as in the figure below. Note that January 2012 is period parameter which user will select when generate report. It is not set in the query.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Fig. example_query</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example_query.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Person Aggregation</title>
      <para>After created query, user can use  <emphasis role="italic">Person Aggregation</emphasis> module to aggregate persons data and import into aggregated data element. To open <emphasis>Person Aggregation</emphasis> module, from the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name-Based Data Records</emphasis> option. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person Aggregation</emphasis> option on left menu.  <emphasis>Person Aggregation form</emphasis> is opened as below -</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.4</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/person_aggregation_form.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>In the <emphasis>Person aggregation form</emphasis> above</para>
      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select <emphasis role="italic">dataset</emphasis> from Dataset List to get aggregate values. Note that only datasets which were assigned to at least one organisation unit will be shown in this list.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Depend on frequency of the selected dataset, select <emphasis role="italic">period</emphasis> to get aggregate data. For example, if frequency of dataset is quarterly, then select begin quarter and end quarter. To select a particular quarter, then begin quarter and end quarter is the same particular quarter name.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select <emphasis role="italic">organisation unit level</emphasis> where person data will be select to aggregate. There are 3 options - </para>
            <para>- Children only: Individual data from the children of  the selected organisation unit will be aggregated.</para>
            <para>-  Selected: Individual  data from the selected organisation unit will be aggregated. </para>
            <para>- All: Individual data from both selected organisation unit and its children will be aggregated.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the 
<emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> button to execute aggregate function. The <emphasis>Person aggregation result</emphasis>page is opened as below figure -</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure - Person aggregation result</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/person_aggregation_result.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>In <emphasis>Person aggregation result</emphasis> page -<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="italic">Save all values</emphasis> button to save all aggregated data values .</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click<emphasis role="italic"> orange arrow</emphasis> next to period name for showing list of aggregated data values at this period. Select only necessary data values and click <emphasis role="italic">Save</emphasis> selected values to save them</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis>Show details</emphasis> icon  to view detail  information which aggregated.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Sample of person aggregation</title>
      <para>E.g.  Find the number of the children vaccinated BCG by defining a linking rule between the data elements of aggregate dataset named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis>  and the data element of a program stage named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given</emphasis>.<orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Data Element and Indicators</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Element</emphasis> option to define two new data elements -</para>
            <para><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Patient</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Datasets</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Dataset</emphasis> option to create a new dataset named <emphasis role="italic">BCG Report</emphasis> and add <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> data element into the dataset.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option   and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis> option to create a program named <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis> with a stage named <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> and add the <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given</emphasis> data element into this stage.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a new person aggregation query builder named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG Builder </emphasis>to linking between the data elements.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example agg query builder.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Name-Based Data Records </emphasis>option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person</emphasis> option below <emphasis role="italic">Registration</emphasis> header in the left menu to register three persons named <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis> in <emphasis role="italic">Ngelehun CHC</emphasis> and enroll them into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>For  <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis>, open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>. Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2012-01-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>For  <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis>, open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into Child Health Program. Enter Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2012-01-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>For    <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis>,  no enter any data value for <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage.</para>
                <warning>
                  <para>Before entering data value for the stage, choose <emphasis role="italic">Report Date</emphasis> as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2012-01-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
                </warning>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Name-Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person aggregation</emphasis> option to run<emphasis role="italic"> Number of children - BCG Builder</emphasis> to get data value  and save it into database.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.5</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example person aggregation.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.6 - Result after running the query builder</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/example_person_aggregation_result.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Persons and Programs maintenance</title>
    <para>The content in this part is for the expert users or administrative users who are capable and responsible for development and change.</para>
    <para>Each of the options for the maintenance will be described in the following section<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Attribute</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view Person attributes. An attribute can be used to register extra information for a Person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Attribute Group</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view Person attribute groups. Groups makes it more convenient to add attributes to a Person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Identifier Type</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view Person identifier types. Any type and multiple identifiers can be registered.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Relationship Type</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view relationship types. A relationship is typically wife and husband or mother and child.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Program</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view programs. A program has program stages and defines which actions should be taken at each stage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Person Aggregation Query Builder</para>
          <para>Define formulas, expressions, rules for aggregation data from name-based to aggregation system</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Validation Criteria</para>
          <para>Create, modify and view validation criteria. A criteria is used for validation of Person data. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>he options for the maintenance will be described in the following section - </para>
    <section>
      <title>Person attribute</title>
      <section>
        <title>Creating and Editing person attributes</title>
        <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Persons and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Person Attribute</emphasis> option to create/editing a  person attribute. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.1.1</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.1.1.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>After, click on <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Attribute Management</emphasis> window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Beneficiary Attribute Management</emphasis> window.<screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.1.2</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.1.2.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot><screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.1.3</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.1.3.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot></para>
        <para>Basic information</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of beneficiary attribute.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Description of beneficiary attribute.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Mandatory</emphasis>: Entering value for this attribute is required or not.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Inheritable</emphasis>: </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of characters</emphasis>: Maximum number of characters for value inputed.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Value Type</emphasis>: Data type of value inputed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Define a beneficiary attribute group</title>
        <para>To access the beneficiary attribute group maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Attribute Group</emphasis> option to create a new an attribute group.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.2.1</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.2.1.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>To create a new attribute group, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Attribute Group</emphasis> window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Beneficiary Attribute Group</emphasis> window , click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill in the <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis> fields and then select attributes that should belong to the group from the left panel. </para>
        <para>Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected items</emphasis> button to add the selected attributes to the attribute group. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected items</emphasis> button to remove attributes from the group that have been selected in the right panel. </para>
        <para>Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes..</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.1.2.2</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.1.2.2.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Define a beneficiary identifier type</title>
      <para>To access the beneficiary identifier type maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Identifier Type</emphasis> option to create a new identifier type.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.2a</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.2a.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>To creating a  new identifier type, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Identifier Type Management </emphasis>window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add New Beneficiary Identifier Type</emphasis> window.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.2b</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.2b.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Basic information -</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of identifier type.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Description of identifier type.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Mandatory</emphasis>: Entering value for the  identifier is required or not.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Related</emphasis>: </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of characters</emphasis>: Maximum number of characters for value inputed. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Type</emphasis>: Data type of value inputted.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Define a relationship type</title>
      <para>Relationship type section provides a mechanism for defining any relationship types and link beneficiaries through these relationship types by creating specific relationships.</para>
      <para>To access the relationship type maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Relationship Type</emphasis> option to create a new relationship type.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.3a</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.3a.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>To define a new relationship type, click  <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button into <emphasis role="italic">Relationship Type Management </emphasis>window to go to <emphasis role="italic">Add new Relationship Type</emphasis> window.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Fig 2.7.3b</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.3b.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Beneficiary Registration</title>
      <para>Beneficiary registration section provides a mechanism for managing facilities which allow to registry new beneficiaries or not.</para>
      <para>To access the beneficiary registration maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Registration</emphasis>  option to select facilities. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Fig. 2.7.4</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.7.4.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <warning>
        <para>There are two process for registering facilities. The first one is where the administrator will say which facility can register. The second is when end user logs in and then select a facility, system will display a waring message if the selected facility cannot register beneficiaries; else, the system will display the functions to register beneficiaries.</para>
      </warning>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Define a new program</title>
      <section>
        <title>Define a new program</title>
        <para>Program section provides a mechanism for defining a health program. All name based case entry is organised through the use of programs.

</para>
        <para>To access the program maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>  option to create a new program.</para>
        <para>To create a new program, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and then click the &quot;Add&quot; button.</para>
        <para><screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.1.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot></para>
        <para>Basic information :</para>
        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: The name of the program</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Descriptions, meanings, explanation, etc. of/about the program</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Date of Enrolment Description</emphasis>: The date in which a beneficiary is registered to the system.
For example: the date in which a beneficiary enrols to the system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Date of Incidence Description</emphasis>: The date when the beneficiary got the disease or he/she has just been committed to an equivalent program for being followed-up. E.g. In the Immunization program for child under 1yr old, the incident date is the birthday; in the maternal program, the incident date is the date of last menstrual period (LMP).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of max days allowed to input data</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Define stages for a health program</title>
        <para>To define a program stage, click the <emphasis role="italic">Program Stage Management</emphasis>  icon (Fig. 2.5.1.2a) and then <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button  (Fig. 2.5.1.2b). Fill in the <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis> fields and then select the data elements that should belong to the group from the left panel. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected</emphasis> button to add the selected data elements to the right panel. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected</emphasis> button to remove data elements that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2a</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2a.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2b</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2b.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2c</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2c.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Fig. 2.5.1.2c illustrates for stage named <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> of  <emphasis role="italic">Child Health</emphasis> program.
More explanation for the figure:</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="italic">
              <emphasis role="italic">
                <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue frame labelled 1:</emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of the stage</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: The description of the stage</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Min no of days to wait from start of Program</emphasis>:  The minimum number of days to wait for starting the program</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>: The name of the program which is already defined before.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">
            <emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="italic">
                <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue arrow and labelled 2:</emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <para>Choose the data elements from the list on the left to the right one. These chosen elements are highlighted with BLUE color.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">
            <emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="italic">
                <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue arrow and labelled 3:</emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <para>Function area with button labeled <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis>, see the arrow labelled 3 and in BLUE to execute the function.</para>
        <para>If successfully, the new stages will showed in the list of stages:</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2d</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2d.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Your program will then be ready to be used to enroll beneficiaries (which are modified/created under <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance-&gt;Beneficiaries and Programs-&gt;Beneficiaries</emphasis>) and enter data under the data-entry function <emphasis role="italic">Services-&gt;Name Based Data Records-&gt;Data Entry</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">Multiple Data. Entry</emphasis> for the facilities that you have assigned.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Other functionalities</title>
        <para>You can assign the facilities to a program in the Program Management ( in which a list of available programs are shown) by clicking on the blue folder icon, which is the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the program you would like to modify.

</para>
        <para>The function <emphasis role="italic">Define Program Validation</emphasis> is designed for defining validations of a program in which you would like to modify after entering patient data values for program stages.

For instance, Parity, Previous live birth male, Previous live birth female, Previous still birth are patient data elements. They belong to many stages. And if data value of Parity is 0, then ( Previous live birth female + Previous still birth ) = 0. Besides, if a patient data element exists into many program stages, the system will check whether the values of the patient data element are in all program stages of the program or not.

For instance, TT1 is a patient data element. It exists into program stages as follows Checkup 1, Checkup 2, Checkup 3. If the data value of this data element into Checkup 1 is null, the data values into Checkup 2, Checkup 3 should be null.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Define validation criteria</title>
      <para>Validation criteria section provide a mechanism for defining criteria for beneficiaries when enrolling a program.

</para>
      <para>To access the validation criteria maintenance module, from <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Validation Criteria</emphasis>  option to create a new program</para>
      <para>To create a new validation criterion, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and click <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button.

</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo/>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.6.6.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>You can assign facilities to a validation criterion in the <emphasis role="italic">Validation Criteria Management </emphasis>(list of available validation criteria are shown) by clicking the blue folder icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the validation criterion you would like to assign. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Move selected</emphasis> button to add the selected programs to the validation criterion. Click the <emphasis role="italic">Remove selected</emphasis> button to remove programs from the group that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the <emphasis role="italic">Save</emphasis> button to save changes, or the <emphasis role="italic">Cancel</emphasis> button to discard any changes.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
