<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Data dimensions in DHIS2</title>
  <section>
    <title>The core building blocks describing the data</title>
    <para>A data value in DHIS2 (core module for aggregated data) is at minimum described by three dimensions, 1) data element, 2) organisation unit, and 3) period, which also forms the core building blocks of the data model. E.g. if you want to know how many children that were immunised for measles in Gerehun CHC in December 2009, the three dimensions to that value are the Data Element &quot;Measles doses given&quot;, the Organisation Unit &quot;Gerehun CHC&quot;, and the Period &quot;Dec-09&quot;. All data values have at least these three dimensions describing What, Where and When.</para>
    <para><table frame="all">
        <title/>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2"/>
          <colspec colname="c3"/>
          <colspec colname="c4"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Organisation Unit</entry>
              <entry>Data Element</entry>
              <entry>Period</entry>
              <entry>Value</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
              <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
              <entry>Dec-09</entry>
              <entry>22</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
              <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
              <entry>Dec-09</entry>
              <entry>18</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The data element dimension</title>
    <section>
      <title>Data element categories</title>
      <para>The data element above called &quot;Measles doses given&quot;, although capturing the core essence of what the data is can be further elaborated and disaggregated into what is called data element categories. The system administrators of DHIS are free to define any data element category dimensions to data elements using the user interface for this in the data element maintenance section, but here are some examples of possible categories to use.</para>
      <para>Given the example of Measles vaccination, if you want to know whether these vaccines were given at the facility (fixed) or out in the community as part of the outreach services then you could add a dimension called e.g. &quot;Place of service&quot; with the two possible options &quot;Fixed&quot; and &quot;Outreach&quot;. Then all data collected on measles immunisation would have to be disaggregated along these to options. In addition to this you might be interested in knowing how many of these children who were under 1 year or  above 1 year of age. If so you can add an Age dimension to the data element with the two possible options &quot;&lt;1 y&quot; and &quot;&gt;1 y&quot;. This implies further detail on the data collection process. You can also apply both categories Place of service and Age and combine these into a data element category combination e.g. called &quot;EPI disaggregation&quot;  and thereby you would be able to look at 4 different more detailed values in stead of only 1 as in the example above for the data element &quot;Measles doses given&quot;: 1) &quot;Fixed and &lt;1 y, 2) Fixed and &gt;1 y, 3) Outreach and &lt;1 y, and 4) Outreach and &gt;1 y. This adds complexity to how data is collected by the health facilities, but at the same time opens up for new possibilities of detailed data analysis of Measles immunisation.</para>
      <para><table frame="all">
          <title> Example of detailed storage of data values when using data element categories &quot;Place of Service&quot; and &quot;Age&quot; (simplified for readability compared to the actual database table)</title>
          <tgroup cols="6">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <colspec colname="c3"/>
            <colspec colname="c4"/>
            <colspec colname="c5"/>
            <colspec colname="c6"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Organisation Unit</entry>
                <entry>Data Element</entry>
                <entry>Place of service</entry>
                <entry>Age</entry>
                <entry>Period</entry>
                <entry>Value</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Fixed</entry>
                <entry>&lt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>12</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Outreach</entry>
                <entry>&lt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>4</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Fixed</entry>
                <entry>&gt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>4</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Outreach</entry>
                <entry>&gt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>2</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Fixed</entry>
                <entry>&lt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>10</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Outreach</entry>
                <entry>&lt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>4</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Fixed</entry>
                <entry>&gt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>3</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>Outreach</entry>
                <entry>&gt;1 y</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>1</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Data element group sets</title>
      <para>While the data element categories and their options described above dictated the level of detail (disaggregation) at the point of data collection and how data values get stored in the database, the data element group sets and groups can be used to add more information to data elements after data collection. E.g. if looking at a lot of data elements at the same time in a report you would want to group these based on some criteria, e.g. if looking at all the data captured in a form for immunisation and nutrition you might want to separate or group data elements along a programme dimension (called group set) where &quot;Immunisation&quot; (or EPI) and &quot;Nutrition&quot; would be the two groups. Expanding the report to include data from other programs or larger themes of health data would mean more groups to such a group set dimension, like &quot;Malaria&quot;, &quot;Reproductive Health&quot;, &quot;Stocks&quot;. For this example you would create a data element group set called &quot;Programme&quot; (or whatever name you find appropriate), and to represent the different programmes in this dimension  you would define data elements groups called &quot;EPI&quot;, &quot;Nutrition&quot;, &quot;Malaria&quot;, &quot;Reproductive health&quot; and so on, and add all these groups to the &quot;Programme&quot; group set. To link or tag the data element &quot;Measles doses given&quot; to such a dimension you must (in our example) add it to the &quot;EPI&quot; group. Which groups you add &quot;Measles doses given&quot; to does not affect how health facilities collect the data, but adds more possibilities to your data analysis. So for the group set dimensions there are three levels; the group set (e.g. &quot;Programme&quot;), the group (e.g. &quot;EPI&quot;), and the data element (e.g. &quot;Measles doses given&quot;).</para>
      <para>Indicators can be grouped into indicator groups and further into indicator group sets (dimensions) in exactly the same way as data elements.</para>
      <para><table frame="all">
          <title/>
          <tgroup cols="5">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <colspec colname="c3"/>
            <colspec colname="c4"/>
            <colspec colname="c5"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Organisation Unit</entry>
                <entry>Data Element</entry>
                <entry>Programme</entry>
                <entry>Period</entry>
                <entry>Value</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>EPI</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>22</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Vitamin A given</entry>
                <entry>Nutrition</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>16</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>EPI</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>18</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Vitamin A given</entry>
                <entry>Nutrition</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>12</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Malaria new cases</entry>
                <entry>Malaria</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>32</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Malaria new cases</entry>
                <entry>Malaria</entry>
                <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                <entry>23</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The organisation unit dimension</title>
    <para>Organisation units in DHIS2 can be either any type of health facility like Community Health Centres or referral hospitals, or an administrative unit like &quot;MoHS Sierra Leone&quot;, &quot;Bo District&quot; or &quot;Baoma Chiefdom&quot;. Orgunits are represented in a default hierarchy following the health system at large, and are therefore assigned an organisational level. E.g. Sierra Leone has 4 levels; National, District, Chiefdom, and PHU, and all orgunits are linked to one of these levels. An orgunit hierarchy in DHIS can have any number of levels. Normally data is collected at the lowest level, at the PHUs, and then data values are linked to individual PHUs.  When designing reports at higher levels with data aggregated by chiefdom or district, the DHIS will use the hierarchy structure to sum up all the health facilities&apos; data for any given unit at any level. The orgunit level capturing the data always represents the lowest level of detail that is possible to use in data analysis, and the organisational levels define the available levels of aggregation along a geographical dimension.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Organisation unit group sets and groups</title>
      <para>While PHU is the lowest geographical level for disaggregation in DHIS2 there are ways to flexibly group organisation units into any number of dimensions by using the group sets and groups functionality. E.g. if all PHUs are given an official type like CHC, CHP, MCHP etc. it is possible to create an orgunit group set called &quot;Orgunit type&quot; and add groups with the names of the  types mentioned above. Then you can link your orgunits to their corresponding groups (orgunit types). Other common orgunit dimensions are Rural/Urban (Rural, Urbal, Peri-urban), and Ownership (Public, Private. NGO etc.). When analysing data from the PHU level it then becomes possible to aggregate data by these dimensions, e.g. look at Measles immunisation in BO district by the type of PHU in stead of the PHUs themselves.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Alternative orgunit hierarchies - advanced use of group sets and groups</title>
        <para>A more advanced use of orgunit group sets and groups is to create alternative hierarchies e.g. use administrative borders from other ministries. In Sierra Leone that could mean an alternative hierarchy of 1:MoHS, 2:Districts, and 3: Local councils,  instead of the 4 level hierarchy with  chiefdoms and PHUs. E.g. if all PHUs where linked to a specific local council it would be possible to look at data aggregated by local council instead of chiefdom. Then you would first need to create a group set called &quot;Local council&quot; and then create one orgunit group for every local council, and finally link all PHUs to their corresponding local council group.</para>
        <para><table frame="all">
            <title/>
            <tgroup cols="5">
              <colspec colname="c1"/>
              <colspec colname="c2"/>
              <colspec colname="c3"/>
              <colspec colname="c4"/>
              <colspec colname="c5"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>District</entry>
                  <entry>OrgUnit Type</entry>
                  <entry>Data Element</entry>
                  <entry>Period</entry>
                  <entry>Value</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Bo</entry>
                  <entry>CHC</entry>
                  <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                  <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                  <entry>121</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Bo</entry>
                  <entry>CHP</entry>
                  <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                  <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                  <entry>98</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Bo</entry>
                  <entry>MCHP</entry>
                  <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                  <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                  <entry>87</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Bombali</entry>
                  <entry>CHC</entry>
                  <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                  <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                  <entry>110</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Bombali</entry>
                  <entry>CHP</entry>
                  <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                  <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                  <entry>67</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Bombali</entry>
                  <entry>MCHP</entry>
                  <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                  <entry>Dec-09</entry>
                  <entry>59</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Best practice on the use of group sets and groups</title>
      <para>Groups that are not members of group sets are more or less useless for analysis (should we allow this at all?). With all the groups you get by e.g. including all different diagnoses as groups the full list of groups does not makes sense in any pivot table, and you easily get duplicates in your pivot tables since data elements or indicators are members of multiple groups. This can be controlled by the use of group sets. So the recommodation is to assign all your groups to a group set, and then you pull the group sets you need into your reports and analysis. </para>
      <para>It is also recommended to have one group set that is used for the major organising of all data in e.g. a pivot table, e.g use health programs or other larger themes for data elements or indiactors that together cover all the data. That will provide a nicely organised overview of all your raw data or indicator data.</para>
      <para>The resource table gives all groupsets as columns with groups as rows, and 1 DE per row.
This means that all groupsets are joined in when e.g. creating a view to a pivot table. Resource tables have to be generated from the Mainteance-&gt;Data Administration-&gt;Resource Table window, and more information on this is available in a later chapter called Data Administration in DHIS2 or from the inline help text in that window. 
</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The time (period) dimension</title>
    <para>The period dimension becomes an important factor when analysing data over time e.g. when looking at cumulative data, when creating quarterly or annual aggregated reports, or when doing analysis that combines data with different characteristics like monthly routine data, annual census/population data or six-monthly staff data.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Period Types</title>
      <para>In DHIS2 the periods are organised according to a set of fixed period types: 1) Daily, 2) Weekly, 3) Monthly, 4) Quarterly, 5) Six-monthly, 6) Yearly, 7) Two-yearly, and 8) a special period type called Relative.

</para>
      <para>As a rule of thumb all organisation units should collect the same data using the same frequency or periodicity, so first of all the periods play an important role in standardising data collection across the country. A data entry form therefore needs to know its period type to make sure data is always collected according to the correct and same periodicity across the country. </para>
      <para>It is possible however to collect the same data elements using different period types by assigning the same data elements to multiple data sets with different period types, however then it becomes crucial to make sure no orgunit is collecting data using both data sets/period types as that would create overlap and duplication of data values. If set up correctly the aggregation service in DHIS2 (through datamart and report tables) will aggregate the data together, e.g. the monthly data from one part of the country woth quarterly data from another part of the country into a national quarterly report. For simplicicty and to avoid data duplication we stronly advice to use the same period type for all orgunits for the same data elements when possible. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Relative periods</title>
      <para>When creating reports within the DHIS (report tables, standard reports, charts) it is possible to make use of the relative periods functionality. The simplest scenario is when you want to design a monthly report that can be reused every month without having to make changes to the report template to accomodate for the changes in period. The relative period called reporting_month allows for this, and the user can at the time of report gemeration  through  a report parameter select the month to use in the report.  </para>
      <para>A slightly more advanced use case is  when you want to make a monthly summary report for immunisation and want to look at the data from the current (reporting) month together with a cumulative value for the year so far. The relative period called &quot;So far this year&quot; provides such a cumulative value relative to the reporting month selecting when running the report. Other relative periods are the last 3,6, 9 or 12 months periods which are cumulative values calculated back from the selected reporting month. If you want to create a report with data aggregated by quarters (the ones that have passed so far in the year) you can select &quot;Individual quarters this year&quot;. Other relative periods are described under the reporting table section of the manual. Common for all the relative periods is that they are relative to a selected reporting month. Even quarterly or annual reports need to know their reporting month to derive the year, the quarter and so on. The reporting month then becomes one of the report parameters the users have to select when running a report based on relative periods.</para>
      <para><table frame="all">
          <title/>
          <tgroup cols="5">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <colspec colname="c3"/>
            <colspec colname="c4"/>
            <colspec colname="c5"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Organisation Unit</entry>
                <entry>Data Element</entry>
                <entry>Reporting month</entry>
                <entry>So far this year</entry>
                <entry>Reporting month name</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Gerehun CHC</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>15</entry>
                <entry>167</entry>
                <entry>Oct-09</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Tugbebu CHP</entry>
                <entry>Measles doses given</entry>
                <entry>17</entry>
                <entry>155</entry>
                <entry>Oct-09</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Aggregation of periods</title>
      <para>While data needs to be collected on a given frequency to standardise data collection and management, this does not put limitations on the period types that can be used in data analysis and reports. Just like data gets aggregated up the organisational hierarchy, data is also aggregated according to a period hierarchy, so you can create quarterly and annual reports based on data that is being collected on a Monthly basis. The defined period type for a data entry form (data set) defines the lowest level of period detail possible in a report.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Sum and average aggregation along the period dimension</title>
        <para>When aggregating data on the period dimension there are two options for how the calculation is done; 1) sum and 2) average, which is specified per data element in the DHIS2 through the use of the &apos;aggregation operator&apos; attribute in the Add/Edit Data Elements window.

</para>
        <para>Most of the data collected on a routinely basis should be aggregated by summing up the months or weeks, e.g. you create a quarterly report on Measles immunisation by summing up the three monthly values for &quot;Measles doses given&quot;. 

</para>
        <para>Other types of data that are more permanently valid over time like &quot;Number of staff in the PHU&quot; or an annual population estimate of &quot;Population under 1 year&quot; need to be aggregated differently. These values are static for all months as long as there are valid data. E.g. the estimated population under 1 calculated from the census data is the same for all months in a year, or the number of nurses working in a PHU is the same for every month in the 6 months period the number is reported for. 

</para>
        <para>This difference e.g. becomes important when calculating an annual value for the indicator morbidity service burden for a PHU. The monthly headcounts are summed up for the 12 months to get the annual headcount while the number of staff for the PHU is calculated as the average of the two 6-monthly values reported through the 6-monthly staff report. So in this example the data element &quot;OPD heahcount&quot; would have the aggregation operator &quot;sum&quot; and the data element &quot;Number of staff&quot; would have it set to &quot;average&quot;.

</para>
        <para>Another important feature of average data elements is the validity period concept. Average data values are standing values for any period type within the borders of the period they are registered for. E.g. an annual population estimate following the calendar year will have the same value for any period that falls within that year no matter what the period type. E.g. if the population under 1 for a Tugbebu CHP is 250 for the year of 2009 that means that the value will be 250 for Jan-09, for Q3-09, for Week 12 of 2009 and for any period within 2009. This has implications for how e.g coverage indicators are calculated as the full annual population will be used as denominator value even when doing monthly reports. If you want to look at an estimated annual coverage value for a given month then you will have the option of setting the indicator to &quot;Annualised&quot; which means that a monthly coverage value will be multiplied by 12, a quarterly value by 4 etc. The annualised indicator feature can therefore be used to mimic the use of monthly population estimates.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Data collection vs. data analysis</title>
    <section>
      <title>Data collection and storage</title>
      <para>The datasets determine what raw data that is available in the system as they describe how data is collected. Through the data sets we define the building blocks of the data to be captured and stored in the DHIS. For each data dimension we decide what level of detail the data should be collected on; 1) the data element (e.g. diagnosis, vaccine, or any event taking place) and its categories (e.g. age and gender), 2) the period/frequency dimension, and 3) the orgunit dimension.  For any report or data analysis you can never retrieve more detailed data than what is defined in the datasets so the design of the datasets and their corresponding data entry forms (the data collection tools) dictate what kind of data analysis that will be possible.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>INPUT != OUTPUT</title>
      <para>It is important to understand that the data entry forms or datasets themselves are not linked to the data (values) and that  the meaning of data (the What) is only described by the data element (and its categories). This makes it perfectly safe to modify datasets and forms without altering the data (as long as the data elements stay the same). This loose coupling between forms and data makes DHIS  flexible when it comes to designing and changing new forms and in providing exactly the form the users want.   </para>
      <para>Another benefit of only linking data to data elements and not to forms is the flexibility of creating indicators and validation rules based on data elements, and also in providing any kind of output report (in pivot tables, charts, maps etc) that can combine data individually or across forms, e.g. to correlate data from different health programs. Due to this flexibility of enabling integration of data from various programs (forms) and sources (routine and semi permanent (population, staff, equipment)) a DHIS database is used as an integrated data repository for many or all parts of the aggregated data in a larger HIS. The figure below illustrates this flexibility.</para>
      <para>
<screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/dhis_input_output.JPG" format="JPG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Some more examples</title>
    <para>The table below combines data element the two group sets Diagnosis (all the diseases) and Morbidity/Mortality (New cases, Follow-ups, Refrerrals, Deaths) with the data element category PHU/Community. Deaths are captured in a separate form with other dimensions (e.g. the PHU/Community) than morbidity.</para>
    <para>
<screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/Ex_table1.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
</para>
    <para>This output table combines the two data element categories HIV_Age and Gender with the data element group set ART Group. The group enables subtotals for staging and entry points summing up the data elements in that group. Subtotals for either age groups and gender would be other possible columns to easily include  here.</para>
    <para>
<screenshot>
        <screeninfo>DHIS2 Login screen</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/Ex_table2.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>How this works in pivot tables</title>
    <para>When doing data analysis in Excel pivot tables or any other OLAP based tool the dimensions become extremely powerful in providing many different views into the data. Each data element category or group set become a pivot field, and the options or groups become values within each of these fields. In fact categories and groupsets are treated exactly the same way in pivot tables, and so are orgunits, periods, and data elements. All these become dimensions to the data value that can be used to rearrange, pivot, filter, and to drill down into the data. Here we will show some examples of how the data dimensions are used in pivot tables.  </para>
    <para>Using the example of morbidity and mortality data, a pivot table can show how the  dimensions can be used to view data for different aggregation levels.

</para>
    <para>The completely aggregated number is viewed when none of the pivot fields are arranged in the table area, as column or row fields, but are listed above the table itself  as page field (filter).
</para>
    <para>
<screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/pivot_overview_1.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
</para>
    <para>Here we have selected to look at the Morbidity total. The various data elements on morbidity have been ordered into the main_de_groups Morbidity (we will get back to Mortality later). The fields above the table itself are all set to &quot;All&quot;, meaning that the totals in the table will contain data from all Countries, Districts, Chiefdom, ou_type, year, months, the various categories as listed in the red fields, and all data elements in the Morbidity group.</para>
    <para>As we have seen, this is not a very useful representation, as Morbidity is organized into new cases, follow-ups, referrals, and then again in age groups. Also, we do not see the various diagnoses. The first step is to include the diagnoses field (which is a group set), which is done by dragging the &quot;diagnosis&quot; field down to be a row field, as shown in the figure below, and to add the group set called &quot;morbiditymortality&quot; in the column field to display new cases, follow-up, and referrals.</para>
    <para>
<screenshot>
        <screeninfo>DHIS2 Login screen</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/pivot_diagnoses.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
</para>
    <para>Contrast this figure above to the one below.</para>
    <para>
<screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/pivot_dataelements.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
</para>
    <para>They both show the same data (some of teh rows have been cut in the screenshot due to image size), albeit in a different way. </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The &quot;dataelement&quot; field, used in the bottom figure, displays each diagnosis as three elements; one follow-up, one new, and one referrals. This is the way the data elements have been defined in DHIS, as this makes sense for aggregation. You would not like to aggregate follow-ups and new, thus these have not been made as categories, the whole point of is to ease aggregation and disaggregation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The &quot;diagnosis&quot; group set has instead been made to lump these three (follow-up, new, referrals) together, which can then be split with another group set, namely the one called &quot;morbiditymortality&quot;. This allows us to organize the data as in the first of the two figures, where we have the single diagnosis per row, and the groups new, follow-up, referrals as rows.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The idea of using group sets is that you can combine, in any set, different data elements. Thus, if we add the mortality data (by checking it from the drop-down menu of the main_de_groups field, and moving this field out of the table) we can see also the deaths, since the mortality data elements have been included as a &quot;death&quot; group in the &quot;morbiditymortality&quot; group set. The result is shown below.</para>
    <para>
<screenshot>
        <screeninfo>DHIS2 Login screen</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/pivot_diagnoses_all.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
</para>
    <para>The result is a much more user-friendly pivot table. Now, another figure shows the relationship between the group sets and elements (these are fake data values).</para>
    <para>

</para>
    <para>This small detail of the pivot table show how the actual data elements link to the group sets: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The four data elements, as defined in DHIS, are Measles death, Measles follow-up, Measles new, and Measles referrals</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>They all belong to the group set &quot;diagnosis&quot;, where they have been lumped together in the group Measles</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The group set &quot;morbiditymortality&quot; contains the groups New cases, Follow-up, Referrals, and Deaths.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Only the data element Measles deaths has data related to the group Deaths, thus this is where the data value (20) is shown, at the upper right corner. The same for Measles new; the value (224) is shown at the intersection of the data element Measles new and the group New cases (in the group set morbiditymortality)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All the intersections where the data element does not link with the groups in morbiditymortality are left blank. Thus in this case we would get a nice table if we excluded the dataelement from the table, and just had diagnosis and the group set morbiditymortality, as in the figure shown earlier</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Now lets see how the data element categories can be used. In the data entry form for Morbidity the new cases and follow-ups use one age category, the referral data another,, and the mortality data a third age breakup, so these are available as three individual age group fields in the pivot tables called morbidity_age, referrals_age and mortality_age. It doesn&amp;apos;t make sense to use these while looking at these data together (as in the examples above), but e.g. if we only want to look at the only the  new cases we can put the MobidityMortalityGroups field back up as a page field and there select the New cases group as a filter. Then we can drag the Morbidity_age field down to the column area and we get the following view:</para>
    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/pivot_morb_age.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>
    <para>The following table illustrates the benefits of reusing data element categories across datasets and catecorycombinations. The VCCT, ART and PMTCT data are collected in three different datasets, the first two with both gender and age breakdown, and the PMTCT only age (gender is given). All three share the same age groups and therefore it is possible to viev data elements from all these three datasets in the same table and use the age dimension. In the previous example with morbidity and mortality data this was not possible since new cases, referrals and deaths all have different age groups.</para>
    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_dimensions/pivot_hiv_age.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>  </para>
    <para>In the table below PMTCT data has been removed from the table and the gender category added to the column area so that you can analyse the data for VCCT and ART by age and gender. An optional subtotal for gender has also been  added, as well as a grand total for all age and gender.</para>
    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources\images\data_dimensions\pivot_hiv_age_gender.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>From paper for to multidimensional datasets - lessons learned</title>
    <para>Typically the design of a DHIS 2 dataset is based on some requirements from a paper form that is already in use. The logic of paper forms are not the same as the data element and data set model of DHIS, e.g. often a field in a tabular paper form is described both by column headings and text on each row, and sometimes also with some introductory table heading that provides more context. In the database this is captured in one atomic data element with no reference to a position in a visual table format, so it is important to make sure the data element with the optional data element categories capture the full meaning of each individual field in the paper form. </para>
    <para>Another important thing to have in mind while designing datasets is that the dataset and the corresponding data entry form (which is a dataset with layout) is a data collection tool and not  a report or analysis tool. There are other far more sophisticated tools for data output and reporting in DHIS than the data entry forms. Paper forms are often designed with both data collection and reporting in mind and therefore you might see things such as cumulative values (in addition to the monthly values), repetition of annual data (the same population data reported every month) or even indicator values such as coverage rates in the same form as the monthly raw data. When you store the raw data in DHIS every month and have all the processing power you need within the computerised tool there is no need (in fact it would be stupid and most likely cause inconsistency) to register manually calculated values such as the ones mentioned above. You only want to capture the raw data in your datasets/forms and leave the calculations to the computer, and presentation of such  values to the reporting tools in DHIS.</para>
    <section>
      <title>From tables to category combinations - designing multidimensional data sets</title>
      <para>As we have seen in the examples above the data element categories and their options are helpful in representing tabular data, when adding dimensions to a field in a paper form. We have also seen how the data element is the central dimension and that the data element categories are used to provide further details or disaggregation to the data element. As we will see in the example below there are often more than one way to represent a paper form in DHIS, and it can be difficult to know which dimension to represent with a data element name and which to represent as categories, or even as groups as we have seen above. Here are some general lessons learned from working with data element and category combinations:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Design your dimensions with data use in mind, not data collection. This means that disaggregation of data values at collection time should be easily aggregated up along the various dimensions, as in adding up to a meaningful total.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reuse dimensions as much as possible as it increased the ability to compare disaggregated data (e.g. age groups, fixed/outreach, gender). Not necessary to share all dimensions, it helps to share only one as well (much better than none).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Disaggregation dimensions should add up to a total</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Different levels of dimensions; 1) disaggregation and 2) grouping. Disaggregation dimensions dictate how you collect and how detailed you store your data, so plan these carefully. The group dimension is more flexible and can be changed and added to even after data collection (think of it as tagging). </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Think integrated data repository and not forms or programs when designing the metadata model and revising forms. Use the same disaggregation for the same or similar data across forms. Reuse definitions so that the database can integrate even though the forms might be duplicating. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">STEP BY STEP APPROACH TO DESIGNING DATASETS</emphasis></para>
      <para>1. Identify the different tables (or sub datasets) in the paper form that share the same dimensions</para>
      <para>2. For each table identify the dimensions that describe the data fields</para>
      <para>3. Identify the key dimension, the one that makes most sense to look at in isolation (when the others are collapsed, summed up). This is your data element dimension, the starting point and core of your multidimensional model (sub dataset). The data element dimension can be a merger of two or more dimensions if that makes more sense for data analysis. The key is to identify which total that makes most sense to look at alone when the other dimensions are collapsed.</para>
      <para>4. For all other/additional dimensions identify their options, and come up with explanatory names for dimensions and their options.</para>
      <para>5. Each of these additional dimensions will be a data element category and their options will be category options.</para>
      <para>6. Combine all categories for each sub dataset into one category combination and assign this to all the data elements in your table (or sub dataset if you like). </para>
      <para>7. When you are done with all the tables (sub datasets), create a new dataset and add all the data elements you have identified (in the whole paper form) to that dataset.</para>
      <para>8. Your dataset will then consist of a set of data elements that are linked to one or more category combinations. </para>
      <para>In order to better explain the approach and the possibilities we present an example paper form and will walk through it step by step and design data elements, categories, category options and category combinations.</para>
      <para><screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources\images\data_dimensions\PHUF3.jpg" format="JPG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot> </para>
      <para>This form has many tables and each of them potentially represent a data element category combination (from now on referred to as a catcombo). As such there is no restriction on a dataset to only have one set of dimensions or catcombo, it can have m For any and as we see above this is necessary as the dimensions are very different from table to table. We will walk through this table by table and discuss how to represent it in the DHIS.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">ANC table</emphasis>. This table in the top left corner is one the simpler ones in this form. It has two dimensions, the first column with the ANC activity or service (1st visit, IPT 2nd dose etc) and the 2nd and 3rd column which represent the place where the service was given with the two options fixed and outreach. Since the ANC service is the key phenomena to analyse here and often there is a need for looking at e.g. total of ANC 1st visits no matter where (fixed+outreach) it makes a lot of sense to use this dimension as the data element dimension. So all items on the first column from 1st ANC visit to 2nd IPT dose given by TBA are represented as individual data elements. The place dimension is represented as a data element category (from now on referred to as category) with the name &quot;fixed/outreach&quot; with the two data element category options (from now on catoptions) &quot;fixed&quot; and &quot;outreach&quot;. There is no other dimension here so we add a new catcombo with the name &quot;Fixed/Outreach&quot; with one category &quot;Fixed/Outreach&quot;. Strictly speaking there is another dimension in this table, and that is the at PHU or by TBA dimension which is repeated for the two doses of IPT, but since none of the other ANC services listed have this dimension it does not seem like a good idea to separate out two data elements from this table and give them another catcombo with both fixed/outreach and at PHU/by TBA. reusing the same catcombo for all the ANC services makes more sense since it will be easier to look at these together in reports etc. and also the fact that there is not much to loose by repeating the at PHU or by TBA information as part of the data element name when it is only for four data elements in a table of totally 11 data elements.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">DELIVERY table.</emphasis> This table is more tricky as it has a lot of information and you can see that not all the rows have the same columns (some columns are merged and a one field is grayed out/disabled.). If we start by looking at the first column &quot;Deliveries assisted by&quot; that seems to be one dimension, but only down to the &quot;Untrained TBA&quot; row, as the remaining three rows are not related to who assisted the delivery at all. Another dimension is the place of delivery, either In PHU or in Community as stated on the top column headings. These deliveries are further split into the outcome of the delivery, whether it is a live or still birth, which seems to be another dimension. So if we disregard the three bottom rows for a moment there seems to be 3 dimensions here, 1) assisted by, 2) place of delivery, and 3) delivery outcome. The key decision to make is what to use as the data element, the main dimension, the total that you will most often use and want easily available in reports and data analysis. We ended up using the outcome dimension as total live births is a very commonly used value in many indicators (maternal mortality ratio, births attended by skilled health personnel etc.). In this case the Assisted By dimension could also have been used without any problem, but the added value of easily getting the total live births information was the decisive point for us. This means that from this table (or subtable of row 1 to 6) there are only two data elements;  &quot;Live births&quot; and &quot;Still births&quot;. Then there are two more dimensions, the &quot;PHU/Community&quot; with its two options and a &quot;Births attended by&quot; with options (&quot;MCH Aides&quot;, &quot;SECHN&quot;, &quot;Midwives&quot;, &quot;CHO&quot;, &quot;Trained TBA&quot;, &quot;Untrained TBA&quot;). These two categories make up the catcombo &quot;Births&quot; which is assigned to the two data elements &quot;Live births&quot; and &quot;Still births&quot;.  Considering the final three rows of the delivery table we can see that &quot;Complicated Deliveries&quot; does not have the assisted by dimension, but has the place and the outcome. &quot;Low birth weight&quot; also does not have the assisted by dimension and not the outcome either. The LLITN given after delivery does not have any additional dimension at all.                      Since not any of the three rows can share catcombo with any other row  we decided to represent these fields as so called flat data elements, meaning data elements with no categories at all, and simply adding the additional information from the column headings to the data element name, and therefore ended up with the following data elements with the default (same as none) catcombo; &quot;Complicated deliveries in PHU live birth&quot;, &quot;Complicated deliveries in PHU still births&quot;, &quot;Complicated deliveries in community live birth&quot;, &quot;Complicated deliveries in community still births&quot;, &quot;Low birth weight in PHU&quot;, &quot;Low birth weight in community&quot;, and &quot;LLITN given after delivery&quot;.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">POST-NATAL CARE table</emphasis> This table is simple and we used the same approach as for the ANC table. 3 data elements listed in the first column and then link these to the catcombo called &quot;fixed/outreach&quot;. Reusing the same category fixed/outreach for these data elements enables analysis on fixed/outreach together with ANC data and other data using the same category.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TT table</emphasis> This is a bit more tricky. We decided to use &quot;TT1&quot;, &quot;TT2&quot; ... &quot;TT5&quot; as data elements which makes it easy to get the total of each one of these. There is fixed/outreach dimensio here, but there is also the In school place that is only applied to the Non-Pregnant, or more correctly to any of the two as the school immunisation is done whether the girls are pregnant or not. We consulted the program people behind the form and found out that it would be ok to register all school TT immunisations as non-pregnant, which simplifies the model a bit since we can reuse the &quot;TT1&quot; to &quot;TT5&quot; data elements. So we ended up with a new category called &quot;TT place&quot; with the three options (Fixed, Outreach, In School), and another category called &quot;Pregnant/Non-pregnant&quot; with two options. The new catcombo &quot;TT&quot; is then a combination of these two and applied to the 5 TT data elements. Since we agreed to put all In Schools immunisations under Non-pregnant in means that the combination of options (Pregnant+In School) will never be used in any data entry form, and hence become a passibe optioncombo, which is ok. As long as the form is custom designed then you can choose which combinations of options to use or not, and therefore it is not a problem to have such passive or unused catoptions. Having school as one option in the TT place category simplifies the model and therefore we thought it was worth it. The alternative would be to create 5 more data elements for &quot;TT1 in school&quot; ... &quot;TT5 in school&quot;, but then it would be a bit confusing to add these together with the &quot;TT1&quot; ...&quot;TT5&quot; plus TT catcombo. Having school as a place in the TT place category makes it a lot easier to get the total of TT1.. TT5 vaccines given, which are the most important numbers and most often used values for data analysis.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Complications of early and late pregnancy and labour tables</emphasis> We treat these two tables as one, and will explain why. These two tables are a bit confusing and not the best deisgn. The major data coming out of these tables are the pregnancy complications and the maternal deaths. These are the major things for data analysis. And then there is further detail on the cause of the complication or death (the first column in both tables), as well as a place of death (in PHU or community), and a outcome of the complication (when its not a death) that can be either Managed at PHU or Referred. We decided to create two data elements for these two tables; &quot;Pregnancy complications&quot;, and &quot;Maternal Deaths&quot;, and two category combinations, one for each of the data elements. For the Pregnancy Complications data element there are two additional dimensions, the cause of the complication (the combined list of  the first column in the two tables) and the outcome (managed at PHU or Referred), so these are the categories and options that make up that category combination. For the &quot;Maternal deaths&quot; data element the same category with the different causes are used and then another category for the place of death (in PHU or In community). This way the two data elements can share one category and it will be easy to derive the total number of pregnancy complications and maternal deaths. While the list of complications on the paper form is divided into two (early and late/labour) you can see that e.g. the malaria in 2nd and 3rd trimester are listed under early, but in fact are for a later phase of the pregnancy. There is no clear divide between early and late complications in the form, and therefore we gave up trying to make this distinction in the database. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Family Planning Services table</emphasis> This table has 2 dimensions, the family planning method (contraceptive) and whether the client is new or continuing. We ended up with one data element only &quot;Family planning clients&quot; and then added two categories &quot;FP method&quot; with all the contraceptives as options, and another category &quot;FP client type&quot; with new or continuing as options. This way it will be easy to get the total number of family planning clients which is the major value to look at in data analysis, and from there you can easily get the details on method or how many new clients there are.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
