<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using Event Capture</title>
  <section>    
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The event capture app allows users to register events that occurred at a particular time
      and place. An event can happen at any given point in time. This stands in contrast to routine
      data, which can be captured for predefined, regular intervals. Events in DHIS 2 are linked to
      a program. Hence, the event capture app lets you select the organisation unit and program and
      specifiy a date when a event (also known as case or record) happened, before entering
      information for the event.</para>
    </section>
  <section>
    <title>Capturing events</title>
    <para>To capture an event, the first step is to select an organisation unit from the left-side
      organisation unit tree. After selecting an org unit, the list of programs will display the
      programs which have been associated with the selected organisation unit and which have been
      given access to the current user through user roles. Events are displayed in a tabular fashion
      as shown in the figure below. As seen in the screenshot, each row corresponds to an event. The
      columns display information about the events, more specifically they display data for data
      elements which are part of the program.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example event list</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/event_capture/event_list.png" format="PNG"
            width="70%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>All event related operations are accessible from the screen shown above. The operations
      currently available are: <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Capturing data:</emphasis> this available by clicking the
            "Register event" button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Showing/hiding colums: </emphasis>this is to allow users
            decide which columns to show/hide in the table of events. This feature is especially
            important when we have a long list of data elements assigned to a program stage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Editing:</emphasis> the rows in the table are clickable,
            clicking them shows three menus - <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">Edit in grid</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Remove.</emphasis> The
            edit function takes you to a new page where information for the selected event can be
            updated. The edit in grid function allows you to edit the selected event within the
            table but only those columns (data elements) visible in the grid. If more columns are
            required it is possible to add using the "Show/Hide columns" button to speficy which
            columns should be displayed in the list.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Sorting:</emphasis> this can be done by clicking the sorting
            icon of each column header. A red sorting icon implies the current sorting column. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Filtering:</emphasis> this is done by clicking the small
            search icon shown to the right of each column header. Clicking them provides an input
            field to type a filtering criteria. The system starts applying the filter the moment a
            user starts to type. During filtering it is possible to define start and end dates for
            date type data elements and lower and upper limits for number types.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Paging:</emphasis> The list of events can be paged by using
            the paging section at the bootom of the list. Paging allows you to quickly move between
            pages of events and to change the page size, i.e. the number of events per page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Printing:</emphasis> The "Print list" button allows to print
            the list of events. This button also changes its label accordingly - for example "Print
            details" and "Print form" - and does the printing functionality.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
    <para>The event capture app works offline, in the sense that if Internet connectivity drops
      during your working session, you can continue to capture events which will be stored locally
      in your web browser (client). When connectivity has returned the system will ask to upload
      locally stored data, and sends it to the server where it is stored. Note that if the Web
      browser is closed while in offline-mode, it is not possiblew to reopen a new browser window
      and continue the working session; however the data will still be saved locally and can be
      uploaded to the server the next time the machine is online and the user has logged into the
      server.</para>
    
    <para>If the selected program's program stage is configured to capture GPS coordinate, the app
      provides two ways of capturing coordinates. The first is two simple text boxes so that a user
      can fillin proper latitude and longitude values.  The second option is using google map, where
      it is possible to point and click for coordinates. The google map option also displays
      polygons and points that are defined for organisation units.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
