<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Name-Based Information Tracking Module</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
      <title>Quick Background</title>
      <para>The DHIS Community Module ( also known as DHIS patient module or NBITS) is an integrated module in DHIS2, built to support community health systems and facilitate a smooth integration between the community health data and aggregated data management ( e.g. HMIS ).</para>
      <para>The module deals with person-level data as opposed to aggregated data which is the main focus of the core DHIS2 modules. The module supports management of community health programs such as: child immunization, maternal health and e.g. allows for tracking of individuals enrolled in various programs and activity planning for community health workers.</para>
      <para>Basically, it is similar to DHIS2, the following are the major things:</para>
      <para>1. Beneficiary</para>
      <para>2. Program</para>
      <para>3. Program Stage</para>
      <para>4. Data Entry</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Context and Concept</title>
      <para>Conventionally, Public Health Systems have been recording and reporting aggregated data of the services provided across various health programmes. Though this is crucial in monitoring &quot;reach&quot; and &quot;availability&quot; of public health services, but it lacks tracing the beneficiaries being provided these services and quality of service. </para>
      <para>For example, the aggregate report will show that 300 pregnant women registered  for ANC and 120 women given IFA tablets or 90 women given TT injection. In an aggregate system, it is not possible to ascertain that if a particular pregnant woman registered for ANC, has also been given IFA and TT, as data only shows aggregate numbers. To understand the quality of services given to each pregnant woman registered for ANC, immunization cycle of each child or treatment of each leprosy beneficiary, etc. it is important that treatment information of each beneficiary is maintained as an individual case.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Objectives of Name Based Information Tracking</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Objectives of Name Based Information Tracking:</emphasis></para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Track (follow-up) a beneficiary through the entire treatment period.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate the service provider ( health worker or doctor ) in ( beneficiary ) patient&apos;s treatment follow-up; by recording all treatment related information in one place ( makes it comprehensive for the service-provider ).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help the beneficiary in recording treatment history in one place, which could be used later in case of referral.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages of Name Based Information Tracking :</emphasis></para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitates in recording entire treatment information of each beneficiary ( patient ).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitates health-workers in organizing out-reach.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitates service-provider in treatment follow-up.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitates in effective monitoring of different health services and drill down to individual beneficiary ( patient ) information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Helps strengthen the quality and fidelity of data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>Though at sub-center level, the data in primary registers is recorded and maintained by individuals (name based), but is sent up-wards as aggregated reports. Now with HMIS reforms implemented and district on-wards data available on-line, the thrust has been on ensuring data quality implemented completeness. To-wards this one important initiative has been starting name based reporting - from sub-center to national level.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Working of Name Based Information Tracking</title>
      <para>NBITS registers cases and tracks these cases over time through different forms that are filled for the treatment of a beneficiary.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Registration and Identification for a beneficiary</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Programme enrolment</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Treatment plan</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Case encounters</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Registration and Identification for a beneficiary</title>
        <para>The system has a function to manage facilities which allow to registry new benificiaries or not. To start creating a patient, we need to select a facility which allows to registry a new benificiary.</para>
        <para>The process of creating a new beneficiary in the system is through the registration process. The beneficiary is first registered in the system ( or checked if beneficiary already exists in system ). Searching a beneficiary can be done through identifiers, name, location or benificary&apos;s attributes (address, phone number, e.g. ). If the beneficiary already exists in the system, the encounter details can be opened and filled and the programme process can continue. If the beneficiary does not exist in the system, then new registration takes place. </para>
        <para>When a beneficiary is registered in the system, multiple identifiers can be associated with the registration, such as Passport number, PAN, driving license, health identifier, UID. Internally, a location unique identifier is used to track the beneficiary.</para>
        <para>The process of identification is location independent, this implies that irrespective of location where beneficiary registered for service the service/medical record can be searched and pulled-up in any other facility provided the same is in the database. For facilities, which are not in the database, for e.g. a private facility, it will just be noted that &quot;<emphasis role="italic">Service is provided at other facility</emphasis>&quot;. In such case, the beneficiary should be encouraged, to provide these details of services taken from other facility to the ANM. The health worker is first identified through any of the identifiers or username in the system and the beneficiary is identified through identifiers for receiving a health service. After identification, the beneficiary&apos;s case history can be viewed or case can be updated with the new care that they have received</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Programme Enrollment and Treatment Plan</title>
        <para>When a beneficiary is enrolled into any health programme, a record of treatment is created for the beneficiary. Various services provided to the beneficiary through the treatment are recorded for the beneficiary. This recording  results in creation of a treatment plan for the beneficiary.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Case Encounters</title>
        <para>Each interaction with the beneficiary related to the case is considered to be an encounter and these encounters are recorded into the beneficiary case. Beneficiary case is updated with the identification of both the health worker and the beneficiary who is receiving the service.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>NBITS Application User Guide</title>
    <section>
      <title>Starting the application</title>
      <para>To use the online NBITS application, in client computer which is connected to Internet, launch web browser ( use of <emphasis role="italic">Mozilla Firefox</emphasis> browser is recommended ).</para>
      <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Firefox-icon.png" align="center"/></para>
      <para>Once you have started NBITS online, the displayed screen will prompt you to enter your registered &quot;<emphasis role="italic">Username</emphasis>&quot; and &quot;<emphasis role="italic">Password</emphasis>&quot;. After entering the required information, click <emphasis role="italic">Login</emphasis> button to log into the application.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure 2.1.1</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.1.1.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>After clicking  the login button, you will be directed to the <emphasis role="italic">Welcome</emphasis> screen of the NBITS:</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Figure 2.1.2</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.1.2.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Modules in NBITS</title>
      <para>The NBITS application is an online application and developed as open source application. The application is platform independent and can be easily linked with other open source application. The application is developed on the similar DHIS framework and it has three basic modules as DHIS 2 namely - </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maintenance  module</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Services module</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help module</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The functionalities of these modules are same as DHIS 2. There will be some additions in the NBITS in both maintenance and services module. <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> module will have one additional sub module for the beneficiary registration and <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> module will have one additional sub-module for Name based data entry and Recording.</para>
      <para>The module provide three main functionalities -</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Processes of case tracking in NBITS</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reports</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Beneficary Aggregation</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Processes of case tracking in NBITS</title>
      <para>The NBITS application is developed with the objective of tracking cases of any disease or condition by using this application. The process of tracking starts with the registration of cases in the application. Application can provide information for only those cases which are available in the database, so the first process is the registration of beneficiary in the NBITS application. Once the beneficiary is registered, she/he can be enrolled in the program for which registered. The application will guide the health provider for the services required by the beneficiary through activity plan and the services received by the beneficiary from time to time can be updated into his/her profile.  The working process of the application can be understood in steps depicted in picture below - </para>
      <para><screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.1</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.1.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>
      <section>
        <title>STEP 1: Beneficiary registration</title>
        <para>The First step in the tracking is the registration of beneficiary/case in the NBITS application. In the registration process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contact and location details &amp; health provider details, are entered in the application. In the registration itself, beneficiary is provided with the unique identification number. This number will be unique and will not match with the identification number of any person in the state jurisdiction. The issue of identification number will be the responsibility of facility where the beneficiary is registered first time.</para>
        <warning>
          <para>Any case irrespective of the program will be registered first and then will be enrolled in any of the program. E.g. every pregnant women and the child need to be registered first as a beneficiary, than the beneficiaries will be enrolled in Mother Care program or Child Health program.</para>
        </warning>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">
              <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">
            <emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="underline"> of Beneficiary registration Process in application</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis> - </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To register a beneficiary in the application, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, select option <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary and Programs</emphasis>.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.2</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.2.png" format="CGM-CLEAR"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.3</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.3.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Now click on the <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries</emphasis> option to go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary Registration</emphasis> window.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.4</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.4.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select <emphasis role="italic">Organisation unit</emphasis> and  click on the<emphasis role="italic"> Add New</emphasis> button to start the registration process.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.5</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.5.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start process of registration by providing name, location details, identification details, contact details and health provider details.  To complete to process of registration, click on <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button (arrow in RED color, fig. 2.3.6,  given at the end of patient registration ).</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.6</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.6.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <para>To check the duplicates or to avoid double registration, after providing name &amp; demographic details, click on the <emphasis role="italic">Check duplicate</emphasis> button ( arrow in BLUE color, fig. 2.3.6 ). Application will check from the existing records that whether same patient exists in the database or not. If the patient exists on the database, application will show that same patient exists in the database. Now user needs to cancel the registration process and update the records in existing patient database. If the patient doesn’t exist in the database, user can continue the process of registration.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>STEP 2 - Patient Enrolment</title>
        <para>After the patient registration, patient needs to be enrolled in any of the program available in the application and for which she/he has been registered. To enroll -</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="italic">Manage Program Enrollment </emphasis> icon</para>
            <para><graphic fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/enroll-icon.png" align="center"/></para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.7</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.7.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a program from the list  ( i.e., Mother Care Program, Child Health Program... )</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.8</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.8.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <warning>
              <para>This task can be executed after register successfully, a  form like Fig. 2.3.8. is  showed up for enrolment.
</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>After the selection of program, you need to provide two dates -</para>
            <para>1) Date of Enrolment</para>
            <para>2) Date of Incidence</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.9</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.9.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Date of enrollment</emphasis> is the date of registration of patient with facility.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Date of incidence</emphasis> is the date of last menstrual period (LMP) in case of pregnant women and date of birth in case of child.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <warning>
              <para>The date of incidence and enrollment is very important to generate the activity plans for the facilities. Facility needs to ensure that they record and report date of incidence with each case.</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="italic">Enroll</emphasis> button to complete the enrollment process.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.10</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.10.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <para>The application will automatically calculate  due-date for each the program stage  and will show same below enrollment. To reschedule any of visits,  clicking on the <emphasis role="italic">calendar</emphasis> icon, selecting a date and later clicking on <emphasis role="italic">Update </emphasis>button. These dates will be used to generate the activity plan form.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.11</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.11.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>STEP 3 – Updating the record at different stages of Program</title>
        <para>As we know, in the health programs, an beneficiary registered and enrolled into the system, needs to be checked from time to time by service providers.
The case updation in the NBITS application is designed in the same manner so that services which received by the beneficiaries can be updated from time to time  when they visit the facility  or  whenever they are visits by the health provider.</para>
        <section>
          <title>Single DataEntry for beneficiary</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>From the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> option, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.12</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.12.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 3.3.14</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.13.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Selection of organisation unit and individual case</para>
              <para>First select the organisation unit. Then search the beneficiary/patient in the existing database. 
There are two way to search a patient -<itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Search patient by different identifiers such as Identification number, address, name of village etc.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Or search patient by clicking on <emphasis role="italic">Listing All Benificiaries</emphasis> button, and then search manually.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.14</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.14.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Updating the records</para>
              <para>Once the patient is identified in the existing database, click on the  <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> icon to start the process.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.15`</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.15.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Selection of the Program and Program Stage</para>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">What is program stage ?</emphasis> - This is to handle specific stages of a health program  because of  having multiple encounters for a given health program. E.g.   once a pregnant  woman is in &quot;<emphasis role="italic">ANC Program</emphasis>&quot;,  she will be treated for her first trimester, second trimester and/or third trimester. These encounters in most cases are mandatory, and  there will be dropouts in some cases, which a pregnant woman should go through once she is in the &quot;<emphasis role="italic">ANC Program</emphasis>&quot;. So the specific stages of the health program is defined when creating a health program.</para>
              <para>Select the program and the program stage for the data entry first, then provide the <emphasis role="italic">Report Date</emphasis>  to go to the case updation form and open  the data entry form.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.16</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.16.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <para>After filling data into the data entry form, click on the <emphasis role="italic">Complete data entry</emphasis> button to complete the  data filling process for this stage. Similarly, select the other stages for which to update the record of the case.</para>
              <para>During each stage, the section related to that particular stage will be enabled for data entry form, rest of the sections will remain disabled in that particular stage. E.g. if data entry form of ANC registration stage is selected, then only data elements of ANC registration stage  will be enabled and the rest of the data elements of other stages will remain disabled.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Multiple Data Entry for beneficiaries</title>
          <para>This is an advanced function for data entry. On the same interface on above, many beneficiaries are listed for data entered by stages. </para>
          <para>From the <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Name Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Multiple Data Entry</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.1</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.1.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 1: List all beneficiaries of the programs</emphasis> by choosing:</para>
              <para>1)  Select  an organisation unit on the left menu</para>
              <para>2) Select a program from list of programs.</para>
              <para>2)  Select an option from <emphasis role="italic">Sort by</emphasis>  combobox to sort by beneficiary&apos;s attributes [option].</para>
              <para><screenshot>
                  <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.2</screeninfo>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.2.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 2: Choose a stage of a beneficiary</emphasis> for data entered. </para>
              <para>See the below figure illustrates for beneficiary named <emphasis role="italic">Nguyễn Văn Nam</emphasis> ( first row ) and the second column for stage named <emphasis role="italic">At 6 weeks after birth</emphasis>.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.3</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.3.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 3: Enter data</emphasis> ( arrow <emphasis role="italic">labelled 1</emphasis> in Fig. 2.5.3.3  ). After finishing the entering, close the pop-up ( arrow <emphasis role="italic">labelled 2</emphasis> in Fig. 2.5.3.3 )</para>
              <para>The benefits of this advanced function is to optimize the time-transition consuming when entering data for a long list beneficiaries by not switching the main window/interface.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Report Generation</title>
      <para>This module provides two main functions, include NBITS Activity Plan report and NBITS Summary report.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NBITS Activity Plan report: This report is a feedback report to the facilities to help them in planning activities. This is also called as activity plan or visit plan. Basically, view the visit plan to get an overview of outstanding, pending, and completed visits. </para>
          <para>See the illustration for Immunization program for Children under 1yr old.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.17</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.17.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>Each card ( see above Fig. 2.3.17 ) present a coming stage information for a beneficiary of a program.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NBITS Summary report: View the summary report to get an overview of the services provided for a program</para>
          <para>See an example -</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.3.18: Each row is a summary of stages of the Immunization program for Children under 1yr old</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.3.18.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>The color highlight the status of the stages:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>PURPLE: Data entered and uncomplete stages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>RED: Stages open but no data entered while the date estimated for closing/completing is over.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>YELLOW: Coming stages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>GREEN: Compete stages.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Beneficiary Aggregation</title>
      <para>This is the core functionality for linking data between name-based information tracking system – NBITS ( beneficiaries, programs, etc ) and aggregate management system ( dataset, report, charts, etc.) by defining the linking/aggregating rules.</para>
      <para>This provides two functions - </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries Aggregation QueryBuilder</emphasis> is a tool for define formula, expression, rules for aggregation data from name-based to aggregation system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Beneficiary Aggregation to used for generating routine data values from patient-data by month (or other interval if desired) and organization unit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Beneficiary Aggregation QueryBuilder</title>
        <para>From the <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to the <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Programs</emphasis> option. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries Aggregation QueryBuilder</emphasis> option on left menu to proceed</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.2</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.2.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>After click on <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button, the following will appear:</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.3</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.3.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 1:</emphasis>
          </emphasis> Provide the basic information for a query: description, aggregation data element from data element group.</para>
        <para>See the example (Fig. 2.5.4.3): description as <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis>,  and the result with be stored with data element as <emphasis role="italic">Number of Children - BCG</emphasis>  in data element group <emphasis role="italic">BCG Program</emphasis>.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">
              <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 2:</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis> </para>
        <para>Select the equivalent data element for the beneficiaries to link to the data element selected above. The information include: program, program stage and data element by the selected program stage.</para>
        <para>Double click on the data element the equivalent code of it will be showed in the condition box (labelled 4). An example of Fig. 2.5.4.3, if double click on the data element named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given date ((default))</emphasis> the code appear as <emphasis role="italic">[DE:8.75.1]</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>To make the condition valid, as default click on button “<emphasis role="italic">!=NULL</emphasis>”. Then there will be the text “<emphasis role="italic">[DE:8.75.1] is not null</emphasis>” in the Condition box.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 3:</emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <para>For adding and advanced condition for the query. So, it is required more knowledge about the health services of the programs specifically.</para>
        <para>All properties and options listed in this area are flexible and depend on the health program. And users can modify them.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="underline">
              <emphasis role="underline">Area labelled 4:</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
          </emphasis></para>
        <para>Includes the buttons of operands and a text box showing the conditions for the query.</para>
        <para>After finishing the area above (1, 2, 3 and 4), click on the <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Beneficiary Aggregation</title>
        <para>Here are the main screen shots:</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.4</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.4.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.5</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.5.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Area in the ORANGE frame: the hierarchy tree of organization units. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Area in the BLUE frame: for choosing the data set, the start and end date of the aggregated period.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Click on the 
<emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> button to execute aggregate function.
</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.6 - Shows the result from the example</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.6.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>A Sample for Beneficary Aggregation</title>
        <para>E.g.  Find the number of the children vaccinated BCG by defining a linking rule between the data elements of aggregate dataset named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis>  and the data element of a program stage named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose given date</emphasis>.<orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Data Element and Indicators</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Element</emphasis> option to define two new data elements -</para>
              <para><itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Aggregate</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Define a new data element named <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> with  <emphasis role="italic">Patient</emphasis> option for Domain Type.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.2.1</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.2.1.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.2.2 - Define a data element with <emphasis role="italic">Patient</emphasis> option for <emphasis role="italic">Domain Type</emphasis>.</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.2.2.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.2.3 - <emphasis role="italic">Add Data Element </emphasis>form</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.2.3.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to<emphasis role="italic"> Data Element and Indicators</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Element Group</emphasis> option to create a new data element group named <emphasis role="italic">BCG DataElement Group</emphasis> and add <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> data element into the group.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Datasets</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Dataset</emphasis> option to create a new dataset named <emphasis role="italic">BCG Report</emphasis> and add <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG</emphasis> data element into the dataset.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Benificaries and Programs</emphasis> option   and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis> option to create a program named <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis> with a stage named <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> and add the <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element into this stage.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Maintenance</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiaries and Program </emphasis>option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Beneficiary</emphasis> option to create three benificiaries named <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis> and enrol them into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Create a new Beneficiary Aggregation QueryBuilder named <emphasis role="italic">Number of children - BCG Builder </emphasis>to linking between the data elements.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.4</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.4.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Name-Based Data Records</emphasis> option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Data Entry</emphasis> option.</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Choose benificiary  <emphasis role="italic">Micheal</emphasis> and open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into <emphasis role="italic">Child Health Program</emphasis>. Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2011-02-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Choose benificiary  <emphasis role="italic">Alice</emphasis> and open the <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage into Child Health Program. Enter Enter value for <emphasis role="italic">BCG dose give date</emphasis> data element as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2011-02-18</emphasis>&quot;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Choose benificiary   <emphasis role="italic">Tom</emphasis> and no enter data value for <emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis> stage.</para>
                  <warning>
                    <para>Before entering data value for the stage, choose <emphasis role="italic">Report Date</emphasis> as &quot;<emphasis role="italic">2011-02-28</emphasis>&quot;</para>
                  </warning>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From <emphasis role="italic">Services</emphasis> menu, go to Name-Based Data Records option and click on it. Select <emphasis role="italic">Case Aggregation</emphasis> option to run<emphasis role="italic"> Number of children - BCG Builder</emphasis> to get data value  and save it into database.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.3.5</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.3.5.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.4.6 - Resultafter running the query builder</screeninfo>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.4.6.png" format="PNG" width="70%"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Important Notes</title>
      <para>Here are some notes for using DHIS2 – NBITS efficiently.</para>
      <section>
        <title>For section: “Beneficiaries and Programs” &gt;&gt; “Programs” &gt;&gt; “Add new a program stage”</title>
        <para>After finishing to add new program stages for a program, it is necessary to “Sort” the program stages within the program.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>For section: “Name-based data Records” &gt;&gt; “Data-entry”</title>
        <para>At a stage of a program when the data for a beneficiary is entered in order to confirm the completeness of the data provided, click on the “Complete” button at the bottom of the entry form.</para>
        <para>The purpose of this task is to close the stage to switch to the next. So, once data entered for a stage complete and closed (or complete confirmation) then it is impossible to re-open or go back to the previous stages for updating data or changing.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Advanced functions</title>
      <para>The content in this part is for the expert users or administrative users who are capable and responsible for development and change</para>
      <section>
        <title>Create a new program</title>
        <section>
          <title>STEP 1 : Create a new program</title>
          <para><screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.1</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.1.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
          <para>Basic information :</para>
          <para><itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: The name of the program</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: Descriptions, meanings, explanation, etc. of/about the program</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Date of Enrolment Description</emphasis>: The date in which a beneficiary is registered to the system.
For example: the date in which a beneficiary enrols to the system.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Date of Incidence Description</emphasis>: the date in which a beneficiary practically enrol to the health program. E.g. In the Immunization program for child under 1yr old, the incident date is the birthday; In the maternal program, the incident date is the date of last menstrual period (LMP)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of min days allowed to input data</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Number of max days allowed to input data</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>STEP 2: Define (Create) stages for a health program</title>
          <para>By clicking on the <emphasis role="italic">Program Stage Management</emphasis>  icon ( Fig. 2.5.1.2a ) and then <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button  (Fig. 2.5.1.2b ).</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2a</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2a.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2b</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2b.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2c</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2c.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>Fig. 2.5.1.2c illustrates for stage named “<emphasis role="italic">Birth Details</emphasis>” of  “<emphasis role="italic">Child Health</emphasis>” program.
More explanation for the figure:</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">
              <emphasis role="italic">
                <emphasis role="italic">
                  <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue frame labelled 1:</emphasis>
                </emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis></para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>: Name of the stage</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>: The description of the stage</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Min no of days to wait from start of Program</emphasis>:  The minimum number of days to wait for starting the program</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Program</emphasis>: The name of the program which is already defined before.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">
              <emphasis role="bold">
                <emphasis role="italic">
                  <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue arrow and labelled 2:</emphasis>
                </emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis></para>
          <para>Choose the data elements from the list on the left to the right one. These chosen elements are highlighted with BLUE color.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">
              <emphasis role="bold">
                <emphasis role="italic">
                  <emphasis role="underline">Area with blue arrow and labelled 3:</emphasis>
                </emphasis>
              </emphasis>
            </emphasis></para>
          <para>Function area with button labeled “<emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis>”, see the arrow labelled 3 and in BLUE to execute the function.</para>
          <para>If successfully, the new stages will showed in the list of stages:</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Figure 2.5.1.2d</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="70%" fileref="resources/images/patients_programs/Fig. 2.5.1.2d.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>Attention: It is required to firstly choose a program from the list of Programs and then add a new stages by clicking on the &quot;<emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis>&quot; button.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
