<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="dhis2_r">
  <title>DHIS2 and R integration</title>
  <section id="dhis2_r_intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>R is freely available, open source statistical computing environment. R refers to  both the computer programming language, as well as the software which can be used to create and run R scripts. There are <ulink url="http://cran.r-project.org/">numerous sources on the web</ulink> which describe the extensive set of features of R. </para>
    <para>R is a natural extension to DHIS2, as it provides  powerful statistical routines, data manipulation functions, and visualization tools. This chapter will describe how to setup R and DHIS2 on the same server, and will provide a simple example of how to retrieve data from the DHIS2 database into an R data frame and perform some basic calculations.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="dhis2_r_odbc">
    <title>Using ODBC to retrieve data from DHIS2 into R</title>
    <para>In this example, we will use a system-wide ODBC connector which will be used to retrieve data from the DHIS2 database. There are some disadvantages with this approach, as ODBC is slower than other methods and it does raise some security concerns by providing a system-wide connector to all users. However, it is a convenient method to provide a connection to multiple users. The use of the R package RODBC will be used in this case. Other alternatives would be the use of the <ulink url="http://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/code/rpostgresql.html">RPostgreSQL</ulink> package, which can interface directly through the  Postgresql driver.</para>
    <para>First, we will install R and some other required and useful packages. Invoke the following command:</para>
    <para><command>apt-get install r-base r-cran-odbc r-cran-lattice odbc-postgresql</command> </para>
    <para>Next, we need to configure the ODBC connection. Edit the file to suit your local situation using the following template as a guide. Lets create and edit a file called odbc.ini</para>
    <para><screen>[dhis2]
Description         = DHIS2 Database
Driver              = /usr/lib/odbc/psqlodbcw.so
Trace               = No
TraceFile           = /tmp/sql.log
Database            = dhis2
Servername          = 127.0.0.1
UserName            = postgres
Password            = SomethingSecure
Port                = 5432
Protocol            = 9.0
ReadOnly            = Yes
RowVersioning       = No
ShowSystemTables    = No
ShowOidColumn       = No
FakeOidIndex        = No
ConnSettings        =
Debug = 0</screen>
</para>
    <para>Finally, we need to install the ODBC connection with <command>odbcinst -i -d -f odbc.ini</command></para>
    <para>Next, lets execute R and see if the ODBC connection is working. Invoke <command>R</command> from the command line. </para>
    <para><screen>foo@bar:~$ R

R version 2.14.1 (2011-12-22)
Copyright (C) 2011 The R Foundation for Statistical Computing
ISBN 3-900051-07-0
Platform: i686-pc-linux-gnu (32-bit)

R is free software and comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY.
You are welcome to redistribute it under certain conditions.
Type &apos;license()&apos; or &apos;licence()&apos; for distribution details.

R is a collaborative project with many contributors.
Type &apos;contributors()&apos; for more information and
&apos;citation()&apos; on how to cite R or R packages in publications.

Type &apos;demo()&apos; for some demos, &apos;help()&apos; for on-line help, or
&apos;help.start()&apos; for an HTML browser interface to help.
Type &apos;q()&apos; to quit R.

[Previously saved workspace restored]

&gt;
</screen></para>
    <para>This shows that R is working properly. </para>
    <para>From the R prompt, execute the following commands to connect to the DHIS2 database. </para>
    <para><screen>&gt; library(RODBC)
&gt; channel&lt;-odbcConnect(&quot;dhis2&quot;)#Note that the name must match the ODBC connector name
&gt; sqlTest&lt;-c(&quot;SELECT dataeleemntid, name FROM dataelement LIMIT 10;&quot;)
&gt; sqlQuery(channel,sqlTest)
                                                                        name
1   OPD First Attendances Under 5
2   OPD First Attendances Over 5
3   Deaths Anaemia Under 5 Years
4   Deaths Clinical Case of Malaria Under 5 Years
5   Inpatient discharges under 5
6   Inpatient Under 5 Admissions
7   Number ITNs
8   OPD 1st Attendance Clinical Case of Malaria Under 5
9  IP Discharge Clinical Case of Malaria Under 5 Years
10 Deaths of malaria case provided with anti-malarial treatment 1 to 5 Years
&gt;
</screen></para>
    <para>It seems R is able to retreive data from the DHIS2 database. As an illustrative example, lets say we have been asked to calculate the relative percentage of OPD male and female under 5 attendances for the last twelve months.First, lets create an SQL query which will provide us the basic information which will be required.</para>
    <para><screen>OPD&lt;-sqlQuery(channel,&quot;SELECT p.startdate, de.name as de, sum(dv.value::double precision)
 FROM datavalue dv
 INNER JOIN period p on dv.periodid = p.periodid
 INNER JOIN dataelement de on dv.dataelementid = de.dataelementid
 WHERE p.startdate &gt;= &apos;2011-01-01&apos;
 and p.enddate &lt;= &apos;2011-12-31&apos;
 and de.name ~*(&apos;Attendance OPD&apos;)
 GROUP BY p.startdate, de.name;&quot;)</screen></para>
    <para>We have stored the result of the SQL query in an R data frame called OPD. Lets take a look at what the data looks like. </para>
    <para><screen>&gt; head(OPD)
   startdate                                 de    sum
1 2011-12-01   Attendance OPD &lt;12 months female  42557
2 2011-02-01   Attendance OPD &lt;12 months female 127485
3 2011-01-01   Attendance OPD 12-59 months male 200734
4 2011-04-01   Attendance OPD 12-59 months male 222649
5 2011-06-01   Attendance OPD 12-59 months male 168896
6 2011-03-01 Attendance OPD 12-59 months female 268141
&gt; unique(OPD$de)
[1] Attendance OPD &lt;12 months female   Attendance OPD 12-59 months male  
[3] Attendance OPD 12-59 months female Attendance OPD &gt;5 years male      
[5] Attendance OPD &lt;12 months male     Attendance OPD &gt;5 years female    
6 Levels: Attendance OPD 12-59 months female ... Attendance OPD &gt;5 years male
&gt; 
          </screen>
</para>
    <para>We can see that we need to aggregate the two age groups (&lt; 12 months and 12-59 months) into a single variable, based on the gender. Lets reshape the data into a crosstabulated table  to make this easier to visualize and calculate the summaries.</para>
    <para><screen>&gt;OPD.ct&lt;-cast(OPD,startdate ~ de) 
&gt;colnames(OPD.ct)
[1] &quot;startdate&quot;                          &quot;Attendance OPD 12-59 months female&quot;
[3] &quot;Attendance OPD 12-59 months male&quot;   &quot;Attendance OPD &lt;12 months female&quot;  
[5] &quot;Attendance OPD &lt;12 months male&quot;     &quot;Attendance OPD &gt;5 years female&quot;    
[7] &quot;Attendance OPD &gt;5 years male&quot; </screen>     
</para>
    <para>We have reshaped the data so that the data elements are individual columns. It looks like we need to aggregate the second and fourth columns together to get the under 5 female attendance, and then the third and fifth columns to get the male under 5 attendance.After this, lets subset the data into a new data frame just to get the required information and display the results.</para>
    <para><screen>&gt; OPD.ct$OPDUnder5Female&lt;-OPD.ct[,2]+OPD.ct[,4]#Females
&gt; OPD.ct$OPDUnder5Male&lt;-OPD.ct[,3]+OPD.ct[,5]#males
&gt; OPD.ct.summary&lt;-OPD.ct[,c(1,8,9)]#new summary data frame
&gt;OPD.ct.summary$FemalePercent&lt;-
OPD.ct.summary$OPDUnder5Female/
(OPD.ct.summary$OPDUnder5Female + OPD.ct.summary$OPDUnder5Male)*100#Females
&gt;OPD.ct.summary$MalePercent&lt;-
OPD.ct.summary$OPDUnder5Male/
(OPD.ct.summary$OPDUnder5Female + OPD.ct.summary$OPDUnder5Male)*100#Males </screen></para>
    <para>Of course, this could be accomplished much more elegantly, but for the purpose of the illustration, this code is rather verbose.Finally, lets display the required information.</para>
    <para><screen>&gt; OPD.ct.summary[,c(1,4,5)]
    startdate FemalePercent MalePercent
1  2011-01-01      51.13360    48.86640
2  2011-02-01      51.49154    48.50846
3  2011-03-01      51.55651    48.44349
4  2011-04-01      51.19867    48.80133
5  2011-05-01      51.29902    48.70098
6  2011-06-01      51.66519    48.33481
7  2011-07-01      51.68762    48.31238
8  2011-08-01      51.49467    48.50533
9  2011-09-01      51.20394    48.79606
10 2011-10-01      51.34465    48.65535
11 2011-11-01      51.42526    48.57474
12 2011-12-01      50.68933    49.31067</screen></para>
    <para>We can see that the male and female attendances are very similar for each month of the year, with seemingly higher male attendance relative to female attendance in the month of December.</para>
    <para>In this example, we showed how to retreive data from the DHIS2 database and manipulate in with some simple R commands. The basic pattern for using DHIS2 and R together, will be the retrieval of data from the DHIS2 database with an SQL query into an R data frame, followed by whatever routines (statistical analysis, plotting, etc) which may be required.  </para>
  </section>
  <section id="dhis2_r_mydatamart">
    <title>Using R with MyDatamart</title>
    <para>MyDatamart provides  useful interface to the DHIS2 database by making a local copy of the database available on a users desktop. This means that the user does not need direct access to the database and the data can be worked with offline on the users local machine. In this example, we will have used the <ulink url="http://apps.dhis2.org/demo">demo database</ulink>. Data was downloaded at the district level for Jan 2011-Dec 201l. Consult the MyDatamart section in this manual for more detailed information. </para>
    <para/>
    <para>First, lets load some required packages. If you do not have these packages already installed in your version of R, you will need to do so before proceeding with the example.</para>
    <screen>library(&quot;DBI&quot;)
library(&quot;RSQLite&quot;)
library(&quot;lattice&quot;)
library(&quot;latticeExtra&quot;)</screen>
    <para>Next, we are going to connect to the local copy of the MyDatamart database. In this case, it was located at C:\dhis2\sl.dmart. </para>
    <screen>dbPath&lt;-&quot;C:\\dhis2\\sl.dmart&quot;
drv&lt;-dbDriver(&quot;SQLite&quot;)
db&lt;-dbConnect(drv,dbPath)</screen>
    <para>Let suppose we have been asked to compare ANC 1, 2, 3 coverage rates for each district for 2011. We can define an SQL query to retrieve data from the MyDatamart database into an R data frame as follows.</para>
    <screen>#An SQL query which will retreive all indicators 
#at OU2 le
sql&lt;-&quot;SELECT * FROM pivotsource_indicator_ou2_m 
WHERE year = &apos;2011&apos;&quot;
#Execute the query into a new result set
rs&lt;-dbSendQuery(db,sql)
#Put the entire result set into a new data frame
Inds&lt;-fetch(rs,n=-1)
#Clean up a bit
dbClearResult(rs)
dbDisconnect(db)</screen>
    <para>We used one of the pre-existing Pivot Source queries in the database to get all of the indicator values. Of course, we could have retrieved only the ANC indicators, but we did not exactly know how the data was structured, or how the columns were named, so lets take a closer look. </para>
    <screen>#Get the name of the columns
colnames(Inds)
#output not shown for brevity
levels(as.factor(Inds$indshort)) </screen>
    <para>We see from the <command>colnames</command> commnand that there is an column called &quot;indshort&quot; which looks like it contains some indicator names. We can see the names using the second command. After we have determined which ones we need (ANC 1, 2, and 3), lets further subset the data so that we only have these. </para>
    <screen>#Subset the data for ANC
ANC&lt;-Inds[grep(&quot;ANC (1|2|3) Coverage&quot;,as.factor(Inds$indshort)),]</screen>
    <para>We just used R&apos;s grep function to retrieve all the rows and columns of the Inds data frame which matched the regular expression &quot;ANC (1|2|3) Coverage&quot; and put this into a new data frame called &quot;ANC&quot;. </para>
    <para>By looking at the data with the <command>str(ANC)</command> command, we will notice that the time periods are not ordered correctly, so lets fix this before we try and create a plot of the data.  </para>
    <screen>#Lets reorder the months
MonthOrder&lt;-c(&apos;Jan&apos;,&apos;Feb&apos;,&apos;Mar&apos;,&apos;Apr&apos;,
&apos;May&apos;,&apos;Jun&apos;,&apos;Jul&apos;,&apos;Aug&apos;,&apos;Sep&apos;,&apos;Oct&apos;,&apos;Nov&apos;,&apos;Dec&apos;)
ANC$month&lt;-factor(ANC$month,levels=MonthOrder)</screen>
    <para>Next, we need to actually calculate the indicator value from the numerator, factor and denominator. </para>
    <screen>#Calculate the indicator value
ANC$value&lt;-ANC$numxfactor/ANC$denominatorvalue</screen>
    <para>Finally, lets create a simple trellis plot which compares ANC 1, 2, 3 for each district by month and save it to our local working directory in a file called &quot;District_ANC.png&quot;. </para>
    <screen>png(filename=&quot;District_ANC.png&quot;,width=1024,height=768)
plot.new()
 xyplot(value ~ month | ou2, data=ANC, type=&quot;a&quot;, main=&quot;District ANC Comparison Sierra Leone 2011&quot;,
 groups=indshort,xlab=&quot;Month&quot;,ylab=&quot;ANC Coverage&quot;,
 scales = list(x = list(rot=90)),
 key = simpleKey(levels(factor(ANC$indshort)),
 points=FALSE,lines=TRUE,corner=c(1,1)))
 mtext(date(), side=1, line=3, outer=F, adj=0, cex=0.7)
dev.off()</screen>
    <para>The results of which are displayed below.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/r/District_ANC.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
  <section id="dhis2_r_maps">
    <title>Mapping with R and Postgresql</title>
    <para>A somewhat more extended example, will use the RPostgreSQL library and several other libaries to produce a map from the coordinates stored in the database. We will define a few helper functions to provide a layer of abstraction, which will make the R code more reusable. </para>
    <programlisting>#load some dependent libraries
 library(maps)
 library(maptools)
 library(ColorBrewer)
 library(ClassInt)
 library(RPostgreSQL)

#Define some helper functions
 
#Returns a dataframe from the connection for a valid statement
dfFromSQL&lt;-function (con,sql){
    rs&lt;-dbSendQuery(con,sql)
    result&lt;-fetch(rs,n=-1)
    return(result)
}
#Returns a list of latitudes and
 longitudes from the orgunit table
dhisGetFacilityCoordinates&lt;- function(con,levelLimit=4) {
sqlCoords&lt;-paste(&quot;SELECT ou.organisationunitid, ou.name,
substring(ou.coordinates from E&apos;(?=,?)-[0-9]+\\.[0-9]+&apos;)::double precision as latitude,
substring(ou.coordinates from E&apos;[0-9\\.]+&apos;)::double precision as
 longitude FROM organisationunit ou where ou.organisationunitid
 in (SELECT DISTINCT idlevel&quot;,levelLimit, &quot; from _orgunitstructure)
 and ou.featuretype = &apos;Point&apos;
 ;&quot;,sep=&quot;&quot;)
 result&lt;-dfFromSQL(con,sqlCoords)
 return(result)
 }

#Gets a dataframe of IndicatorValues,
# provided the name of the indicator,
# startdate, periodtype and level
dhisGetAggregatedIndicatorValues&lt;-function(con,
indicatorName,
startdate,
periodtype=&quot;Yearly&quot;,
level=4)
{
  sql&lt;-paste(&quot;SELECT organisationunitid,dv.value FROM aggregatedindicatorvalue dv
where dv.indicatorid  =
(SELECT indicatorid from indicator where name = \&apos;&quot;,indicatorName,&quot;\&apos;) and dv.level
 =&quot;, level,&quot;and
 dv.periodid  = 
(SELECT periodid from period where 
startdate = \&apos;&quot;,startdate,&quot;\&apos;
and periodtypeid = 
(SELECT periodtypeid from periodtype
 where name = \&apos;&quot;,periodtype,&quot;\&apos;));&quot;,sep=&quot;&quot;)
   result&lt;-dfFromSQL(con,sql)
 return(result)
 }

#Main function which handles the plotting.
#con is the database connection
#IndicatorName is the name of the Indicator
#StartDate is the startdate
#baselayer is the baselayer
plotIndicator&lt;-function(con,
IndicatorName,
StartDate,
periodtype=&quot;Yearly&quot;,
level=4,baselayer) 
{
myDF&lt;-dhisGetAggregatedIndicatorValues(con,
IndicatorName,StartDate,periodtype,level)
coords&lt;-dhisGetFacilityCoordinates(con,level)
myDF&lt;-merge(myDF,coords)
myDF&lt;-SpatialPointsDataFrame(myDF[,
c(&quot;longitude&quot;,&quot;latitude&quot;)],myDF)
IndColors&lt;-c(&quot;firebrick4&quot;,&quot;firebrick1&quot;,&quot;gold&quot;
,&quot;darkolivegreen1&quot;,&quot;darkgreen&quot;)
class&lt;-classIntervals(myDF$value,n=6,style=&quot;quantile&quot;
,pal=IndColors)
colCode&lt;-findColours(class,IndColors)
myPlot&lt;-plot.new()
plot(baselayer)
points(myDF,col=colCode,pch=19)
title(main=IndicatorName,sub=StartDate)
return(myPlot) }


</programlisting>
    <para>Up until this point, we have defined a few functions to help us make a map. We need to get the coordinates stored in the database and merge these with the indicator which we plan to map. We then retrieve the data from the aggregated indicator table, create a special type of data frame (SpatialPointsDataFrame), apply some styling to this, and then create the plot. </para>
    <programlisting>
#Now we define the actual thing to do
con &lt;- dbConnect(PostgreSQL(), user= &quot;dhis&quot;, password=&quot;SomethingSecure&quot;, dbname=&quot;dhis&quot;)
#Define the name of the indicator to plot
MyIndicatorName&lt;-&quot;Total OPD Attendance&quot;
MyPeriodType&lt;-&quot;Yearly&quot;
#This should match the level where coordinates are stored
MyLevel&lt;-4
#Given the startdate and period type, it is enough
#to determine the period
MyStartDate&lt;-&quot;2010-01-01&quot;
#Get some Some Zambia district data from GADM
con &lt;- url(&quot;http://www.filefactory.com/file/c2a3898/n/ZMB_adm2_RData&quot;)
print(load(con))#saved as gadm object
#Make the map
plotIndicator(con,MyIndicatorName,MyStartDate,MyPeriodType,MyLevel,gadm)</programlisting>
    <para>The results of the plotIndicator function are shown below.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/r/OPDAttendance.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>In this example, we showed how to use the RPostgreSQL library and other helper libraries(Maptools, ColorBrewer) to create a simple map from the DHIS2 data mart. </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
