<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>DHIS Mobile</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Collection of data in the field can be technically
      challenging and expensive. Mobile phone
      solutions has the potential to
      significantly reduce the complexity of deploying a distributed
      data collection system. Using a simple Java client installed on
      a mobile phone, field workers
      can report directly to DHIS2 instance. </para>
    <para>There are currently two
      mobile solutions for DHIS2, an older SMS based solution and a new
      solution relying on the phone having a data connection to the web (e.g. GPRS).</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>GPRS based solution</title>
    <para>This solution is currently being developed, documentation
      coming soon...
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SMS based solution</title>
    <para>With the SMS solution, the forms filled in on the phone is
      sent using SMS messages to a
      central server. The SMS message is
      decrypted and converted, and then imported into the DHIS2
      database.</para>
    <para>
      By default, DHIS2 does not ship with the DHIS SMS Mobile web
      module. <!-- The DHIS2 downloads site ( <ulink url="http://dhis2.org/downloads">http://dhis2.org/downloads</ulink> 
        ) has a prebuilt version of the latest release with this module added. Otherwise y -->
      You will need to build in these modules
      yourself. You also need to modify the client side
      application with your own data elements.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Build DHIS2 with the dhis-web-mobile module</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Download the latest source code from
            launchpad, i.e. the DHIS2 trunk source
            code from
            <ulink url="https://code.launchpad.net/~dhis2-devs-core/dhis2/trunk">
              https://code.launchpad.net/~dhis2-devs-core/dhis2/trunk</ulink>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Build
            DHIS2 as normal, by running
            <code>mvn clean install</code>
            (to skip tests, use
            <code>mvn clean install -Dtest=false
              -DfailIfNoTests=false</code>
            ) in the dhis-2 and
            dhis-2\dhis-web folders.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Build the mobile modules by
            running
            <code>mvn clean install</code>
            in the dhis-mobile folder.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Modify
            the dhis-web-portal\pom.xml file, adding a dependency to dhis-web-mobile:
            </para>
          <para>
            <screen>
                  &lt;dependency&gt;
                  &lt;groupId&gt;org.hisp.dhis&lt;/groupId&gt;
                  &lt;artifactId&gt;dhis-web-mobile&lt;/artifactId&gt;
                  &lt;version&gt;${version}&lt;/version&gt;
                  &lt;type&gt;war&lt;/type&gt;
                  &lt;/dependency&gt; </screen>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Build the portal (
            <code>mvn clean
              install</code>
            in the dhis-web-portal folder)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Copy the dhis.war file from dhis-web-portal\target to the
            tomcat\webapps folder.
            Rename it if you
            want.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Install the GSM modem</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Driver for the GSM modem</para>
          <para>Plug
            in your modem and install the drivers. You might have to use the
            manufacturer&apos;s
            provided drivers from a CD or their web page.
            <emphasis>You might need administrator privileges to do this. If you still can&apos;t
              do
              it, try starting Windows in Safe Mode.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>comm.jar</para>
          <para>
            Copy it to your
            <code>java\jreX\lib\ext</code>
            folder. If you&apos;ve got multiple
            installations of JRE, you can find the path to the
            installation used by
            DHIS 2 by right clicking the Monitor Tomcat icon in the system
            tray,
            then Configure -&gt; Java.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>javax.comm.properties</para>
          <para>
            Copy it to your
            <code>java\jreX\lib</code>
            folder.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>win32com.dll</para>
          <para>
            Copy it to your
            <code>java\jreX\bin</code>
            folder.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Note: You might need administrator privileges to do this. If you still
              can&apos;t do it, try starting Windows in Safe Mode.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>SMSserver.conf</para>
          <para>
            Copy it to your
            <code>DHIS2_HOME</code>
            folder (the folder where hibernate.properties is located). The settings in this file
            can also be modified from the Settings page in the mobile module in DHIS 2.
          </para>
          <para>
            In this file the manufacturer and the model of the GSM modem are specified. Also,
            make
            sure the PIN code for the SIM card in the GSM modem is turned off, and set
            <code>modem1.pin=0000</code>
            in the SMSserver.conf, or use the Settings page in the mobile module in DHIS 2 to
            set
            the pin to 0000.
          </para>
          <para>The port of the modem also needs to be specified in this file. After the drivers
            are successfully installed and the modem is installed in a usb port, you can find
            the
            port of the modem by opening Device Manager, locate your modem and right click
            on it,
            click on Properties and navigate to the Modem tab. There you&apos;ll see
            which port is
            assigned to the modem.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Important: Note that if you install the modem into another usb port
              another
              time, the port will change, and you will have to update the settings. If
              you for some
              reason need to take the modem out of your computer, make sure
              you&apos;ll install it
              in the same usb port as last time, or else you&apos;ll have
              to update the
              SMSserver.conf file.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>formIDLayout.csv</para>
          <para>
            Copy it to your
            <code>DHIS2_HOME\mi</code>
            folder. If you have not yet deployed your latest build of DHIS2, you&apos;ll have to
            create the mi folder manually.
          </para>
          <para>This
            file specifies which data elements are to be imported. There&apos;s one line for
            each
            different mobile application in use. The lines start with a mobile
            application&apos;s
            id, then followed by comma separated data element ids and their
            categoryoptioncombo
            ids. The lines will be on the form
            <screen>
                  1 = &lt;data element id&gt;.&lt;categoryoptioncombo id&gt;, 
                  &lt;data element id&gt;.&lt;categoryoptioncombo id&gt;, ... , 
                  &lt;data element id&gt;.&lt;categoryoptioncombo id&gt; </screen>
            E.g.
            <screen>1 = 652.207, 652,208, 20485.271, 20485.272, 683.14</screen>
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Note: If the same mobile application is installed on several phones, the
              id for each application is the same! The formIDLayout.csv file should thus only
              have one line, starting with 1 = .</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Register users</title>
      <para>
        The phone numbers of the cell phones used for reporting with the
        mobile application needs to
        be registered in DHIS 2 in order for the data
        to be imported and stored in the database. A
        phone number has to be
        registered for a user, and the user can
        <emphasis>only</emphasis>
        be
        associated with
        <emphasis>one organisation unit</emphasis>
        !
      </para>
      <para>
        The phone number must include the regular phone number as well as
        the country code without
        <code>+</code>
        or
        <code>00</code>
        . E.g. for a
        Norwegian number, having the country code
        <code>47</code>
        and phone number
        <code>98765432</code>
        , the phone number to store is
        <code>4798765432</code>
        .
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Install the mobile application on a phone</title>
      <para>If
        you&apos;ve got a phone and a computer with Bluetooth, you will in the most cases be able
        to
        send the
        <code>.jar</code>
        file (the mobile application) via Bluetooth from the computer to the phone. When using a
        cable, and also in some cases for phones with Bluetooth, you might have to install some
        software to be able to communicate with the phone. E.g. Nokia PC Suite for Nokia phones.
      </para>
      <para>Once the mobile application is installed on the phone, open it and navigate to the
        last
        page in the application. Select settings, and enter the number of the SIM card in the GSM
        modem. This works both with and without country code.</para>
      <para>If there are several GSM modems installed on several computers running DHIS 2 and you
        want to report to all of these, you can enter the numbers of the SIM cards installed in
        these GSM modems as well in the remaining fields in your mobile application. When clicking
        send, the application will now send the registered data to all the registered numbers at
        the
        same time.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using the system</title>
      <para>Navigate to the Mobile module via Services -&gt; Mobiles</para>
      <section>
        <title>Start the SMS Service</title>
        <para>To start the SMS Service, navigate to &quot;Receive Data and Import&quot; or
          &quot;Send SMS&quot; in the left menu, and then press the Start button next to where
          it
          says: &quot;SMS Service: Not Started&quot;. If everything works well, it should
          now say:
          &quot;SMS Service: Started&quot;.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Receive Data and Import</title>
        <para>To receive and import data, the SMS Service needs to be started. </para>
        <section>
          <title>Automated import of messages</title>
          <para>When SMSs are sent from the phones while the SMS Service is running, the messages
            will be processed automatically, and the data will automatically be imported and
            stored
            in the database.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Import pending messages</title>
          <para>
            If SMSs are sent from the phones to the SIM card in the GSM modem
            while the SMS Service
            is inactive, the messages will be stored as xml
            files in the folder
            <code>DHIS2_HOME\mi\pending</code>
            short time after
            the service is started. On the Receive Data and Import page it will say
            how many SMSs are pending. These can be imported by pressing the &quot;Import
            All
            Pending&quot; button.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Send SMS</title>
        <para>
          The mobile module can be used to send messages to one number at a
          time. To send an SMS, the
          SMS Service needs to be started. Use the local
          phone number here
          <emphasis>without</emphasis>
          the country code.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
