<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Integration Engine</title>
  <para>DHIS2 has a built in component for managing integration scenarios. The functionality is
    provided by <ulink url="http://camel.apacher.org">Apache Camel</ulink> which is itself an
    implementation of the Enterprize Integration Patterns (EIP) described in the book <ulink
      url="http://www.eaipatterns.com"/> by Gregor Hohpe and Bobby Woolf. It complements the web-api
    by providing the means to consume services from other applications and perform transformations
    on data. Because integration requirements are always dependent on particular contexts, the
    integration engine is designed to be configurable on site.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>The integration engine is configured by defining <emphasis>routes</emphasis>. A route
      defines a particular message flow from an external system into DHIS2. Routes may consist of
      timers, http client requests, transformations, message processors, loggers etc. Routes can be
      defined in XML or in Java. XML routes have the advantage that they can be easily configured
      and loaded into a running DHIS2 instance. More complex routes might require the greater
      expressiveness of the Java language. Routes written in Java need to be made available on the
      classpath of the web application on application startup.</para>
    <para/>
    <para>Some sample routes are shown in the sections following. <emphasis>Disclaimer</emphasis>:
      please do not experiment with these routes on a production server. Be sure to test routes
      thoroughly on a test instance before deploying to production. These routes update metadata and
      data automatically.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Synchronising orgunits - an XML route</title>
    <para>One use case which motivated the inclusion of the integration engine into DHIS2 is the
      need to synchronise orgunits. In this example we present a simple XML route which allows one
      DHIS2 instance to update it's orgunits from another DHIS2 instance.</para>
    <para>The unavoidable long lines in the route listing may not render well in the DHIS2 user manual.  This and other
    sample routes can be found in the resources section of the DHIS2 source code.</para>
    <para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<route xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://camel.apache.org/schema/spring camel-spring-2.9.1.xsd"
  xmlns="http://camel.apache.org/schema/spring" id="dataUpdater">

  <description>Synch orgunits every 5 minutes</description>
  <!-- trigger every 5 minutes ... -->
  <from uri="quartz://everyHour?cron=0+0/5+*+*+*+%3F"/>
  <!-- filter required elements from metadata export -->
  <setHeader headerName="CamelHttpQuery">
    <constant>assumeTrue=false&amp;organisationUnits=true&amp;organisationUnitGroups=true&amp;organisationUnitGroupSets=true&amp;organisationUnitLevels=true&amp;attributeTypes=true</constant>
  </setHeader>
  <!-- send http request -->
  <to
    uri="http://apps.dhis2.org/demo/api/metaData.xml?httpClient.authenticationPreemptive=true&amp;authMethod=Basic&amp;authUsername=system&amp;authPassword=System123"/>
  <log logName="org.hisp.dhis.camel" loggingLevel="INFO" message="Importing orgunits"/>
  <!-- import to dhis2 component -->
  <inOut uri="dhis2:metadata"/>
  <!-- log the import summary -->
  <log logName="org.hisp.dhis.camel" loggingLevel="INFO" message="${body}"/>
</route>
]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>Some notes on the above:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Note that the route has an id and a description.  These are important if you want the route to show up in the Import-Export module.</para></listitem>
      <listitem>
          <para>Camel components are configured using urls. The trigger expression for the quartz
            URL should be cron=0+0+*+*+*+?" but the "?" character cannot appear unencoded in the XML route,
            hence the escaped "%3F".  Similarly, the "&amp;" is replaced in the query string with "&amp;mp;"/</para></listitem>
      <listitem>
          <para>Additional parameters to the URL such as "authenticationPreemptive" etc are
            documented for the Camel http component <ulink url="http://camel.apache.org/http.html"
            />. These are consumed by the camel processor and not sent to the server as part oif the
            request.</para></listitem>
      <listitem>
          <para>The dhis2:metadata endpoint is not part of the camel core. It is a DHIS2 specific
            component which is available to the author of DHIS2 routes as a destination for
            importing DXF2 metadata.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Loading an XML route</title>
    <para>Routes like the one in the previous section can be loaded into a running DHIS2 instance through the integration configuration screen found under the Import/Export module.
    From here routes can be enabled and disabled.  The route definition can be updated by adding a new route with the same route id.</para>
    <para>DHIS2 also provides a means to automatically load a set of XML routes on application startup.  When the application starts it will look for a directory called "routes" under the
    DHIS2_HOME directory.  Any XML routes found in that directory will be loaded into the running application.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>A Java route</title>
    <para></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
