<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Getting started with DHIS 2</title>
  <section id="mod2_1">
    <title>Getting started with DHIS2</title>
      <para>After reading this chapter you will be able to understand:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start DHIS 2 from the desktop</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to log-in from the desktop</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create new users and user roles</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <para>You must be sure that you have a current version of the Java Runtime installed on your machine. Depending on your operating system, there are different ways of installing Java. The reader is referred to this <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">website</ulink> for detailed information on getting java installed. </para>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Starting the DHIS2 Live package</title>
      <para>The DHIS2 Live package is the easiest way to get started with DHIS2. DHIS2 Live is appropriate for a stand-alone type of installation.  Simply download the application from <ulink url="http://www.dhis2.org/downloads">here</ulink>. 
        Once the file is downloaded,  you can simply double-click the downloaded file, and get started using DHIS2. </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Working directly with the H2 database</title>
      <para>
        DHIS2 Live uses an embedded <ulink url="www.h2database.com/">H2</ulink> database. This has several advantages - there is no need 
        to install a separate database engine such as PostgresSql or MySql, and backup can be made by just copying the file. The whole db 
        exists in memory, which means high performance. The disadvantage is need for RAM. It is also not suitable for mulitiuser server 
        installations. 
      </para>
      <para>
      In general, it is recommended to work with the database through the DHIS2 user interface, but in some situations one may need to 
      manipulate the data directly. If one downloads H2 separately, it comes with a web interface. It can also be manipulated using 
        <ulink url="http://openoffice.org">OpenOffice.org</ulink>, using the following procedure. This assumes that dhis2-live is located in
        the user's Linux home directory (represented by ~). Substitute the absolute path to your dhis2-live installation.
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start OpenOffice Word Processor and select Tools - Options, then Java - Class Path ... and click on Add Archive...</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the following file (version may differ): ~/dhis2-live/webapps/dhis/WEB-INF/lib/h2-1.1.119.jar</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Close OpenOffice completely and then open OpenOffice.org Database. Select connect to an existing database - JDBC</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Datasource URL is h2:~/dhis2-live/database/dhis2, and JDBC driver class is org.h2.Driver</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>User name is sa, password not needed. Finally, select a name and folder for the .odb file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Note that you can not access the H2 database through OpenOffice Database while DHIS2 Live is running (and vice versa).
        
      </para>
    </section>  
    <section>
      <title>Downloading and installing the server version</title>
      <para>DHIS2 functions both as a
      desktop application, as well as a web-enabled client-server application.
      For larger, production installations with many users and large volumes
      of data (for instance as a national level server) it is recommended to
      install the server version. The latest version of the infrastructure can be
      found <ulink url="http://dhis.uio.no/ci/job/Dhis2%20Web%20Trunk/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/dhis-2/dhis-web/dhis-web-portal/target/dhis.war">here</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>There are many permutations of getting a server installation up and running, and will depend very much on the nature of the installation. A typical installation for a single machine, running Ubuntu Linux will be described in the discussion that follows. This type of single-installation would be appropriate for a small work-group. There are so many different ways to get the application running, and this will depend to a large extent on the number of users you will be catering to, the type of hardware you have available, and the nature of the implementation of the application (e.g one central server as opposed to multiple subnational installations). The example provided here is meant to be a rough guide for those that are setting up a DHIS2 server instance from scratch, however, you should consider all security requirements of your implementation before blindly following this example. </para>
      <para>You will need to decide which back-end database system you will use. DHIS2 is a database agnostic application in principle, and should run on any system with a compatible JDBC driver. However, it is recommended either to use Postgresql or MySQL, as these systems are widely used by other members of the DHIS2 community. In addition to a back-end database system, you will need a compatible servlet container. Apache Tomcat 6 is recommended by the developers, however in principle, the application should run in any  container that conforms to the Servlet 2.5 specification. </para>
      <para>It is certainly possible to install all packages from source code, but it is suggested that you install most of the basic packages through your systems package manager. Depending on which version of Linux that you may be using, you may need to install a newer version of both the back-end database system (such as Postgresql and MySQL) and Servlet container. It is recommended to use at least Postgresl version 8.3 or MySQL 5.0. </para>
      <para>To get started downloading the necessary packages, execute the following commands. Note that you may need to add the <command>sudo</command> command before these commands, if you are not running as root. </para>
      <para><programlisting><userinput>apt-get install nano <userinput>wget nano /etc/apt/sources.list </userinput></userinput></programlisting></para>
      <para>Uncomment and add “multiverse” after “universe” in each line of this file. </para>
      <para>After editing the sources.list execute these commands. </para>
      <para><programlisting><userinput>apt-get update </userinput>
<userinput>apt-get install sun-java6-jdk postgresql postgresql-client</userinput>
<userinput>postgresql-contrib postgresql-8.3-postgis</userinput></programlisting></para>
      <para>This will install a number of packages on your system, including Java and the Postgresql database system. In principle, DHIS2 will run under any servlet container, but it is recommended to use Apache Tomcat. Check with the DHIS2 developers if you have questions about using other servlet containers. To get Tomcat, execute the following commands</para>
      <para><programlisting><userinput><userinput>wget http://apache.mirror.testserver.li/tomcat/tomcat-6/v6.0.20/bin/apache-tomcat-6.0.20.tar.gz</userinput> tar xvzf apache-tomcat-6.0.20.tar.gz mv apache-tomcat-6.0.20 /usr/local/tomcat</userinput></programlisting></para>
      <para>If you need plan on installing Geoserver as part of your DHIS2 installation, go ahead and download and install it. You should check on the <ulink url="http://www.geoserver.org">Geoserver web page</ulink> for the latest version.  </para>
      <para>

<userinput>wget http://downloads.sourceforge.net/geoserver/geoserver-2.0.0a-war.zip</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>unzip geoserver-2.0.0a-war.zip</userinput></para>
      <para>
<userinput>unzip geoserver.war -d /usr/local/tomcat/webapps </userinput></para>
      <para>
<userinput>mv /usr/local/tomcat/webapps/geoserver/data /usr/local/geodata</userinput></para>
      <para>You should now change the default Geoserver password to something more secure. Execute<userinput> nano /usr/local/geodata/security/users.properties </userinput>and change the password and then save all changes. </para>
      <para>Edit one of your persistent environment variables (see <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/EnvironmentVariables#Persistent%20environment%20variables">this page</ulink> for details). Add the following lines to the chosen file. </para>
      <para><envar>export JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib/jvm/java-6-sun</envar></para>
      <para><envar>export JDK_HOME= /usr/lib/jvm/java-6-sun</envar>
</para>
      <para><envar>export JAVA_OPTS=-XX:PermSize=256m -XX:MaxPermSize=1536 -Xms512m -Xmx1024m -server</envar>
</para>
      <para><envar>export GEOSERVER_DATA_DIR=/usr/local/geodata</envar>
</para>
      <para><envar>export DHIS2_HOME=/root/dhis/dhis2</envar>
</para>
      <para>Note that you may need to alter the file paths to point to the actual directories on your system. </para>
      <para>Assuming that you have installed the postgresql database system, you can create a new database with the following commands. </para>
      <para><userinput>sudo su - postgres</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>createdb createdb -E utf-8 <parameter>dhis</parameter></userinput></para>
      <para>Note that you can change the name of the database to anything that suits your environment. </para>
      <para> To tell the DHIS2 application where to find its database you need a <filename>hibernate.properties</filename> file in <envar>DHIS2_HOME</envar> . For a postgres database connection to a database called &apos;dhis&apos;, with user name and password &apos;dhis&apos;, you need to put the following inside your file /root/dhis/dhis2/hibernate.properties: </para>
      <para><userinput>hibernate.dialect = org.hibernate.dialect.PostgreSQLDialect</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>hibernate.connection.driver_class = org.postgresql.Driver</userinput>
</para>
      <para><userinput>hibernate.connection.url = jdbc:postgresql:dhis</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>hibernate.connection.username = dhis </userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>hibernate.connection.password = dhis</userinput>
</para>
      <para><userinput>hibernate.hbm2ddl.auto = update</userinput></para>
      <para>Save this file in the DHIS2_HOME directory.  Exit the current shell in order to reload the environment variables and open a new shell. You will need to start both postgresql as well as the tomcat server. If you installed postgresql with the apt-get command, you can start this from the /etc/init.d/ directory with the commands.  </para>
      <para><userinput>sudo su - </userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>cd /etc/init.d/</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>./S18postgresql start</userinput></para>
      <para>Note that you may need to alter this command to your particular system. </para>
      <para>It is good security practise to run the tomcat application as a separate user. If you do not already have a separate user account, you can create one with the following commands.  </para>
      <para>    <userinput>sudo useradd -d /home/tomcat6 -m tomcat6</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>sudo passwd tomcat6 </userinput></para>
      <para>You should not change the file permissions for the entire directory that you installed Tomcat to, with the following command. </para>
      <para><userinput>sudo chown -R tomcat6:tomcat6 /usr/local/tomcat</userinput></para>
      <para>To start the application, login as the user, navigate to the <filename>/usr/local/tomcat/bin/</filename> directory, and execute the <filename>start.sh</filename> script. </para>
      <para><userinput>sudo su - tomcat6</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>cd /usr/local/tomcat/bin</userinput></para>
      <para><userinput>./startup.sh</userinput></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing DHIS2 with the Debian install package</title>
      <para>If you are using Ubuntu or Debian, a separate Debian installation package has been created to simplify the installation process. You can simply download this <ulink url="http://www.dhis2.org/download/dhis2-2.0.3.deb">file</ulink> and then install DHIS2 from the command line with the following command. </para>
      <para><userinput>sudo dpkg -i dhis2-2.0.3.deb</userinput></para>
      <para>You can also install this Debian package from your systems package manager. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="mod2_2">
    <title>Logging on to DHIS2</title>
    <para>Regardless of whether you have installed the server version of the
    desktop Live version, you will use a web-browser to log on to the
    application. DHIS 2 should be compatible with most modern web-browsers,
    although you will need to ensure that Java Script is enabled.</para>
    <para>To log on to the application just enter <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/dhis" type="">http://localhost:8080/dhis</ulink> if you
    are using the DHIS2 live package, or replace localhost with the name or IP
    address of the server where the server version is installed.</para>
    <para>Once you have started DHIS2, either on-line or offline, the displayed
    screen will prompt you to enter your registered ‘user name’ and
    ‘password’. After entering the required information click on log-in button
    to log into the application. The default user name and password are &apos;admin&apos; and &apos;district&apos;. They should be changed immediately upon logging on the first time. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>DHIS2 Login screen</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/dhis2_login_screen.jpg" format="JPG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section id="mod2_3">
    <title>Creating new users and roles</title>
    <para>This section will describe how to add new users to the DHIS 2
    application.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Open User Menu</title>
      <para>To create or find a user begin with clicking on the ‘user’ module
      displayed in the drop down menu of the Maintenance module located on the
      main tool bar on the top part of the displayed screen. User names
      already registered will appear as a list as seen in the screen shot
      below.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Select Users menu item</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/select_user_menu.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Search by user name</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/search_user_by_name.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>You can search for specific user names in the user list by
      entering the name in the ‘filter by user name’ field as shown
      above.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Define a new role</title>
      <para>As part of creating a user name you are required to define the user
      role. Do so by clicking on the ‘user role’ appearing on the left side of
      the displayed screen.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Create new user role</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/select_user_role.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>This will lead you to the Role Management page where you will have
      to click on <guibutton>Add new</guibutton> to create a new role.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Add new user role</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/add_user_role.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>The following screen will open and here in the first text box you
      need to give Name of the Role such as Super User, Admin User, etc. The
      second text box called ‘Description’ gives more information about the
      type of User Role that is being created for e.g. State Admin User,
      District Data Entry.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Role maintenance page</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/role_maintainence_page.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Next you will specify the particular data set(s) that are to be
      made available to the particular role. You will also need to specify the
      type of ‘authority’ to be given to the particular user. For each of the
      three options namely Datasets, Reports and Authorities user can select
      multiple options from the scroll down menu provided against each field.
      A user can choose multiple options either by moving them
      one-by-one.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Adding a dataset to a user role</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/assign_one_dataset_user_role.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>In order for particular users to be able to enter data, you must
      add them to both a dataset as well as an organisational unit level. You
      can also select multiple datasets individually by pressing the Ctrl key
      on the keyboard and clicking on individual datasets.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Adding multiple datasets to user roles</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/assign_multiple_datasets_user_role.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Finally when you have entered the required fields click on
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> which is located on the lower part of the
      displayed screen. The desired user role and related authorisation will
      be saved to the database, and can then be assigned to a particular
      user.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Add New User</title>
      <para>Under particular user role there can be more than one user. To add
      new users go to the User options under the Maintenance module.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Add new user</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/add_new_user.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>To add a new user, just follow these steps:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Add New</guibutton> button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter New User details like <guilabel>User name</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Password</guilabel>, <guilabel>Confirm password</guilabel>, <guilabel>Surname</guilabel>, <guilabel>First name</guilabel> and <guilabel>Email</guilabel> in new user’s option
          tabs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button for confirmation of
          new user details and follow the user error while creation of new
          user.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The recently created new user can be seen in main’ User
          management Screen</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can edit (like password, surname….etc) and delete the
          details of new/old users by selecting corresponding User’s
          <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton>
          Buttons.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click on <guibutton>Save</guibutton> tab after editing all
          details of a particular selected user.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Add or edit users</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/add_edit_users.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>User management screen</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/user_management.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="mod2_4">
    <title>Logging off of DHIS2</title>
    <para>Just click on the <guibutton>Log off</guibutton> button to exit the
    application.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Logging off of DHIS 2</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/dhis2_logoff.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
</chapter>
