<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[]>
<chapter>
  <title>Using Tracker Capture</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Tracker capture is an advanced version of the event capture app. While the event capture
      deals with single event without registration, tracker capture deals with multiple events
      (including single event) with registration. The implication of this is that, any event
      capturing has to be for a registered tracked entity instance (TEI). This makes
      registration/searching of TEI a key component of the tracker capture app. </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>TEI Searching/Registration</title>
    <para>To proceed with the tracker capture one needs to have a TEI. As shown in the screenshot
      below, the first page of the app provides two features for this - searching an existing one or
      registering a new one.</para>
    <para/>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example: searching/registration</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/tracker_capture/search_register.png" format="PNG"
            width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>All searching and registration operations are accessible from the screen shown above.<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Searching: there are two modes of searching - simple and advanced. The simple one
            works by typing a free text on the provided area. What is typed in the input box is
            applied across all attributes for partial match. The advanced one, which is accessible
            when the small drop-down button is clicked - works when various search criteria are
            provided in the drop down window. Here, the match is exact match. Both search modes
            return matching list of TEI displayed in a table. </para>
          <para>If a program is selected, the app provides further filtering on the table based on
            enrollment status which are All, Active, Completed, Cancelled.  as shown below.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Enrollment status filtering icons</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="resources/images/tracker_capture/enrollment_status.png" format="PNG"
                  width="20%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
          <para>The advanced search also provides one more additional feature. Under normal
            circumstances, advanced search is conducted for the selected orgunit (from left-hand
            side tree) and scope (which could be Selected, Immediate children or All children).  The
            left-hand side tree is generated based on the logged in user's assigned orgunits.
            However, there could be cases to search for a TEI from another orgunit (which is not
            neccessarily part of the assigned orgunits. To support such use case, advanced search
            provides another orgunit tree. The tree displayed here depends on the role that the
            logged in user has. If the user has role "Search Tracked Entity Instance in All Org
            Units" or "ALL", a tree with all available orgunits is provided other wise the tree
            displayed in advanced search is the same as the one on the left-hand side. Whichever
            tree (or hierarchy of orgunits) is provided, if an orgunit is selected in advanced
            search, the searching is conducted against this selected orgunit and scope.</para>
          
          <para>While in the TEI table, clicking on any row takes to the selected TEI's
            dashboard.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Registration: this is accessible through the "Register" button. During registration,
            it is possible to stay on the same page and keep doing more registration or go straight
            to the dashboard of the registered TEI. Selecting a program and doing registration also
            performs enrollment at the background. If a TEI is registered without a program, then
            enrollment is possible from the TEI dashboard.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
    <para/>
    <para>Both search and registration are dictated by a selected program. It is program attributes
      which are being used as search criteria, registration attributes and also as columns names for
      tracked entity list. If no program is selected, the system picks default attributes. If no
      search criteria is assigned for an attribute, then the attribute has no effect on searching.
      However to control the appearance or not of an attribute as a column list, one has to go
      through a menu available under the small gear icon. </para>
    <para>Once a TEI is obtained - either through searching or registration - the app presents the
      selected TEI's dashboard.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>TEI dashboard</title>
    <para>All operations on a tracked entity are available from this dashboard. Anticipating
      multiple usecases or operations on registered TEI, we have structured the dashboard as a
      collection of widgets - more widgets can be added. This helps to scale and handle complexity
      while staying simple and clean. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example: TEI dashboard</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/tracker_capture/tei_dashboard.png" format="PNG" width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>As shown in the figure above, the dashboard starts with four sets of menus at the top: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>back button - this helps to go back to the search and registration page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>previous and next buttons - these are buttons to acces the previous/next TEI
            details</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>program selection menu - this is to dictate what kind of data to record and track
            for the selected TEI. This also affects the contents of the widgets.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a small gear icon at the right corner - currently this helps to control which
            widgets to display. From the figure above, there are six widgets on display. The widgets
            are collapsible, responsive and draggable - this helps to acquire optimal view area as
            per user needs. Widget (re)arrangments are saved automatically per user per
            program.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para> The widgets:- <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Enrollment widget</emphasis> - this helps to enroll the
            tracked entity for the selected program. If an active enrollment already exists, the
            widget automatically displays it with some details about it. The widget also helps to do
            some operations on active enrollment - for example terminate/complete. A link to history
            is also provided if the TEI has historical enrollment.</para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Dataentry widget</emphasis> - this is for doing data entry
            using either default or custom forms. Depending on program definition, in particular
            program stages, events will be displayed in a timely fashion. Clicking on any of them
            displays the corresponding data entry. If a stage needs new event, a plus icon is
            displayed for new event creation. To proceed with data entry, it is mandatory to have
            event date. Once an event date is specified it is not possible to change due date. The
            assumption is that by specifying event date, the event has already taken place. If the
            event hasn't occurred yet, it is possible to change due date - this is effectively doing
            nothing but rescheduling. The buttons at the bottom help to change the status of a
            selected event. Another key feature from this widget is addition of multiple notes for
            an event. Normally data recording is through datalements, however there are cases where
            it is necessary to record additional information or comments. This is where the notes
            section comes handy. However, a interesting feature here is - it is not possible to
            delete a note. The idea is notes are more like log books. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Profile widget</emphasis> - this is to edit TEI's profile or
            attributes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Relationship widget</emphasis> - this helps to relate the
            selected TEI (the one whose dashboard is shown) to another TEI. Adding a relative is
            possible by either searching from existing or registering a new one.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Notes widget</emphasis> - this is the same as event notes. The
            difference between the two is that, here notes are attached not to events but to
            enrollments. This helps to record some notes based on enrollment - for example why is an
            enrollment terminated or what is the overall observation of the TEI throughout the
            enrollment.</para>
        </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Report widget</emphasis> - this is to provide a "journal" of the
            tracked entity per program. A report row is provided for each program the TEI is/was
            associated.</para>
      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Basic reports</title>
    <para>Tracker capture app also provides some basic reports. These reports are accessible by
      clicking on the "Reports" link on the left-hand side. Below is a description for some of the
      reports.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>List of tracker reports</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/tracker_capture/tracker_reports.png" format="PNG" width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Running any of these repots is very easy, one just has to select a program, orgnisation
      unit scope and whenever possible start and end dates. Below is a sample program summary
      report. It displays a list of TEI's and their records for "MNCH/PNC (Adult Woman)" program.
      The records are organized in the form of tabs where each tab is a program stage. The columns
      in the table are data elements which are configured to be displayed in reports under program
      stage definition.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example: program summary report</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/tracker_capture/program_summary_report.png" format="PNG" width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
</chapter>
