<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Settings</title>
  <para>The settings module provides a set of application configuration options. There are two main
    groups of settings: the <emphasis role="italic">system settings</emphasis> apply to the whole
    system and all its users while the <emphasis role="italic">user settings</emphasis> apply to the
    environment of the currently logged in user. The system settings can be accessed from the
    maintenance menu, settings module. The user settings can be accessed under the profile menu,
    settings page.</para>
  <section>
    <title>System settings</title>
    <para>The system settings section provides general configuration options and options specifically for appearance and email.</para>
    <section id="systemGeneralSettings">
      <title>General settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Cache strategy: Decides for how long reports and responses related to analysis
            should be cached. If you are using the scheduled, nightly data mart tasks it makes sense
            to put this on &quot;Cache until 6 AM tomorrow&quot;. This is because we know that data in reports
            change at that time, and you can safely cache data up to the moment when the data mart
            is updated. If you are loading data continuously into the datamart you should set it to
            &quot;No cache&quot;. If you load data very infrequently into data mart you should consider
            setting it to &quot;Cache for two weeks&quot;.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maximum number of analytics records: This number can be increased to provide more records from the analytics. The default is 50,000 and can be increased. </para>
          <warning>
            <para>You should be exceedingly careful when increasing the maximum number of analytics records, for instance to &quot;Unlimited&quot;. This could result in severe server instability, due to clients requesting large amounts of data from the system. </para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Number of database server CPUs: The number of CPU cores of your database server can be configured as a system setting. This allows the system to perform optimally when the database is hosted on a different server than the application server, as the analytics engine scales linearly on the number of available cores. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Infrastructural data elements: This setting defines a data element group where the member data elements should describe data about the infrastructure of organisation units. Examples of such infrastructural data elements could be population, doctors, beds, Internet connectivity and climate. This infrastructural data can currently be viewed in the GIS module in the facility information sheet.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Infrastructural period type: Sets the frequency for which the data elements in the
            infrastructural data elements group are captured. This will typically be yearly. When
            viewing the infrastructural data you will be able to select the time period of the data
            source.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Feedback recipients: This setting defines a user group where the members will
            receive all messages being sent through the function for writing feedback in the
            dashboard module. This will typically be members of the super user team who are able to
            support and answer questions coming from end-users.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maximum offline organisation unit levels: This setting defines how many levels in
            the organisation unit hierarchy will be available offline in the organisation unit tree
            widget. Under normal circumstances you can leaves this on the lowest level, which is
            default behavior. Setting it to a higher level might be useful in order to reduce
            initial load time in cases where you have a large number of organisation units, typically
            more than 30 000.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>System notifications email address: An email address can be specified to receive system notifications. Notifications about failures in processes such as analytics table generation will be sent here. This is useful for application monitoring.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data analysis std dev factor: Sets the number of standard deviations for use in the outlier analysis performed on the captured data in the data entry module. The default value is 2; a high value will catch less outlier values than a low value.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Days after period end to qualify for timely data submission: Sets the number of days after the end of a period in which a data entry form must be marked as complete in order to be considered timely. This affects the &quot;reporting rate&quot; tool in the reporting module which lists forms marked as complete as well as marked as complete in time. The default value is 15.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Phone number area code: The area code for the area in which your deployment is located. Used for sending and receiving
            SMS.Typically, this would be a country code, for instance , +260 , which is the country code for Zambia. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Help page link: A URL can be provided for an alternative help source. This defines the URL which users will see when selecting Profile-&gt;Help.  </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Server base URL: The full, externally accessible base URL for this server. Example:
            https://apps.dhis2.org/demo is the server base URL for the DHIS 2 demo server. The URL
            is used to provide links to this server from external locations such as in emails sent
            from the system. Note that if this URL is not present, emails sent from the messaging
            system will not contain a reply link.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Google Analytics (Universal Analytics) Key: Set your Google UA key here to provide analytics for your DHIS 2 instance. Most
            places are covered, but it will not be provided for custom apps. Read more about Google Analytics at <ulink url="http://google.com/analytics">http://google.com/analytics</ulink>
              .</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable multi-organisation unit forms: Enable support for entering data forms for
            multiple organisation units at the same time, in data entry, click on the parent
            organisation unit for the children that you want to enter data for, and the dataset list
            will include datasets that are assigned to the children of that parent.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Omit indicator values with zero numerator value in data mart: Defines whether
            aggregated indicator values with zero as the numerator value should be written to the
            indicator data mart table. Having such values written is required for instance when
            connecting Excel pivot tables to the data mart as Excel will need the numerator data to
            correctly aggregate up in the organisation unit hierarchy. If third-party tools like
            Excel are not used with the application this will reduce the total number of values
            written to the data mart (which again will improve performance) and could safely be set
            to omit.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Put analytics in maintenance mode: Puts the analytics engine / Web API resource in
            maintenance mode, implying that 503 Service Unavailable will be returned for all
            requests. This is useful when you need to perform maintenance on the server like
            rebuilding indexes while the server is running in production, in order to reduce load
            and more efficiently carry out the maintenance.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="systemAppearanceSettings">
      <title>System appearance settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application title: Sets the application title on the top menu.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application introduction: Sets an introduction of the system which will be visible
            on the top-left part of the login page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application notification: Sets a notification which should be displayed to users.
            Will be visible on the front page under the login area.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application footer: Sets a text in the footer area of the login page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Style: Sets the style / look-and-feel of the system. The corresponding user style setting overrides this.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start page: Sets page / module which the user will be redirected to after logging
            in. The dashboard module is the recommended start module.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Flag: Sets the flag which is displayed in the left menu of the dashboard module.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Require authority to add to view object lists: Will hide menu and index page items /
            links to lists of objects if the current user does not have the authority to create the
            type of objects (privately or publicly).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="systemEmailSettings">
      <title>Email settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Host name: Refers to the host name of the SMTP server. For instance when using
            Google SMTP services this should be smtp.gmail.com.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Port: The port to connect to the SMTP server.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>User name: The user name of the user account with the SMTP server. For instance mail@dhis2.org.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Password: The password of the user account with the SMTP server.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>TLS: Refers to whether the SMPT server requires TLS for connections.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Access settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Self registration account user role: Defines which user role should be given to self-registered user accounts. To enable
            self-registration of users, select any user role from the list. To disable it, select &quot;Do not allow self registration&quot;. When
            enabled, a link to the self-registration form will be displayed on the login page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Do not require recaptcha for self registration: Whether or not to use reCAPTCHA for user registration.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Self registration account organisation unit: Defines which organisation unit should
            be associated with self-registered users. Any organisation unit must be selected in
            order to enable self registration.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable user account recovery: Defines whether users are allowed to restore the
            password of their account if they forgotten it. When enabled, a link to the account
            recovery form will be displayed on the front page. User account recovery requires that
            you have configured email settings (SMTP).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable user account invite: Defines user account invites can be sent. Account
            invites let you invite new users to create their own accounts by sending an email
            invitation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allow users to grant own user roles: Defines whether users should be allowed to
            grant the user roles they are granted themselves to others.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Users must belong to a group controlled by the user manager: This allows user groups
            to play a role in user management. When checked, user A can manage user B only if user
            B belongs to a user group to which user A has read/write access. When user A creates a
            new user, she or he must assign the new user to such a user group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Require user account password change: Require that users change their password every
            3,6,12 months. Please note that for 2.14 release, they will have to login through the
            desktop to change passwords.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>OpenID provider: Defines the OpenId provider.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>OpenID provider label: Defines the label to display for the specified OpenID
            provider.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Calendar settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Calendar: Defines which calendar system should be used throughout the system.</para>
          <para>There are currently eight calendar systems which are supported, namely Coptic, Ethiopic, Gregorian, Julian, Islamic, ISO, Nepal and Thai. Note that this is a system wide setting. It is not possible to have multiple calendars within a single DHIS2 instance.  </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Date format: Defines which date format should be used throughout the system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Synchronization settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remote server URL: The URL of the remote server running DHIS 2 to upload data values
            to. Use of SSL/HTTPS is recommended since username and password is sent with the request
            (using basic authentication). The system will attempt to synchronize data once every
            minute. Note that you must enable data synch from Data administration &gt;
            Scheduling.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remote server username: The username of the DHIS 2 user account on the remote server
            to use for data synchronization.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remote server password: The password of the DHIS 2 user account on the remote
            server. The password will be stored encrypted.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Remote access settings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>CORS whitelist: A list of domains to acccept cross-origin requests for resources.
            CORS is a mechanism that allows resources to be requested from another domain. This
            means e.,g. that you can make requests to the DHIS 2 Web API from a web page or portal
            living on another domain than the DHIS 2 instance. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
