<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<section id="mobile_web_based">
  <title>Mobile browser based data entry</title>
  <section>
    <title>Getting started with mobile browser data entry</title>
    <para>Once you have entered in the URL of you DHIS2 instance, simply login with your username and password. Press the login button to continue, or the &quot;Reset&quot; button to clear all fields.</para>
    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/mobile-browser-login.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>
    <para>Once you have logged in you will have three options to choose from: Data entry, Settings, and reports.</para>
    <para>To change the interface language of the mobile client, choose the &quot;Settings&quot; option, then select an &quot;Interface language&quot; by choosing a language from the drop-down list. Finally click &quot;Save&quot; to change the interface language.</para>
    <para><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/mobile-browser-settings.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>
    <para>To start data entry, choose the &quot;Data entry&quot; link from the &quot;Home&quot; screen. </para>
    <important>
      <para>If you choose the &quot;Desktop version&quot; link, you will be directed to the standard DHIS2 web interface. This  may consume much more bandwidth. Using the mobile data entry screen is the recommended method for entering data through mobile devices, so that the total amount of bandwidth consumed is minimized.</para>
    </important>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/after-login.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Then select from a list of available organisation units which the user is allowed to enter data on behalf of. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/select-org-unit.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Next, select a dataset to enter data for. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/select-dataset.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Select from a list of available periods to enter data for from the next screen. Periods which have been marked with a check mark indicate that they already have already been completed.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/select-period.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Next, enter data for each data element. The category options for each data element are indicated in parentheses at the end of the name of the data element.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/data-entry.PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Once you have finished entering all the data, you will be given the option to mark the dataset as complete and save it. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis-web-light-data-entry/dataset-complete-save.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Once you have finished entering data, you can logout by pressing the &quot;Logout&quot; link.</para>
  </section>
</section>
