<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Data elements and indicators</title>
  <para>This sub module is required for the management of the data elements and indicators used by the application. When the ‘Data Elements and Indicators’ options is chosen from the main Maintance menu, the following screen appears:
</para>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_main.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
  <para>There are three main functions of this module: addition and attribution of data elements and indicators, and the defintion of a data dictionary . </para>
  <section>
    <title>Data elements</title>
    <para>Data elements form the basis of DHIS2. Data elements define what is actually recorded in system, e.g. number of immunizations or number of cases of malaria. The actual creation and defition of the data elements themselves are far beyond the scope of this manual to describe, but it is assumed that an administrator will be provided with a list of standardized data elements for inclusion into the DHIS2 system. </para>
    <para>There are XXX main options for data elements, each of which will be described below. </para>
    <para/>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data elements. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element group</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data element groups. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element group editor</para>
        <para>Easily add or remove data elements to and from data element groups. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element group set editor</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data elements group sets.   </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element categories</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data element categories. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Data element maintence</title>
      <para>To access the data element maintainence mage, choose Maintainence-&gt;Data elements-&gt;Data element. </para>
      <para>The ‘Filter by name’ will allow you to filter a range of data elements if you know either the full name of the data element, or just a part of it. Type the name
into the search field andany matching data elements are displayed below.
                                                                                            
               You can also choose ‘Filter by group/view all’ to narrow down a data
               element search within a particular data element group. In default mode, this
               field will display all the data elements in the application.
               The ‘Get PDF’ button can be clicked to generate a .pdf file of all the data
               elements. The &apos;Sort&apos; button can be used to sort the data elements into alphabetical order. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_main2.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>To add a new data element, click the &apos;Add new&apos; button. There are various options available from this page that allow the user to modify data elements already present in the database. Click the &quot;Edit&quot;<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/edit.png" align="center"/> button to modify the properties of a data element that has been previouly defined. Each of the options are described below.   </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_edit.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name: Define the precise name of the data element in this field. Each data element must have a unique name. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Short name: Typically, an abbreviation of the full data element name. This attribute is often used in reports to display the name of the data element, where there is limited space available. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Alternative name: Allows the defintion of an alternative name of the data element. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Code: In many countries, data elements are assigned a code. This code can be entered in thsi field. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Description: Allows a full textual description of the data element to be entered. The user should be as precise as possible, and include full information on how the data element is measured and what its meaning is. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Active: Defines whether a given data element is active or not. Data elements marked as inactive, will not be displayed in the data entry screens. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Domain type: Defines whether a data element is an aggregate or patient type of data element. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Value type: Defines the type of data this data element will be used to record. Currently there are four options: number, text, yes/no (boolean), and date. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Aggregation operator: Defines the default aggregation operation that will be used on this data element. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>URL:        A URL having an in-depth description of the data element can be
entered in the ‘URL’ field.
 This could be for instance, a link to a metadata repository or registry that contains detailed technical information about the definition and measurement of the data element. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Combination of categories: Defines which category combination the data element should have. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data element group sets: Click the check box to activate this option  hen choose which data element group sets this data element should belong to. Available data element group sets are displaye din the upper window. Click the desired data element group set, then the <guibutton>&quot;Add selected&quot;</guibutton> button to add the data element to the group set. To remove a data element from a group set, click the data element group set in the lower list, and then click<guibutton> &quot;Remove selected&quot;</guibutton>. </para>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_elements_group_sets.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Calculated: This option is available only when a data element is created. </para>
          <para>Select the data elements that will be used to define the calculated data element, and then click &quot;Add selected&quot; to add them calculated data element composition list. Fill in the correct factor for the data element calculation component (defaults to 1). Component elements of the calculated data element can be removed from the definition by pressing the &quot;Remove&quot; button. <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_calculated_define.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Aggregation levels:         The Aggregation Levels option allows the data element to be
aggregated at one or more levels. When the user clicks on the Aggregation
levels option, a drop down menu appears which displays available
aggregation levels. The desired aggregation level is then selected by clicking
the ‘Add Selected’ button.
 By default, the aggregation will start at the lowest assgined organisation unit. <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_aggregation_levels.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
