<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Using Event Visualizer</title>
  <section>
    <title>Event Visualizer overview</title>
    <para>The event visualizer app enables chart analysis of events.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Charts with aggregated values</title>
      <para>An event report is always based on a program. You can do analysis based on a range of
        dimensions. Each dimension can have a corresponding filter. Dimensions can be selected from
        the left-side menu and includes the following:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data elements</emphasis>: Start by selecting the program and
            program stage for the event report. The data elements associated with the selected
            program will be listed under available items. Each data element acts as a dimension, and
            can be selected by double-clicking on it. After selecting a data element, it will be
            visible under "selected data items". Here you can specify a filter for each data
            element, with operators such as "greater than", "in" or "equal" together with a filter
            value.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Periods</emphasis>: For the period dimension you have three
            options: relative periods, fixed periods and start/end dates. Relative periods can e.g.
            be "last 12 months", and has the advantage that it keeps the data in the report up to
            date as time goes. Fixed periods can e.g. be "January 2014". You can swith to start/end
            dates by selecting from the drop-down menu under the periods tab, which lets you specify
            flexible dates for the time span in the report.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Organisation units</emphasis>: The organisation unit dimension
            lets you select any org unit from the hierarchy. You can use the org unit mode selector
            to select org units explicitly, by org unit hierarchy levels and by org unit
            groups.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/images/event_visualizer/event_visualizer.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>By clicking <emphasis role="bold">Layout</emphasis> from the top menu you can control
        which dimensions should appear as columns, rows and filters in the pivot table. Each data element
        appears as individual dimensions and can be placed on any of the axes. Note that the series and
        category panels can only have one dimension at the time.</para>
      <para>Note that data elements of continuous value types (real numbers/decimal numbers) can only
        be used as filters, and will automatically be positioned as filters in the layout dialog.
        The reason for this is that continuous number cannot be grouped into sensible ranges and
        used on columns and rows.</para>
      <para>Event charts can be saved as favorites by clicking on "Favorites" in the top menu.
        Favorites can later be restored by clicking on them in the list of favorites.</para>
      <para>Event charts can be downloaded in various popular formats by clicking on the "Download"
        button on the top menu.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Options</title>
      <para>An event report can be customized using a range of options, which can be accessed by
        clicking on "Options" in the top menu. The following options apply to aggregated values-type
        reports only:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Show values: Show values as numbers on top of each series.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>Hide empty category items: Hides category items with no data from the chart.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>Show trend lines: The trend line will visualize how your data evolves over time - e.g.
          is performance improving or deteriorating. Makes sense when periods are selected as
          category. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Target line value/title: Displays a horizontal line at the given domain value. Useful e.g. when you want to compare your performance to the current target.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Base line value/title: Displays a horizontal line at the given domain value. Useful e.g. when you want to visualize how your performance has evolved since the beginning of a process.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Range axis max/min: Defines the maximum and minium value which will be visible on the
          range axis.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Range axis tick steps: Defines the number of ticks which will be visible on the range
          axis.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Range axis decimals: Defines the number of decimals which will be used for range axis
          values.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Range axis title: Displays a label next to the range axis (also referred to as the Y
          axis). Can give context information to the chart, e.g. the unit of measure being
          used.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Domain axis title: Displays a label below the domain axis (also referred to as the X
          axis). Can give context information to the chart, e.g. the type of periods being
          listed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hide chart legend: Hides the legend and leaves more room for the chart itself.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hide chart title: Hides the title of your chart.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Chart title: Type any title you like and it will appear above the chart.</para>
      </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
