<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY br ''>]>
<chapter>
  <chapterinfo>
    <title>DHIS 2 Documentation Guide</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Jason</firstname>
      <surname>Pickering</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname/>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <pubdate>14/09/09</pubdate>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>DHIS2</keyword>
      <keyword>documentation</keyword>
      <keyword>DocBook</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>2</revnumber>
        <date>28/10/09</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>
          Added some more information on multilingual documents and editors.</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>29/09/09</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Added more information on getting started with bzr and
          DocBook</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>DHIS2 Documentation Guide</title>
  <section id="docs_1">
    <title>DHIS 2 Documentation System Overview</title>
    <para remap="">DHIS 2 is a web-based aggregate information management system under
    very active development. While primarily intended for management of aggregate, georeferenced health data, it should be possible to use the system for other purposes as well. Currently, there are a large number of
    disconnected pockets of documentation in various formats (e.g.
    MediaWiki, Word documents, Confluence). There is a need to consolidate the
    documentation process and bring it more in-line with the distributed
    nature of the development of the application itself. It has been suggested
    therefore to move the current documentation to the DocBook platform. This
    article will not discuss the relative merits of the DocBook platform, but
    rather will serve as a brief guide to its use by DHIS 2 implementers,
    users and developers. Readers are encouraged to make their own decision
    about whether to use DocBook or not for documentation purposes.</para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
