<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>DHIS 2 Documentation Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jason</firstname>

      <surname>Pickering</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname></orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>14/09/09</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>DHIS2</keyword>

      <keyword>documentation</keyword>

      <keyword>DocBook</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>DHIS 2 Documentation System Overview</title>

    <para remap="">DHIS 2 is a web-based information management system under
    very active development. Currently, there are a large number of
    disconnected pockets of documentation across in various formats (e.g.
    MediaWiki, Word documents, Confluence). There is a need to consolidate the
    documentation process and bring it more inline with the distributed nature
    of the development of the application itself. It has been suggested
    therefore to move the current documentation to the DocBook platform. This
    article will not discuss the relative merits of the DocBook platform, but
    rather will serve as a brief guide to its use by DHIS 2 implementers,
    users and developers. Readers are encouraged to make their own decision
    about whether to use DocBook or not for documentation purposes.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <para>One of the main advantages of DocBook is that there is complete
    seperation between the content and presentation. DocBook is a pure XML
    format, and is well documented. It is beleived that only a very small
    subset of its features will be required in order to acheive much higher
    quality documentation for DHIS. There are some 400 seperate mark-up
    elements that cater to almost any level of technical documentation needs,
    but in reality, only a few dozen of these element will probably need to be
    employed to achieve high-quality documentation for DHIS 2, both for
    printed as well as online formats such as HTML or integrated help systems
    with the application itself. Therefore, there are wide range of
    possibilities in terms of which editor can be used for the creation of
    DocBook files. A fairly complete list of possibilities is located <ulink
    url="http://wiki.docbook.org/topic/DocBookAuthoringTools">here</ulink>.
    <ulink url="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/persoedition.html?">XMLmind
    XML Editor Personal Edition</ulink> is a good balance between
    functionality and simplicity. </para>

    <para>One of the key concepts to keep in mind when authoring documentation
    in DocBook, or other presentation neutral formats, is that the <emphasis
    role="bold">content </emphasis>of the document should be considered in the
    first instance. The <emphasis role="bold">presentation </emphasis>of the
    document will take place in a seperate step, where it will be rendered
    into different formats, such as HTML and PDF. It is therefore important
    that the document is will organized, and strctured, with appropriate
    DocBook tags and structural elements being considered. </para>

    <para>It is good practice to break your document in to various sections
    using the "sect", or section element. Section elements can also be nested
    within each other, such as "Section 1" and "Section 2". This concept is
    essentially the same as Microsoft Word or other word processing programs.
    DocBook will automatically take care of numbering the sections for you
    when the document is produced. Two other important elements are the
    "itemizedlist" and "numberedlist". These are quite similar, but an
    itemized list corresponds to a bulleted list, which a numbered list will
    be rendered with each element being numbered sequentially. Other key
    elements are "screenshot" and "table" which should be self-explanatory.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Producing DHIS2 documentation</title>

    <para>Currently, the documentation system is part of the source code
    housed at <ulink url="???">Launchpad</ulink>. In order to start adding or
    editing the documentation, you should first perform a checkout of the
    sourcecode. Edit your DocBook document and place it in the
    <filename>/dhis2/docs/src/docbkx</filename> directory. Place any image
    files that may be linked to your document in the
    <filename>/dhis2/docs/src/docbkx/images/</filename> folder. Be sure to
    test if you document is actually valid by running <command>mvn
    docbkx:generate-html</command>from the <filename>/dhis2/docs</filename>
    main documentation directory. This command will generate an HTML document
    from your DocBook source images and place them in the
    <filename>/dhis2/docs/target/site/html</filename> directory. You can then
    commit these documentation changes to the main source code tree. </para>
  </section>
</article>
