<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<?altova_sps http://www.altova.com/sps/Template/Publishing/docbook.sps?>
<article>
	<articleinfo>
		<date>17/09/09</date>
		<title>Getting started with DHIS 2</title>
		<author>
			<surname>Unknown</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<orgname/>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>17/09/09</date>
				<authorinitials>JPP</authorinitials>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Initial conversion from MS Word format to DocBook</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<sect1>
		<title>Getting started with DHIS2</title>
		<para/>
		<highlights>
			<para>After reading this chapter you will be able to understand:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Start DHIS 2 from the desktop</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>How to log-in from the desktop</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Create new users and user roles</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</highlights>
		<para/>
		<sect2>
			<title>Downloading and installing the desktop version</title>
			<para>The easist way to get started with the application is to download
      the DHIS2 Live package. This version of the applicaiton comes
      prepackaged, and requires on a single download. You can get the latest
      version <ulink type="" url="???" userlevel="">here</ulink>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Downloading and installing the server version</title>
			<para>As described in the previous module, DHIS2 functions both as a
      desktop application, as well as a web-enabled client-server application.
      For larger, production installations with many users and large volumes
      of data (for instance as a national level server) it is reccomended to
      install the server version. The latest version of the application can be
      found <ulink url="???">here</ulink>. A seperate <olink>guide</olink>
      describing the installation and setup of the server version can be found
      is also available. </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Starting the DHIS2 Live package</title>
			<para>Placeholder for this text. </para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Logging on to DHIS2</title>
		<para>Regardless of whether you have installed the server version of the
    desktop Live version, you will use a web-browser to logon to the
    application. DHIS 2 should be compatible with most modern web-browsers,
    although you will need to ensure that JavaScript is enabled. </para>
		<para>To logon to the application just enter <ulink type="" url="???">http://localhost:8080/dhis</ulink> if you are using the DHIS2
    live package, or replace localhost with the name or IP address of the
    server where the server version is installed. </para>
		<para>Once you have started DHIS2, either online or offline, the displayed
    screen will prompt you to enter your registered ‘user name’ and
    ‘password’. After entering the required information click on log-in button
    to log into the application. </para>
		<screenshot>
			<screeninfo>DHIS2 Login screen</screeninfo>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="???"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Creating new users and roles</title>
		<para>This section will describe how to add new users to the DHIS 2
    application. </para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Open User Menu</title>
			<para>To create or find a user begin with clicking on the ‘user’ module
      displayed in the drop down menu of the Maintenance module located on the
      main tool bar on the top part of the displayed screen. User names
      already registered will appear as a list as seen in the screenshot
      below.</para>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Select Users menu item</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Search by user name</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<para>You can search for specific user names in the user list by
      entering the name in the ‘filter by username’ field as shown
      above.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Define a new role</title>
			<para>As part of creating a username you are required to define the user
      role. Do so by clicking on the ‘user role’ appearing on the left side of
      the displayed screen.</para>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Create new user role</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<para>This will lead you to the Role Management page where you will have
      to click on <guibutton>Add new</guibutton> to create a new role.</para>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Add new user role</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<para>The following screen will open and here in the first text box you
      need to give Name of the Role such as Super User, Admin User, etc. The
      second text box called ‘Description’ gives more information about the
      type of User Role that is being created for e.g. State Admin User,
      District Data Entry. </para>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Role maintaience page</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<para>Next you will specify the particular dataset(s) that are to be
      made available to the particular role. You will also need to specify the
      type of ‘authority’ to be given to the particular user. For each of the
      three options namely Datasets, Reports and Authorities user can select
      multiple options from the scroll down menu provided against each field.
      A user can choose multiple options either by moving them
      one-by-one.</para>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Adding a dataset to a user role</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<para>You can also select multiple datasets individually by pressing the
      Ctrl key on the keyboard and clicking on individual datasets. </para>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Adding multiple datasets to user roles</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<para>Finally when you have entered the required fields click on
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> which is located on the lower part of the
      displayed screen. The desired user role and related authorization will
      be saved to the database, and can then be assigned to a particular user.
      </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Add New User</title>
			<para>Under particular user role there can be more than one user. To add
      new users go to the User options under the Maintenance module. </para>
			<screenshot>
				<screeninfo>Add new user</screeninfo>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="???"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
			<para>To add a new user, just follow these steps:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Click on the <guibutton>Add New</guibutton> button.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Enter New User details like <guilabel>User name</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Password</guilabel>, <guilabel>Confirm
          password</guilabel>, <guilabel>Surname</guilabel>, <guilabel>First
          name</guilabel> and <guilabel>Email</guilabel> in new user’s option
          tabs.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Click on <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button for confirmation of
          new user details and follow the user error while creation of new
          user.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The recently created new user can be seen in main’ User
          management Screen</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>You can edit (like password, surname….etc) and delete the
          details of new/old users by selecting corresponding User’s
          <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton>
          Buttons.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Click on <guibutton>Save</guibutton> tab after editing all
          details of a particular selected user.</para>
					<screenshot>
						<screeninfo>Add or edit users</screeninfo>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="???"/>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
					<screenshot>
						<screeninfo>User management screen</screeninfo>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="???"/>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Logging off of DHIS2</title>
		<para>Just click on the <guibutton>Log off</guibutton> button to exit the
    application. </para>
		<screenshot>
			<screeninfo>Logging off of DHIS 2</screeninfo>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="???"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
	</sect1>
</article>
