<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Support</title>
  <para>The DHIS 2 community uses a set of collaboration and coordination platforms for information and provision of downloads, documentation, development, source code,  functionality specifications, bug tracking. This chapter will describe this in more detail.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Home page: dhis2.org</title>
    <para>The DHIS 2 home page is found at <emphasis role="italic">http://dhis2.org</emphasis>The <emphasis role="italic">download</emphasis> page provides downloads for the DHIS 2 Live package, WAR files, the mobile client, a Debian package, the source code, sample databases and a tool for editing the application user interface translations. Please note that the current latest release will be maintained until the next is released and both the actual release and the latest build from the release branch are provided. We recommend that you check back regularly on the download page and update your online server with the latest build from the release branch. The build revision can be found under <emphasis role="italic">Help</emphasis> - <emphasis role="italic">About</emphasis> inside DHIS 2.</para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">documentation</emphasis> page provides installation instructions, user documentation, this implementation guide, presentations, Javadocs, changelog, roadmap and a guide for contributing to the documentation. The user documentation is focused on the practical aspects of using DHIS 2, such as how to create data elements and reports. This implementation guide is addressing the more high-level aspects of DHIS 2 implementation, database development and maintenance. The change log and roadmap sections provide links to the relevant pages in the Launchpad site described later.</para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">functionality</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">features</emphasis> pages give a brief overview with screenshots of the main functionalities and features of DHIS 2. A demo DHIS 2 application can be reached from the <emphasis role="italic">demo</emphasis> top menu link. These pages can be used when a quick introduction to the system must be given to various stakeholders.</para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">about</emphasis> page has information about the license under which DHIS 2 is released, how to sign up for the mailing lists, get access to the source code and more.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Collaboration platform: launchpad.net/dhis2</title>
    <para>DHIS 2 uses <emphasis role="italic">Launchpad</emphasis> as the main collaboration platform. The site can be accessed at <emphasis role="italic">http://lanchpad.net/dhis2</emphasis> Launchpad is used for source code hosting, functionality specifications, bug tracking and notifications. The <emphasis role="italic">Bazaar</emphasis> version control system is tightly integrated with Launchpad and is required for checking out the source code. </para>
    <para>The various source code branches including trunk and release branches can be browsed at <emphasis role="italic">http://code.launchpad.net/dhis2</emphasis> </para>
    <para>If you want to suggest new functionality to be implemented in DHIS 2 you can air your views on the developer mailing list and eventually write a specification, which is referred to as <emphasis role="italic">blueprints</emphasis> in Launchpad. The bueprint will be considered by the core development team and if accepted be assigned a developer, approver and release version. Blueprints can be browsed and added at <emphasis role="italic">http://blueprints.launchpad.net/dhis2</emphasis></para>
    <para>If you find a bug in DHIS 2 you can report it at Launchpad by navigating to <emphasis role="italic">http://bugs.launchpad.net/dhis2</emphasis> Your bug report will be investigated by the developer team and be given a status. If valid it will also be assigned to a developer and approver and eventually be fixed. Note that bugfixes are incorporated into the trunk and latest release branch - so more testing and feedback to the developer teams leads to higher quality of your software.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
