<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Utilizando la funcionalidad de Reporte</title>
  <section id="reporting_intro">
    <title>Funcionalidad de reporte en DHIS 2</title>
    <para>El módulo de reporte en DHIS 2 ofrece una variedad de alternativas. En esta sección veremos cómo utilizarlas para ver y analizar los datos. En otra sección se verá cómo configurar y poner en marcha las diversas herramientas de reporte.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reportes estándar:</emphasis> Los reportes estándar se construyen con cuadros de reportes, pero su diseño avanzado permite modificar su apariencia y estilo. Estos reportes pueden combinar múltiples cuadros y gráficas en el mismo informe, y se pueden visibilizar como reportes de 'un-click' que son muy fáciles de usar. Podemos descargar estos reportes en formato PDF, por lo que son ideales para imprimir así como para compartir y copiar offline.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reportes de Set de datos:</emphasis> Los reportes de set de datos son simplemente una forma amigable para ver e imprimir los formularios de entrada de datos con datos en bruto o datos agregados (por lugar o tiempo). El diseño utilizado en la entrada de datos es el mismo que se utiliza en estos reportes de set de datos. Aunque esto funcionará solo para los sets de datos que han pre-establecido un formulario de entrada de datos personalizado.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Panel de control (Dashboard):</emphasis> Es la manera más rápida de ver tus datos. El panel de control puede mostrar hasta cuatro gráficas actualizadas así como enlaces a tus reportes favoritos, cuadros de reportes, y vistas de mapas. Cada usuario puede configurar su propio panel personal de control.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Visualizador de datos:</emphasis> Permite formas flexibles de visualizar tus datos como gráficas y cuadros de datos. Es posible incluir aquí tantos indicadores y elementos de datos como deseemos. También podemos elegir entre muchos tipos de gráficas, tales como gráficos de barras, barras apiladas, lineales y diagramas de tarta. Podremos guardar las gráficas a su vez para cargarlas fácilmente en sesiones posteriores, y también podemos incluirlas en nuestro panel personal de control. Las gráficas se pueden descargar como imágenes o como PDF en nuestro computador local. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Tablas de reportes:</emphasis> Son una forma de mostrar los datos en tablas con múliples opciones de configuración, ya sea utilizando datos en bruto, agregados o indicadores. Estas tablas son utilizadas bien como fuente de datos para otros reportes más avanzados, para exportar la información a otros sistemas externos, o como un informe bruto. Se pueden exportar a diversos formatos: PDF, MS Excel, CSV y Jasper. Las tablas representan una manera muy dinámica, flexible y rápida de revisar los datos. Las tablas de reportes pueden configurarse con parámetros específicos para reutilizarlas en otros periodos o lugares.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reportes de distribución de unidades organizativas:</emphasis> Estos reportes se generan a partir del set grupo de unidades organizativas (orgunit) y permiten ver qué tipos (y qué cantidad) de establecimientos de salud están ubicados en un área determinada (en cualquier nivel de la jerarquía). Estos reportes se generan automáticamente y muestran la información tanto en tablas como gráficas, que pueden descargarse en PDF, MS Excel y CSV.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Resumen de la tasa de reportes:</emphasis> Estos reportes ofrecen una bonita vista de cuántos establecimientos han registrado sus datos para un periodo y set de datos determinados. Aquí podemos obtener la cuenta y el porcentaje de la tasa de reporte para uno o para todos los sets de datos.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Cuadros Excel pivot:</emphasis> Los cuadros Excel pivot son una forma potente de analizar nuestros datos y DHIS 2 enlaza directamente con los cuadros pivot, de manera que todos los datos quedan disponibles y actualizados en el fichero Excel. Esto puede ser una herramienta muy útil a usuarios que prefieren trabajar con los datos offline. Para actualizar los cuadros pivot locales necesitarás la herramienta <emphasis role="italic">myDatamart</emphasis> que conecta con el servidor online y descarga los datos restantes. Esta actualización normalmente se realiza una vez al mes cuando están disponibles los nuevos datos, pero no requiere una conexión permanente a Internet como sucede con otras herramientas de reporte (si estás conectado generalmente a un servidor DHIS 2 online).</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Cuadros Web pivot:</emphasis> La herramienta incluida en DHIS 2 de cuadro pivot es una herramienta web sencilla para mostrar los datos de indicadores por unidad organizativa y por periodo en una vista típica de cuadro pivot. Permite algunas manipulaciones básicas de pivotaje de las tablas. Es una manera rápida y fácil de mirar muchos valores de indicadores al mismo tiempo (por orgunit y/o periodo), pero que no tiene las mismas funcionalidades que los cuadros Excel pivot offline.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Sistema de Información Geográfica (SIG):</emphasis> Permite presentar y analizar tus datos utilizando mapas temáticos. Es posible ver tanto los elementos de datos como los indicadores y, suponiendo que sidponemos de las coordenadas de todas nuestras orgunits, podemos explorar la jerarquía y ver los mapas para todos los niveles desde polígonos de país a puntos de establecimientos de salud. Para más detalles revisa el capítulo específico sobre SIG. Toda la información de mapas está cargada en DHIS 2 y tan solo necesitas registrar las coordenadas de tus unidades organizativas y los mapas estarán disponibles inmediatamente.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="standard_reports">
    <title>Utilizando reportes estándar</title>
    <para>You access the available reports from the Services drop-down menu, by selecting Reports. In the report menu in the left bar, click Standard Report. A list of all pre-defined reports will appear in the main window. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Standard reports</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/standard_reports_ke.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>You run/view a report by clicking on the white and green arrow next to the report you want. You will then see a report parameter window where you must fill in the values needed for orgunit and/or reporting month, depending on what has been defined in the underlying report table(s). Click on &quot;Get Report&quot; when you are ready. The report will wither apper directly in your browser or be available as a .pdf file for download, depending on your browser settings for handling pdf files. You can save the file and keep it locally on your computer for later use. </para>
  </section>
  <section id="report_tables">
    <title>Utilizando tablas de reportes</title>
    <para>Report tables is a simple-to-use tool for creating tabular analysis. To run a report table first navigate to the list of available report tables in Services-&gt;Reports-&gt;Report Tables and the click on the Green and white  arrow (the first symbol in the operations list) next to the report table you want to view. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Report parameters:</emphasis> Most report tables have parameters, which means that you can filter which orgunits and/or periods you want in the report. This makes the reports much more reusable. When you run the report table a Report parameter window will open and ask the user to input values for the selected parameters. The possible parameters are Reporting Month and Organisation Unit, and either one of these or both will show in the window.    After selecting the values click on the Get Report button.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Parámetros de tablas de reporte</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/report_parameters.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Export/view options:</emphasis> When the report table is ready it will be displayed in a html view. The report table can be exported to pdf (for better printing and easier saving), excel, csv, and also to a standard report format (Jasper) with a nicer table and a chart shown in pdf, or as  a jasper design file for further improvements and changes to the report design before uploading it as a standard report (see the Creating standard reports section).</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Report table view</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/report_table_view.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para> </para>
  </section>
  <section id="dataset_reports">
    <title>Utilizando reportes de set de datos</title>
    <para>Dataset reports are printer friendly views of the data entry screen filled with either raw or aggregated data. These are only available for data sets that have custom data entry forms and not for default or section forms.</para>
    <para>You can access data set reports from the Report menu under Services.</para>
    <para>A Criteria window will appear where you fill in the details for your report:</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Dataset:</emphasis> The data set you want to display.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reporting period: </emphasis>The actual period you want data for. This can be aggregated as well as raw periods. This means that you can ask for a quarterly or annual report even though the data set is collected monthly. A data set&apos;s period type (collection frequency) is defined in data set maintenance. First select the period type (Monthly, Quarterly, Yearly etc.) in the drop down next to Prev and Next buttons, and then select one of the available periods from the dropdown list below. Use Prev and Next to jump one year back or forward.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Use data for selected unit only:</emphasis> Use this option if you want a report for an orgunit that has children, but only want the data collected directly for this unit and not the data collected by its children. If you want a typical aggregated report for an orgunit you do not want to tick this option.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reporting Organisation unit:</emphasis> Here you select the orgunit you want the report for. This can be at any level in the hierarchy as the data will be aggregated up to this level automatically (if you do not tick the option above).</para>
    <para>When you are done filling in the report criteria you click on &quot;Generate&quot;. The report will appear in html view in a printer-friendly format. Use print and save as functions in the browser to print or save (as html) the report.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="resource">
    <title>Utilizando la herramienta de Recursos</title>
    <para>The resource tool allows you to upload both files from your local computer to the DHIS server and to add links to other resources on the Internet through URLs. If you want to share the direct link to the DHIS resource you can right clik on the "view resource" button and copy the link address.</para>
    <para>The create a resource click on the &quot;Add new&quot; button. Enter a name for the resource, then choose between uploading a file or external URL. If you chose file upload click &quot;Choose file&quot; and select your file your local computer. If you chose URL enter the link to the resource on the Internet. Then click &quot;Save&quot;.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="data_visualizer">
    <title>Utilizando el visualizador de datos</title>
    <para>The data visualizer module can be accessed under &quot;Services&quot; in the top menu. See the chapter called &quot;Using data visualizer&quot; for a thorough explanation of this module.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="reporting_dashboard">
    <title>Utilizando el panel de control</title>
    <para>The dashboard is your first view into the data every time you log on to the system. Every user has its own dashboard, and a dashboard consists of 4 chart areas to the right and 3 short cut areas to the left.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Panel de control (Dashboard)</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/dashboard_kenya.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Customise shortcut areas:</emphasis> Each of the three short cut areas can hold a list of items from one of the following objects; Reports (standard), Documents, Data mart exports, Report tables, Map views, RSS Health. To add a new object type to a shortcut area click on the Insert link just above the area. Then to populate the list you need to add items one by one from the Services-&gt;Reports menus. From the various lists of reports, report tables, charts etc. you can add an item by clicking on the pie chart icon next to the item you want to add to the dashboard. </para>
    <para>E.g. to add your three favourite standard reports to the dashboard, first Insert Reports to one of the shortcut areas in the dashboard, then go to Services-&gt;Reports and click on Standard reports. From the list of standard reports you locate the reports you want and click on the pie chart icon next to each of the reports you want to add to the dashboard. When you go back to the dashboard you will see the three reports listed in the shortcut area where you inserted Reports.</para>
    <para>Use the Clear link above the shortcut area to empty an area. The Close link closes the insert menu without inserting a new object type.  </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Customise chart areas:</emphasis> There are four chart areas. To insert a chart simply click on insert and click on one of the charts in the list. Use Close to close the list without adding a new chart, and use Clear to empty a chart area. These charts will be updated every time you open the dashboard,  will automatically show data for the orgunit assigned to the current user, and will update the data when new periods are available. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Añadiendo gráficas al panel de control</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/dashboard_add_chart.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section id="reporting_reporting_rate_summary">
    <title>Utilizando el resumen de tasa de reporte</title>
    <para>Access the reporting rate summary from the Services-&gt;Reports menu. Reporting rate summaries will show how many datasets (forms) that have been submitted by organisation unit and period. You an use one of three different methods to calculate completeness; 1) based on complete button in data entry, 2) based on a set of defined compulsory data elements, or 3) based on the total registered data values for a dataset.  </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">To run the report do the following:</emphasis></para>
    <para>Select an orgunit from the tree.</para>
    <para>Select one of the completeness methods.</para>
    <para>Select all or one dataset (All will give you a report with all datasets for the seelcted orgunit. One dataset will give you a report with completeness for all the children of the selected orgunit.</para>
    <para>Select a period type and a period from the list of available periods for that period type. Move back/forward one year by using the Prev/Next buttons.</para>
    <para>Then the report will be shown automatically.</para>
    <para>Change any of the parameters above and the report will be updated automatically.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Completeness report</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/completeness_report.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section id="orgunit_distribution_reports">
    <title>Utilizando los reportes de distribución de unidades organizativas</title>
    <para>You can access the Orgunit Distribution reports from the left side menu in the Services-&gt;Reports module. </para>
    <para>Orgunit distribution reports are reports that show how the orgunits are distributed on various properties like type and ownership, and by geographical areas.</para>
    <para>The result can be presented in a table-based report or in a chart.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Running a report:</emphasis></para>
    <para>To run a report first select an orgunit in the upper left side orgunit tree. The report will be based on orgunits located under the selected orgunit. The select the orgunit group set that you want to use, typically these are Type, Ownership, Rural/Urban, but can be any user-defined orgunit group set. The you can click on either Get Report to get the table-based presentation or Get chart to get the same result in a chart.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Reporte de distribución de orgunit</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/orgunit_report.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section id="web_pivot_table">
    <title>Utilizando la tabla web pivot</title>
    <para>The web pivot table is a tool for displaying and pivoting indicator and data element data in an easy way. From the open data selection box start by selecting data type which can be data elements or indicators. Select the a group as a filter or leave it on &quot;All&quot;. Select start date, end date and period type to indicate which periods you want to include in the pivot table. Continue by selecting an organisation unit from the selection tree. The childeren at the level below the selected organisationn unit will be included in the pivot table. Then click &quot;Get data&quot;.</para>
    <para>After loading a pivot table you will see that indicators (or data elements) will appear on top as columns, while periods and organiation units are combined as rows. If you want to pivot the table click on the &quot;Pivot&quot; button and select new dimensions. These dimensions will be displayed as columns in the table when clicking &quot;Pivot&quot;.</para>
    <para>In the pivot table you can click on any cell in order to show a menu. From this menu you can choose to visualize the relevant indicator, org unit and period as various chart variants.</para>
    <para>To save the pivot table data to your local computer click the &quot;Download as excel&quot; button. The Excel workbook will show each period as a sheet.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="data_mart">
    <title>Utilizando la gestión con datamart</title>
    <para>The data mart is a set of tables in the DHIS database which is used by all reporting and analysis tools to retrieve data from. The data mart is populated based on the collected data. This management user interface allows you to controll that process of converting collected data into aggregated data and write to the data mart.</para>
    <para>The data mart management screen allows you to select period types, start date and end date which will control which periods are included in the data mart process. By default all data elements, indicators and organisation units will be included.</para>
    <para>The data mart process might take a long time and heavily utilize the resources of your server so make sure you start such processes at a feasible time in production environments. Data mart processes can be scheduled as regular tasks in the data administration module.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
