<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml
/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<glossary>
  <glossaryinfo>
    <editor>
      <firstname>Jason</firstname>
      <surname>Pickering</surname>
    </editor>
    <title>DHIS2 Glossary</title>
    <releaseinfo>2.0.3</releaseinfo>
  </glossaryinfo>
  <title>DHIS 2 Glossary</title>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>A</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Aggregation</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>In the context of DHIS2, aggregation refers to how data elements are combined within a particular hierarchical relationship. As an example, all the health facilities in a particular district would contribute to the total value for the particular district in question. Different aggregation operators are supported within DHIS2, such as SUM, AVERAGE, and COUNT.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm baseform="aggregateData">Aggregate data</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>In the context of DHIS2, aggregate data refers to either data elements or indicators that have been derived from other hierarchical data sources. For instance, aggreagte facility data would result from the aggregate totals of all patients that have attended that facility for a particular service. Aggregate district data would result from the aggregate totals of all facilities contained with a particular district.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>C</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Category</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Categories are used to disaggreate data elements. As an example, the data element &quot;Number of confirmed cases of malaria&quot; could be disaggregated into an &quot;Age&quot; category, consisting of category options of &quot;Under 1&quot;, 1-5&quot; and &quot;Over 5&quot;. Category options are used during data entry to simplify the number of data elements that need to be created. During analysis of data, categories function essentially as dimensions. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Category option</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Category options are atomic elements that are grouped into cagtegories. Category options are used during data entry to disaggregate data elements into atomic pieces of information. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>D</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Data exchange format</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>In the context of DHIS2, the &quot;data exchange format&quot; refers to a XML schema that enables the transportation of data and metadata between disconnected DHIS instances, as well as between different applications that suppor the DXF schema. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Datamart</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A set of database tables in DHIS2 that contians processed data elements and indicator values that is generated based on aggregation rules and calculated data element and indicator formular. Datamart tables are used for analysis  and report production. Typically, users should not work directly with unaggregated data values, but rather with values that have resulted from a datamart export for analysis. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Data element</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A data element is the fundemental building block of DHIS2. It is an atomic unit of data with well-defined meaning. Essentially it is a data value that has been actually observed or recorded which is further characterized by a number of dimensions. As an example the data element &quot;Number of fully immunized children&quot; would refer to the number of children that received this particular service. Data elements are always linked to a period as as well as an organizational unit. They optionally may be linked to other dimensions. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Dimension</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>A dimension is used to categorize data elements during analysis. Dimensions provide a mechanism to group and filter data based on common characteristics. Typically, related data elements may be aggregated or filtered during analysis with the use of dimensions. Dimensions may be a member of a hierarchy. For instance the &quot;Period&quot; dimension may be broken down into &quot;Day-&gt;Month-&gt;Quarter-&gt;Year&quot;. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>DXF</glossterm>
      <glosssee> Data exchange format</glosssee>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
<!-- <glossdiv>
    <title>E</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>F</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>G</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>E</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>F</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>G</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>H</title>
  </glossdiv> -->  <glossdiv>
    <title>H</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Health management information system</glossterm>
      <abbrev>HMIS</abbrev>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Typically, an electronic database system that is used to record aggregated data on service delivery, disease incidence, human resource data and other information used to evaluate the performance of delivery of health services. Typically, an HMIS does not contain the highly detailed data of electronic medical record systems or individual patient data. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>I</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Indicator</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The divisor of an indicator. Can be composed of multiple data elements with the use of an indicator formula.<equation>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/indicator.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </equation></para>
        <para>This is obviously a very generalized example. The numerator and indicator themselves can be composed of various data elements, factors, and the four basic operands (addition, multiplication, division and subtraction). </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
<!--<title>J</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>K</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>L</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>M</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv> -->    <title>N</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Numerator</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>The dividend of a indicator. Can be composed of multiple data elements and factors with the use of indicator formulas.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>O</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Organisational unit</glossterm>
      <abbrev>orgunit</abbrev>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Typically, an orgunit is a unit within a geographical hierarchy. As an example, in the United States, &quot;Georgia&quot; would be considered an orgunit with in the orgunit level of &quot;State&quot;. Organizational units can also represent units, such as wards within a hospital, withn a single geographical location. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Organisational unit level</glossterm>
      <abbrev>Orgunit level</abbrev>
      <glossdef>
        <para>Refers to a level within an organizational hierarchy. Typically, countries are administered at different levels, such as 1) Country 2) States 3) Counties 4) Health facilities. In the context of DHIS2, health facilities typically are the lowest orgunit level. Data is aggregated upwards from the lowest orgunit level to the highest. </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
<!--<glossdiv>
    <title>P</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>Q</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>R</title>
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Report table</glossterm>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>S</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>T</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>U</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>W</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>X</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>Y</title>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>Z</title>
  </glossdiv> --></glossary>
